alright let's get started thank you
everyone for coming to our talk inside
Katy native serving I am Andrew Chen I'm
a program manager and a technical writer
and with me is Dominick tour now a
principal engineer so for the past year
we've been working together to try to
figure out why kubernetes is so hard to
understand when I started as a Technical
Writer over two years ago I was
bombarded with terms such as control
plane data plane kubernetes object
controller ingress you know and the list
goes on and on all right
I had at my disposal all of the
committee's documentation yet I still
lacked a big picture understanding of
how everything worked together was it
because I didn't read all the source
code who even has the time to do that
and do you even believe that it's
possible to understand a software system
without examining its source code
well Dominic showed me that there is
another way it's called systems modeling
so for the past year we've been writing
blog posts using formal and conceptual
models to help people better understand
how kubernetes works so that they may
reason about its behavior with
confidence so we're applying this
methodology now to K native serving so
that you may understand K native better
and what makes this presentation a
little different than others you may see
is that we're not going to show you
source code we're not going to show you
a console we're not going to do a demo
we're just going to be showing you
systems models and yet you should still
be able to walk away today with the
crystal clear understanding of how cane
ativ serving works and without further
delay here is dominic turnout to talk
about cane and is serving thanks Angela
thank you if you heard of K native
before you probably heard that K native
is a kubernetes extension designed to
manage service applications this
statement about K native is correct
however this statement does not describe
K native well k native is a kubernetes
extension a kubernetes extension is a
collection of custom controllers and
custom resource definitions that an
ember that enable new use cases on top
of kubernetes if you hear members of the
kubernetes community safe kubernetes is
a platform to build a platform they're
talking about kubernetes extensions Kay
native is in fact a collection of three
kubernetes extensions candidate build k
native serving and k native eventing in
combination
k native is not just a server list
extension but it is a zero operations
extension for reactive micro service
applications hosted on kubernetes zero
ops also called no ops or more formally
operation automation refers to the fact
that most or all tasks which are
required to operate an application are
performed by the system not performed by
the developer today we will discuss K
native serving in particular we will
discuss two aspects canada serving as a
zero operations extension for the
lifecycle management of reactive micro
services and k native serving as a
server list extension to understand the
benefits of canada serving we need to
shift our point of view from an
architectural perspective to an
operational perspective from an
architectural perspective a reactive
micro service is an individual stateless
component the processes individual
requests micro services are located
behind the Gateway
the Gateway is responsible for traffic
management the Gateway acts as a reverse
proxy routing a request from a service
consumer to the correct service provider
from an operational perspective for each
micro service there exists at least one
version also called revision in order to
release the initial revision of a
service you have to perform two steps
first you have to deploy the revision to
deploy a revision you have to create a
workload specification a workload
specification is a set of resources that
specify how to process requests and by
the way if you are thinking workload
specification that sounds like pod
specification in essence you are correct
second you have to roll out the revision
to roll out a revision you have to
create a traffic split specification a
traffic split specification is a set of
resources that specify how to route
requests and now if you are thinking
traffic split specification that sounds
like ingress specification again in
essence you are correct here all traffic
splits are probabilistic traffic splits
in order to release the next revision of
a service you have to repeat these steps
first you have to deploy the new
revision second you have to roll out the
revision with a probabilistic traffic
split you have two options to do a
rollout you may choose an immediate
rollout or you may choose a gradual
rollout to perform an immediate rollout
you have to update the traffic split
specification only once shifting all
requests from the current to the next
revision in an instant
to perform a gradual rollout you have to
update the traffic split specification
multiple times shifting all requests
from the current to the next revision
over a period of time
as an operator of a micro service you
are locked in an endless tedious cycle
of deployments and rollouts and if this
dire situation does not ask for
automation nothing else does but let's
not get ahead of ourselves
so far we talked about micro services
but we did not talk about kubernetes and
we did not talk about Canada's yet well
let's talk about kubernetes first
kubernetes is a prominent platform for
hosting micro services kubernetes
provides an extensive set of very
rounded abstractions to compose a micro
service however kubernetes does not
provide a dedicated abstraction for a
micro service simply put kubernetes
gives us everything we need but we have
to piece everything together ourselves
and there are many options to choose
from turns out the most prominent is
also the most basic pattern here one
micro service is represented by
composing four kinds of objects a
kubernetes deployment a kubernetes
horizontal pod autoscaler
a kubernetes service and o kubernetes
ingress deployment and HP a represent
the workload specification service and
ingress represent the traffic split
specification in order to release the
initial revision the developer has to
create a deployment object a horizontal
port or a scalar object a service object
and an ingress object in order to
release a subsequent revision the
developer has to update the deployment
object again the basic pattern from an
actions point of view in order to
release the initial revision of a micro
service the developer has to create a
deployment object a horizontal port
order scalar object an ingress object
and a service object in order to release
a subsequent
vision the developer has to update the
deployment object this pattern is simple
to implement and simple to operate
however the developer has limited
control over the rollout that is limited
control over the traffic split
specification this diagram illustrates
in mechanics of the traffic split
specification of the basic pattern here
we have one microservice that is
currently in rollout that is traffic is
shifted from deployment number one
replica set number one to deployment
number one replica set number two
kubernetes ingress directs all requests
that are bound to one micro service to
one kubernetes service in turn the
kubernetes service directs request to
matching parts with equal probability in
summary traffic split is implicit in
effect determined solely by the
kubernetes service and dependent on the
number of ports per replica set for
example here if there are three parts in
replica set number one and three parts
in replica set number two the resulting
traffic split is 50/50 to grant the
developer full control over the traffic
split specification a more advanced
pattern emerged here again one micro
service is represented by composing four
different kinds of objects a kubernetes
deployment a kubernetes horizontal pod
autoscaler
a kubernetes service and an sto virtual
service deployment and HP a represent
the workload specification service and
virtual service represent the traffic
split specification in order to release
the initial revision the developer has
to create a deployment object a
horizontal port autoscaler object a
service object and an easier virtual
service object in order to release a
subsequent revision the developer has to
create a new deployment object
a new horizontal pod or a scalar object
and a new service object and has to
update the existing sto virtual service
object again the advance pattern from an
actions point of view in order to
release the initial revision of a micro
service the developer has to create a
deployment object a horizontal port or a
scalar object a service object and an
sto virtual service object in order to
release a subsequent revision the
developer has to create a new deployment
object a new horizontal port or the
scalar object a new service object and
has to update the existing is your
virtual service object in case of an
immediate rollout the developer has to
update the ISTE of virtual service only
once in case of a gradual rollout the
developer has to update the ischial
virtual service multiple times this
pattern is still simple to implement but
way more involved to operate however the
developer has full control over the
rollout that is full control over the
traffic split specification this diagram
illustrates the mechanics of the traffic
split specification of the advanced
pattern here we have one micro service
that is currently in rollout that is
traffic is split from I'm sorry traffic
is shifted from deployment number one
replica set number one to deployment
number two replica set number one is to
virtual service directs all requests
that are bound to one micro service to a
configurable set of kubernetes services
in turn the kubernetes service directs
request to matching parts with equal
probability
in summary traffic split is explicit in
fact determined solely by the ISTE of
virtual service so far we had good news
and we have bad news the good news
kubernetes is a convenient choice to
implement micro service applications the
bad news kubernetes is not a convenient
choice to operate micro service
applications you have to perform an
involved with edit of sequence of
steps for the initial release in every
subsequent release well meet K native
serving finally K native serving
automates the sequence of steps for the
initial release and every subsequent
release of your microservice K native
provides a custom resource definition
the K native service object that
implements the advanced pattern and
automates its operations when you create
a K native service object K native
automatically creates an initial
deployment the initial autoscaler
the initial service and the sto virtual
service for you please note that K
native replaces the horizontal part
autoscaler with a K native pod
autoscaler the kubernetes horizontal pod
autoscaler scales instances based on
metrics like CPU utilization or memory
utilization the K native pod autoscaler
scales instances based on in-flight
request count in addition the k p8 can
scale from n to 0 we will go into more
detail in the next section of the
presentation when you update a K native
service object K native automatically
creates the next deployment the next
autoscaler and the next service and
updates is to virtual service for you in
conclusion from an actions point of view
K native reduces the operational burden
on the developer in order to release the
initial revision of a micro service the
developer simply has to create a K
native serving object in turn can ativ
automatically creates a required set of
objects
in order to release this subsequent
revision the developer simply has to
update the tentative serving object and
in turn Canada automatically creates and
updates a required set of objects still
in case traffic is shifted immediately
the developer updates the key native
service once in case traffic is shifted
gradually the developer updates the key
native service multiple times let's take
a closer look at the mechanics of
Canada's AK a native service object
combines the workload and traffic split
specification of your micro service
ultimately the workload specification is
your part specification specifying the
image of your service the traffic split
specification is the ISTE of virtual
service specification specifying one
revision or two revisions with the
traffic split as your traffic target for
each K native service there exists
exactly one K native configuration when
the service object is created a
configuration object will be created
with the services initial workload
specification when the workload
specification of the service object is
updated the configuration will be
updated with the services new workload
specification for each K native
configuration there exists at least one
K native revision when the configuration
object is created a revision object is
created with the configurations initial
workload specification when the
configuration object is updated a new
revision object will be created with the
configurations new workload
specification each revision results in a
deployment a K native port autoscaler
and a service in addition for each K
native service there exists a K native
route when the service object is created
a route object will be created with the
services traffic split specification
when the traffic split specification of
the service object is updated the route
object will be updated with
services new traffic split specification
and ultimately a route results in an sto
virtual service let's take a closer look
at the workload specification of your
service as stated the workload
specification is a part specification
you have to specify one image called the
user container image that contains your
application or more specifically that
contains a revision of your application
your application must be an HTTP
application processing HTTP requests
kay native injects another image into
the pot specification on creation of the
deployment called the cue container
image the cue container is a reverse
proxy to the user container the cue
container intercepts all requests to the
user container and is responsible for
collecting and reporting statistics
namely the in-flight request count to
the autoscaler again we will go into
more detail in the next section of the
presentation so to release the initial
revision of a micro service the
developer creates a que native service
object with an initial workload and an
initial traffic split specification in
turn can aid of creates a Canadian
configuration object with the workload
specification in turn can ativ creates a
candidate revision object with the
workload specification in turn que
native creates a deployment object with
the workload specification a service and
make a native autoscaler additionally
que native creates a Canada Froude
object with the initial traffic split
specification in turn can aid of creates
an SEO virtual service with the traffic
split specification at this point the
initial revision is released and
receiving 100% of requests to release
the next revision of a micro service the
developer updates the kinetic service
object here with an updated workload and
an updated traffic split specification
Canada updates a configuration object
and in turn creates a new revision
object additionally que native updates a
route object and in turn updates a
virtual service at this point the next
revision is deployed and receiving 100%
of requests so we could stop here and
enjoy the sweet benefits of operation
automation however Canada has one more
trick up its sleeve que native serving
is able to scale a revision from n to
zero an approach that is frequently
called serve
as computing in a traditional
environment resources must be acquired
before a request can be received simply
put in kubernetes terms if your pod is
not up and running yet your application
cannot receive requests in a service
environment resources may be acquired
after a request has been received in
kubernetes terms even if your pod is not
up and running yet your application may
already receive requests typical
implementations of a service environment
do not release resources after
processing a request immediately instead
once acquired resources are held in
anticipation of additional requests for
some period of time code path refers to
the situation where receiving a request
and processing a request are separated
by acquiring resources hot path refers
to the situation where receiving a
request and processing a request are not
separated by acquiring resources but how
does key native scale from n20 and if
there is no part who is listening to
your requests meet the key native
serving activator for this walkthrough I
assume one key native service service
number one to revisions revision number
one in revision number two and that the
service is currently in roll out that is
traffic is split between revisions
currently both revision number one and
revision number two are scale it to zero
now this is a fun part
when a request enters the system the
Gateway inspects a request determines
the service and selects a revision to
process the request here I assume the
Gateway selects revision number one
since no instance of revision number one
is running requests to revision number
one are on a code path the Gateway is
configured to forward the request to the
activator the activator buffers the
original request and sends a request to
the autoscaler to scale revision number
one the autoscaler sends a request to
kubernetes to increase the replicas
count of the deployment object
corresponding to revision number one
kubernetes creates a pot object and
executes the queue and user container
therefore scaling from zero to one the
Gateway is configured to forward future
requests for revision number one
directly to a part of that revision by
passing the activator the activator
forwards a buffered original request of
the queue container the queue container
forwards the original request to the
user container for processing in
addition the queue container sends a
request to the autoscaler to increase
the in-flight request count omitted in
this animation when the response of the
user container is returned to the caller
the queue container sends another
request to the autoscaler to decrease
the in-flight request count now to do
this all over again when a new request
enters the system the Gateway inspects a
request determines the service and
selects a revision to process the
request here I assume the gateway
selects revision number one again since
an instance of revision number
is running requests to revision number
one are on a hot path the Gateway is
configured to forward requests for
revision number one directly to a part
of that revision bypassing the activator
again the queue container forwards to
originally request to the user container
for processing again the queue container
sends a request to the autoscaler to
increase in flight request count if the
number of in-flight requests passes a
configurable threshold the autoscaler
sends a request to kubernetes to
increase the replica count of the
deployment object corresponding to
revision number one kubernetes creates
additional pods and execute the queue
and you can use a container here scaling
from one to three ultimately the same
process takes place for revision number
two in summary que native is a zero
operations extension for reactive micro
service applications on kubernetes
within canada 'the que native serving is
a zero operations extension for the
lifecycle management of reactive micro
service applications on kubernetes k
native serving provides a dedicated
abstraction for a micro service and
automates its operation that is it
automates deployment and rollout
additionally k native serving is a
service extension k native serving is
able to scale a micro service from n to
zero instances in response to service
requests thank you very much with that I
hand back to Andrew
thank you thanks Dominic that was great
so if you like how Dominic explained K
native serving not just the content
please come and talk to us after the
presentation we'd love to hear your
feedback and I think we have some time
for some questions just one second for
the microphone to arrive I won't ask if
I run application in cognitive service
and which component to ensures that my
applications is a high available because
my application perhaps you know has some
trouble and it can be broke down in the
Canadian Canadian service container so I
should I develop another application to
fix these to fix this problem or the
Canadian who has a internal mechanism to
have me to do that Canada actually does
not address this problem can it it falls
back on to kubernetes because a que
native service or more specifically a
revision of ack a native service
ultimately translates into a deployment
so from there on it inherits all the
properties that the deployment exposes
and since kubernetes deployment
controller makes sure or at least tries
as much as you can to bring up as many
pots as specified in the replicas count
k native falls back on to the
availability guarantees of kubernetes
but the problem the the point stands and
is correct kubernetes deployment does
not give you a guarantee that it can
scale yes to this point it just gives
you the guarantee it will keep trying k
native does the same thing
yep because you know our applications
always was deployed deployed in our
production environment through
deployment workload and the stiff side
workload but our application is a
database system so there are so many
unstable problems will be happened in
the container so the Canadian stories is
very convenient - for us if we want to
provide as a database service to our
customers yeah
actually in that case so Canada Canada
serving is specifically designed for
reactive micro services that is
stateless components that process HTTP
requests if a database is running in
your container then ke native serving is
not the choice for you it's not a
solution okay thank you you're welcome
well thank you I'm a little bit confused
with the concept with the cold path and
how paths also so here confused about
like say it seems that a native can
sense first sense that there whether
there is a rollout going on and then to
put it and to trigger that with a cue
container and then is that means that
the to wait to finish that rollout and
intuitive scaling so I mean like so if I
see I mean the rollout and scaling will
they happens simultaneously or a little
bit confused about that thank you I see
so actually the cue container is not
involved in cold path or hot path the
only component that is involved in cold
path or hot path is the gateway and the
activator the ingress gateway is if
there is no no pod running the ingress
gateway is configured to forward a
request to the activator and then the
activator will talk to the autoscaler to
scale up in the future after just one
second
in the future after a pot has been
acquired the gateway is reconfigured we
are the ISTE of virtual service to then
direct requests directly to the pot so
this situation now or actually the blue
line you can think of the blue line as
the hot path and the queue container
within the pot its sole responsibility
is to count statistics so it every time
it receives the requests it increases in
flight requests count and every time it
returns a response it decreases in
flight requests come in super helpful
please me have one question over there
thank you
there's some in the back
hi the Gateway is configured to route
certain requests to service one revision
one and certain to say revision 2 while
the rollout is happening right so now in
the cold path we had the first request
come to revision one and your user
container came up and now it's directly
going to the queue container off so this
one revision one now say a request comes
where the Gateway has to route it to
revision 2 but the cold path is still
enable there so to reduce the response
time does it route it to so revision 1
meanwhile no no no now not to my
knowledge
I mean to do please do not quote me on
that but I am 99% sure no it does not
right so if we wish for us to have SLA
of 99 like triple nine or something and
have lower response times can we
configure it to do that though I do not
think that this is a possibility no it's
a it's a strictly probabilistic traffic
split that does not take any other
environmental conditions into account
understand alright thank you very much
all right I got I got the final warning
so I'm not sure I can take more
questions up here on stage but please do
not hesitate come find us we're gonna
hang out right in front of this room and
are happy to answer any more questions
thank you very much thanks for coming
[Applause]