hey everybody welcome to today's online
training intro to k3s we have quite a
few people joining the line so I just
want to take a moment while while people
are joining to let everybody know that
this session is being recorded we'll go
about an hour we have an hour and a half
scheduled we have plenty of time for Q&A
and all that but if you do need a drop
don't worry about it
this session is being recorded and we
will send you the recording and the
slides after the training so Wow now
that people would join line go ahead and
get us started we have a lot to cover
just as a way of introduction my name is
Matthew Shearer mark the marketing
manager here and sure I help host a lot
of these training sessions we have more
on the calendar I'll talk about that in
a bit
and I also included my contact info
email Matthew at Rancho comm and on the
ranch for user slack I am at Matthew
please reach out to me I'm happy to be
your point of contact if you're looking
for resources you have questions or you
know the recording doesn't get your way
or something like that and I'd also love
to hear from you if you are using
rancher if you are using any of the
software if you're having trouble or
you're doing something really cool we
would so love to hear your stories and
know what what you guys are all doing
with this stuff since it is open source
and it is just out there in the wild so
so feel free to reach out to me I'd love
to chat but the person who's really
doing the heavy lifting today is going
to be Mark Abraham's I feel that
engineer mark are you there
okay I'm here hello everybody I'll let
mark introduce himself a little bit more
as we get going just a couple other
ground keeping items sort of house rules
you know this is a k3s intro training we
are trying to keep this to an hour you
know but we can go along if need be we
do our absolute best to respond to every
single question that you all may have if
for whatever reason you want your
question to be private just let us know
GoToWebinar has a cool a chat feature so
just enter your question in the chat
and I will see them will take me a
couple pauses here and there during the
training for questions then leave a lot
of room and time at the end for just
extended Q&A we oh I like I said at the
beginning this session is recorded it
will be posted on YouTube we have a ton
of other training sessions on YouTube as
well everything is there for you all to
enjoy so check so do check that out if
for whatever reason you don't see it on
your email or you want to look up a
different topic and more resources
probably a lot of you are already using
these but if you're not I highly
recommend you join it's all totally free
our ranch or user slack so slack ranch I
owe thousands of members hundreds of
people every day asking and answering
questions
our engineers are on there too checking
those out and escalating questions
internally as needed there is a k3s
channel just pound k3s specifically for
k3s discussion and then longer form
announcements and posts are on our
forums so forums rancher comm again just
just great free resources for the
community and finally there are a lot of
other upcoming classes and trainings
that we offer if you are brand new to
rancher I highly recommend tomorrow's
session it is free it is just live and
there'll be live Q&A and that is on an
intro to kubernetes Rancher and then
every month we do an online meet the up
work sort of a whole community gets
together there you know usually hundreds
of people on and just tons of questions
we talk about the latest and greatest in
rancher
you know and what's going on around the
cloud native landscape so that's January
22nd please check that out and then
after that the next week we'll just
continue to focus on security with a
master class by one of our principal
software engineers Prachi it should be
really good so check all those out this
slide this this deck will be sent to you
all so you'll have the links and you can
you can sign up as what all right now
that all of that is out of the way I'm
gonna pass this over to you mark make
you the presenter so that you can
is going great all right I'm making you
presenter all right let's see can you
see my interest your slide you're good
to go okay so for today's masterclass
we're going to do an intro to k3s I'll
go over some of the fundamentals of k3s
we'll have a demo of k3s on a single
node and then we'll get into high
availability and I'll do an H a a demo
of kts in H a mode as well and then I'll
take some time to talk about use cases
now if we have time we'll get to the
multi cluster management and we can view
you know view clusters multiple clusters
in us from a single pane of glass that
is ranch or I will I'll do that if we
have time again my name is Mark Abrams
and I'm a field engineer with rancher
labs
I have been with rancher for almost a
year and a half now doing doing field
work work with a lot of different
customers in all areas all all areas of
business get to learn lots of
interesting things that people are doing
with it trying to do with it
out in the community I present various
events last year I was at the open
source summit and that the the armed
tech con as well as some local regional
stuff as well so with that let's jump
right into some of the fundamentals of
k3s and let's talk about let's start
with the kubernetes architecture right
because k3s is lightweight kubernetes so
we have to look at what what is
kubernetes and how did we get to k3s
this is a diagram that that comes right
off of the kubernetes i/o site and it
shows that
component parts of kubernetes and and
what it takes to run kubernetes
basically breaking it up into what
kubernetes caused masters and the nodes
the masters typically have the control
plane and the data plane you may have
seen installations where these are even
separated out into different different
worker into different servers but this
is the general architecture that
kubernetes shares with us so the you
know the the components here are really
I think everybody knows these but I'll
just go through them real quick because
the this is sort of what what really
gets interesting
with k3s is how k3s manages what we did
with these component parts so the API
server of course is the front-end for
the control plane @cd is the datastore
for the cluster the coop scheduler
selects nodes for newly created pods to
run on so based on hardware software
policy constraints the scheduler is
going to figure out where to put the
pods the controller manager is actually
a single process of multiple controllers
so it's the default controllers that you
get with kubernetes you can of course
create your own as well and then the
cloud controller manager is actually
cloud specific it's loud provider
specific control loops that are that are
in the cloud controller manager and then
over on the right-hand side you see the
node components and that includes the
kulit where the which is basically a
node agent that ensures that containers
run inside a pod so so if you know
making sure the pod has all the
containers it should have the pot of
course is not on this picture but it's
the smallest appliable unit that can be
created and managed in kubernetes and
then there's the coop proxy which
basically maintains the network rules on
the node implementing a part of the
kubernetes service concept as you know
you can also create you know CNI a
software-defined network you can add
that on as well and create the pod
networks through that and then of course
what you don't see here is the container
runtime underneath all of these things
the Kubla makuu proxy we require some
sort of a container runtime and the
defaults with kubernetes with many
kubernetes installations as docker but
it's not required so with that let's
let's take a look at the k3s
architecture which has many of the same
components but it's it's different in a
lot of ways
now we break out these component parts
into the k3s server and the k3s agent
these are similar to the master and the
node that the kubernetes refers to and
you can see that there are many of the
same component parts we have the API
server the scheduler the controller
manager and and then and that's in the
caitria server you'll notice that CD is
not on the server so that's something
we'll talk about and then on the agent
on those nodes you'll notice that we've
got the Kubla the coop proxy and a
container run time we're using container
D here so let's talk about the so so
each of these can run in their own
process and that's something a little
bit different than we have in the
straight-up kubernetes so in in whoops
let's go back one page so in kubernetes
we we run each of these things in
independent processes that Kubb api
server the code scheduler the couplet
and so k3s is doing something different
here because it's running this single
process that runs all those components
in fact you can run a single node k3s
that has both a server and agent
component
combined together and these two
processes actually will be run in a
single process so so what did we do to
get kubernetes into such a small
footprint one of the things is we
removed the the dependency on EDD and
you can see that here where we have
sequel Lite so the dependency on on at
CD allowed us to run a single node by
having a sequel database instead but we
did some other things and I'll talk
about those later why the sequel works
in this scenario and and how we did it
in addition so so out of the box are the
initial version of lightweight
kubernetes k3s had a low memory
footprint could run in less than 512 Meg
of RAM all the components were in a
single binary we deployed it with us
multiple architectures it was important
based on the landscape and the interest
for a lightweight kubernetes that we
were deploying to both arm d7 and rb8
and as well as x86 and and we deployed
out of the box with an ingress
controller we removed the dependency on
docker as you saw we have container D
instead of docker and then we removed
the dependency on Etsy D which is where
we we put in the sequel Lite instead of
at CD overall we removed about three
million lines probably about a million
lines of code and that included entry
storage providers entry cloud providers
alpha features legacy and non default
features and so part of how we got here
is we were working on another project
and and in that project the developer
was was kind of frustrated with the
complexity of kubernetes and really just
wanted
the kubernetes the the fundamentals
right he wasn't he didn't need cloud
providers he didn't need storage
providers out of the box and those
things are in the source tree but
initially we stripped those out so I'm
going to show you now what this looks
like when we run it just as a sync node
so so I'm just going to download the
binary we'll run it it's actually kind
of boring it's very simple so let's see
we're gonna we're going to do curl
command and we'll get go ahead and get
this from from the web and actually I
can show you let's see so this is the
case vs site on github and if you go
into the releases page you can see that
version 1.1 seven release is the latest
release right and if we scroll down here
you can see that we've released it for
Army chaff that's arm v7 arm eight v8 as
well as the amd64 and the the x86
packages essentially which is this is
the x86 package right here k3f so i'm
gonna run this let's take a look at what
is this so everything I'm running today
is arch 64 it's it's all a bunch of
raspberry PI's I have so this is a PI 4
B+ and you can see it
it's our 64 so it's running 64-bit Linux
and if we do cat at CE OS releases you
can see I'm running Debian Buster
essentially this is a raspbian version
buster okay so I am going to run this
command it's a curl command and I'm
going to just basically download that's
the link if we if we go here and we you
know get get the link address this is
what it'll be I've added so the the L
command says follow links so if there
were any 301 that redirect me to
someplace else to download it that'll
take me there
the - oh says download it as k3s so
before I do that me oh and I'm going to
turn on my key caster so you can see
what Keys I'm hating as we go through
here so so you can see this is just a
straight up it's actually a Raspberry Pi
desktop it's not even light I've got a
TFT display attached to this thing and
so I have nothing here and we'll put
this back in and we'll just download k3s
pull that down I'm
why key caster is not casting right now
I don't see the keys coming up okay so
we have it great so now I'm going to
[Music]
write so I'm going to look at it's it's
not an executable so I'm going to change
the mode to executable and then we're
going to run it using sudo we'll run the
server there are ton of options that you
can run will create a log a log file of
the output and will run in a background
mode so that's now running and now I can
run k3s coop CTL get node run any cube
CTL commands and it might take a minute
for that to come up there we go so I
have a single node and it's kids like
keys are not what's going on here
I seem to have lost access to that
device obvious on my commands are not
kidding entered so fortunately we can
see that we did a coop CTL get node and
it works so let's go back and take a
look at where we're going to go next so
that that was like I said it's very
simple you might be saying to yourself
well why would I do that instead of
running micro Cades or mini Kubb or
something like that and the reason is
that
well k3s is designed for production we
our intention was to build this as
production kubernetes micro Cades and
mini Kubb are really designed for the
developer you can run a single node
kubernetes cluster which is basically
what we just did but we want to go
beyond that and I could I could connect
nodes to that cluster that I just stood
up on that single node I could attach
worker nodes but we might even want
a highly available you know at CD type
data store it won't be at CD in the kts
case although it could be we allow that
too so we're very flexible so what we
did when we did GA our version 1 release
was around coop con last year and it had
all the things that we just talked about
the low memory footprint the multi
architecture distribution but we added
out-of-the-box helm controller so you
can drop in into a directory with the
deployment you can drop in a help chart
and it'll automatically install that
chart we deployed a service load
balancer as I said we took out some of
the cloud entry cloud provider stuff but
the really important thing here was you
know load balancing that that was what
was that was the key piece and then the
other thing was the adding a local
storage provider so you can actually set
up local storage it actually by default
sets up a local storage provider in
every node you can disable that all
these things can be disabled by the you
know if you don't want them by default
but the local storage provider gives you
local storage out-of-the-box so you have
PVCs they can pick up the default volume
from local storage obviously you need a
pretty good sized system to do that we
also expanded the datastore option so we
had embedded
sequel Lite and that's how we were able
to get rid of Etsy and get rid of the
need for 3 nodes but we of course wanted
to have something highly available what
we really did was it was a process so so
we we weren't just getting rid of SED we
were remapping the interface for ED CD
and remapping it to sequel back-end so
we built something called kind ki and he
kind is not at CD and we we map that
interface the API to other data
so in theory kind could be mapped to any
data store and now you have that Etsy D
interface for kubernetes which
kubernetes requires but instead of
talking to you in that CD data store is
talking to a sequel datastore and in
doing that we were then able to slip in
any external database as the backend we
started with my sequel and Postgres
sequel so we'll take a look today with
my sequel as an external datastore for H
a and then we added some documentation
around how to do air-gap installation so
as well as giving you the capability
through basically text files that
contain the content of what needs to be
pulled down into your air-gap pre polled
so that when you actually do the
installation the images are available
and there so let's take a look let's
move on to what the architecture looks
like with the high availability mode
you've seen this slide this is this is
the slide I showed you before with
sequel Lite but then when we went into
an H a version we actually said okay
well let's let's pull that external
sequel database out everything else
stays the same one thing that I forgot
to mention here is this tunnel proxy so
kubernetes that the KU proxy talks to
the API server and you could have your
gonna have an external client to talk to
the API server as well but the when the
coup proxy talks to it they actually use
a number of ports for communication in a
pure kubernetes cluster and so what we
did is we built this tunnel proxy so
that there's this initial one
directional communication from the KU
proxy to the API server once the so the
KU proxy reaches out through this tunnel
proxy proxy to API server once the
communication is established they can
talk
and have bi-directional communication
but it requires then only one part be
open so it reduces the footprint and and
basically reduces the security
it increases security by reducing
accessible ports on a k3s installation
okay so here we have the external
database but in a che mode but what we'd
really like to do is keep the simplicity
right so this requires that I manage an
external database and we'll talk about
that a little more in the use cases but
what we also want it to be able to do
was do an AJ mode with an embedded
database so we started looking at equal
light which is distributed sequel light
and we're pulling that back in right now
you can actually try this out it's
experimental on our on the k3s site
there is instruction and the docs on how
to use it we're gonna eventually get to
a point where we we release with equal
light as part of it so what's the
difference between equal light and an
external data store the difference is
that with an external data store you
only need two nodes because you're
talking to a single database and those
two nodes would constitute H a state the
the thing with equal light is that we're
actually using we're still using the
capabilities that Ed CD had that allowed
it to be highly available and in doing
so it requires that you actually have
three nodes so for the embedded equal
light you'll actually need three nodes
to have an H a installation so all these
options now easy to install but
depending on your use case that'll
dictate which one you choose and how it
drives what you're going to do with KPS
so some of the requirements for running
k3s in a che you need unique host names
if you don't have unity coast names
let's say you have a bunch of raspberry
PI's you have an SD card image and you
don't change the host name on those you
could still run this of course you're
going to be addressing those with IP
address to shell into them for SSH but
if you add the dash dash node name flag
or the environment variable k3s node
name you can actually get k3s working
even though they don't have unique host
names in your environment in addition
that we're testing on Ubuntu 1604 1804
and raspbian buster as you can see I'm
running on arm 64 it's not in our test
suite if you're looking for support and
it's something you really need talk to
us we can we can provide we can talk
about providing that I you know I'm sure
we can we can figure something out to
get arm 64 into the matrix the test
matrix so k3 sha requirements continued
hardware again it's still a minimum of
512 mega RAM 1 CPU and then we recommend
SSDs and just like SCD the high I ops is
gonna have you give you better
performance of your kubernetes
installation kubernetes cluster in terms
of networking we need six four four
three open if you're using flannel out
of the box we have flannel if you're
using it you need 8472 open if you're
using the metrics api you need 10 to 50
open and you know that's pretty much the
the basics of the requirements you can
of course go and and look at the full
requirements on the docs page as well so
here's k3 sha with a two
in an external database pretty simple
that's what it looks like in this in
this scenario what I'm showing here is
two node kubernetes installation that's
highly available where we're using an
external database all nodes have all
components they have the data playing
the control plane and the worker role we
can also do the separate masters right
and so this this is a little bit more
like that yellow diagram where I've
isolated the k3s agents from the k3s
masters the servers and workers in this
case you'll notice that not only do I
have an external database for the
server's to store the kubernetes cluster
data but I've got a fixed registration
address server in today's demo I won't
I won't set one up this will add a layer
of complexity that it may or may not be
necessary so I can I can point my
workers so what I need is for my workers
to initially register with the cluster
in some way I could point to the IP
address of one of the servers or or to
the host address they have the host name
of one of the servers the fqdn
or I could have this front-end server
that that has a fixed registration
address maybe maybe it's spans all three
some sort of reverse proxy or load
balancer but then I need to make sure
that my fixed registration server is
available at the time when I'm trying to
register workers so it might also need
to be written in some H a mode so that's
why I say it adds complexity but you can
use you can do that if you want to
alright so let's get down to business
here let's do a demo of highly available
kts
and what that looks like
alright so here I have my pain split up
let's take a look at what I've got here
so you can see I've got another arch 64
system and in this case I've got a
fedora 30 installation the next
installation both so this is master one
you can see right below it is master to
both my master nodes are running Fedora
there's no there's no significant reason
why I'm doing this I had originally when
I was trying to work on getting arch 64
working I initially started with fedora
image and so I had a couple of Fedora
images already available and and just
kept using them but there's there's no
other reason than that it's it's not you
know it could also run on the Debian
images as well as I showed in the single
node now on the other one so so those
two nodes are raspberry pi 3 B plus and
actually let's go back up and we'll do
an H top on these to install a chap I
did so you can see that in this case
I've got oh it's not showing how much
memory I have available interesting so
these have one gig of memory and if I
recall that this used to shows the
amount of memory I'm not sure what
changed here but anyways so so you can
see that I have four cores I do have a
gig of memory swap is turned off
and basically in the memory I don't know
if you can distinguish colors as this
comes across to your screen but there's
there's a about eight green bar so to be
at the beginning that's used memory and
then the the blue is buffers and the
yellow is cash so you can see even with
cache memory not a lot is going on on
this system right now let's get out of
there
and we'll go down and we'll take a look
at the beef plus so I've got a 4b plus
here again running our 64 and running
raspberry but raspy and Buster and you
can see again not much going on a lot
less usage this is a four gig device so
so much bigger device and then finally
let's go down here and we'll just run a
CH top this is also our 64 also raspbian
buster and in this case this is actually
512 mega RAM this is a Raspberry Pi 3d
A+ so it's very small device and and a
lot smaller form factor than the other
ones but I'm gonna I'm gonna pull these
all together and make a kubernetes
cluster out of these so let's do that so
I'm going to start with installing just
the the server component on each of
these master nodes
so here's a long command that I copied
and pasted out in my notes I'm pulling
down the get k3s script and if you just
pull this and and you can read it but
I'm gonna pipe it through shell and I'm
going to add some environment variables
along the way so this is curl be silent
and fail on errors and follow links and
then I pipe it into shell but then I
create before I do that I create this
environment variable called install k3s
exact I set one called write code config
mode you know if you recall when I
installed when I did the yes we lost
connection here I don't know if we'll
get it back but when I initially did
cube CTL on this single node I did it
with sudo and I did that because I can't
access the yellow file the way I ran it
but there are command-line arguments and
this is a command-line argument for k3s
that allows me to set the coop config
mode when I create it actually 644 is is
actually not a good mode that's the
wrong mode to set it to because that's
gonna make it world's readable and
that's actually not what I want right so
that that's the wrong mode the because
this is a security file right but but
anyways the point is you can write the
coop config mode and that allow me not
to have to run sudo every time as this
user when I when I run this then I
actually I'm gonna go ahead and start
this and I'm on the next one and then
we'll take a look at it while it's
starting to install well we'll continue
to discuss what we're running so I'm
running in our master two
and I'm master one will continue talking
about what what else I have here I
specify a data store endpoint so I've
created a external database I have a my
sequel running in a container on this
Mac laptop actually that I'm running so
they're all in the same network space
and so my data store endpoint here is my
sequel k3s Adnan and and then I'm giving
the parameters for password and end user
in that and the database name is k3s DB
so that's what I'm creating I'm creating
a secret - T is is the agent secret and
that's the secret that I'm going to use
with my agents - to connect to this so
we're gonna have this shared secret
you'll obviously want that to be secret
and not shared with 30 other people in a
in a demo and then the TLS on I'm
actually saying in my cert make sure
that oh and it's actually a little bit
this this TLS on is not going to help me
too much because that was when I had a
registration server so this is an old
master o1 it's going to be wrong in the
other one but basically that's going to
add to the cert the and I'm since this
gets stored in the database we may have
to go with what we had before not sure
how that's going to work that's
something I should test out the node
taint so I'm saying taint this node to
be just part of the control plane so no
acts
nothing can execute here so it's not
schedulable in the kubernetes parlance
meaning i don't want any worker i don't
want any any pods deployed here right
and then finally my last environment
variable is the version of k3s that i'm
gonna install so we're going to go ahead
and run that here as well
and we'll come down and do a coop CTL
notice no sudo and no k3s the other
thing I did in that that original one is
you'll notice I ran coop CTL as an
argument to k3s the difference here is
on this single node I downloaded k3s and
I ran k3s directly and I could create a
sim link a link a local link to k3s like
an alias to k3 s cube CTL for the coop
CTL command or or a linked file but
basically it's embedded in KPS right
that's that's the whole single process
whereas here I'm running coop CTL
independently and I'm going to do a coop
CTL get node and that's going to show me
the nodes attached it should just be one
now do a watch on this and we can watch
these as they come up
okay so we have one node and it's more
nodes join we'll see additional nodes so
the next thing I want to do is actually
join in my worker nodes
so I'm going to run it on the four
b-plus first and then I'll explain it
down here again you see pulling this
it's the exact same script but this time
my environment variable is agent instead
of server I'm using that same secret
agent secret right
and then I'm specifying in this case I'm
specifying master to has the server this
would be my registration server in this
case I'm just specifying this server
here I'll look that second that that
node came up so I now have a worker node
that's joined as well it doesn't specify
the role you actually have to label
those if you want those labeled there
comes master one as well so now I have
two masters and one worker let's get
this other worker installed the final
thing is the k3s version and again I'm
installing the the latest k3s version so
we'll get all those nodes come up and
[Music]
let's do a quick take a look at what
pods are there
all right so we've got all four nodes
are in now so I now have a kubernetes
cluster and you can see that the we've
installed traffic we've installed core
DNS we've installed a metric server
there's the local path provisioner and
some of those things have not actually
come up yet
let's do actually - Oh wide and see what
node those are running on everything's
running on the 4 for B+ which is the
node with with lots of memory right so
kubernetes is kind of doing its thing
looks like traffic is having some errors
coming out but kubernetes is is doing
its thing right it's looking at the the
resource pools and it's going hey this
node has a lot of resources
let's run everything there all right
let's um let's get back into the deck so
here again and I did this just so you
have this when Matthew sends out the
deck
so here's setting up the master without
the agent please refer to the github
page and the docs for all of the things
all of the things you can do with k3s
all the flags and the parameters and
things like that
that's the server this is the agent
basically then the other thing is this
is the the setup the configuration right
so this is what it looks like on my lab
top I've got that sequel container and
I've got my two masters which are Fedora
the three B+ pies I'm doing registration
I'm not going through a registration
server but I have to do registration and
then kind of what this doesn't show is
that that proxy server that opens up
once registration has done the the
communication after this initial
registration goes through that proxy
server and then I've got my my two
workers in this case I we often get the
question you know can I run both can I
run are me x86 and arm simultaneously in
the same cluster absolutely kubernetes
doesn't care it doesn't really know it's
just that your workloads need to be
configured for the resource type that
that you you have available right so if
you have an architecture your containers
have to be built for that architecture I
want to get into some use cases and show
you a little bit about what what are
people using k3s for so people are using
them you know as you might imagine edge
devices an arm that's partly why a lot
of my demos aren't arm the edge is the
majority of edge what we call edge now
is arm devices see ICD we're seeing k3s
actually in the cloud and data center as
well as well as on the developer desktop
let's drill down into each of these so
for edge and arm we're seeing edge
weights so software developer network
compositions so also machine learning
before the cloud so right now these the
the edge compute has been done in the
cloud and the the gateways been used to
just do a protocol translation so going
from whatever protocol the edge nodes
are speaking to http sending things up
to the cloud where data can be processed
it's actually onerous it's very
heavyweight it's there's a lot of push
to move that the the process the the
actual data analysis down into the edge
right now we're seeing it at edge
gateways we will likely see it actually
deeper into the edge as well as those
devices get more compute as FPGAs become
more prevalent as you know the the
ecosystem is changing we're also seeing
k3s in branch management servers so in
you know stores retail outlets where you
may have multiple retail outlets tens or
hundreds of stores that need the same
product but they all have some somewhat
different configurations so they're
creating the you know k3s provides an
environment for turnkey operations where
i can just send this to the store flip
us you know plug it in and flip a switch
turn it on go to a website that hosts
enter my code and it will pull down
whatever configuration i need it will
auto configure the system now the the
home office now has telemetry into these
multiple branches they can now introduce
a chains in places where they had single
servers running you know file servers
applications for processing POS data and
stuff like that can all be done now
through containers and and sort of I
think one of the common themes across
all of these things is the consistency
of development so now if you're
developing for cloud you can have a
process for
in containers and the same goes for edge
you can now deploy to edge in the same
way the far edge maybe we're still
seeing from where updates and that sort
of thing but even there in far edge on
for example windmills which are you know
little micro data centers really they're
they're doing containers and data
processing there for you know on-site
data processing and then field operation
data center so we're seeing mobile AI
units in military applications where
they need to process data
you know they strip a laptop from some
operative and they need to process it
right away
energy remote operations you know they
need to do do location geosphere
positioning all sorts of interesting
things and they have little data centers
operating in these in these rigs as well
and then in you know shipping and you
know in actual physical chips have data
centers as well
so those are some of the sort of the
edge locations and types of use cases
we're seeing and then from the CI CD
perspective for CI pipelines you know
really just being able to automate
environment up down just for the the
purpose of integration and testing
environments load testing scale testing
you know basically it's really mostly
the CI aspect at this this point we're
obviously CD is is delivery into your
production systems the cloud and data
center we're seeing a lot of just
generally simplified installation of
kubernetes where you know the its
kubernetes right so so
you need full-blown installations you
might you might still want to do that we
still have a distribution called rke
that is the most used distribution I
think it's the most used distribution it
could be round bye-bye rancher certainly
it's you know used by the rancher
management server and many rancher
customers but k3s provides simplified
management and clouded cloud and data
center part of that is that you don't
have the overhead of @cd and so this
this third bullet about relational
database solutions being well understood
now you can basically say well I've
already got you know I have licenses for
relational databases
I have staff who understand how to use
them how to create failover I know how
to do encryption at rest you know I have
DBA is that know are DB and then the
other thing is just generally many small
clusters and and sort of how easy it is
to to make ephemeral clusters with a
solution like k3s and finally for the
developer desktop okay now you know
again coming back to the micro Kate's
and and and mini cube you know as a
single node kubernetes you couldn't
really do true kubernetes orchestration
between nodes right nice with k3s
developers can really actually do that
you really get this sort of easy to up
and down kubernetes cluster with things
like role based access control if you're
developing C RDS or you're developing
helm charts you you actually have a
place to do this that's not a public
kubernetes cluster or you know in
private one in your enterprise but where
other people are using it so you can
really take it to its limits with with
k3s so we are let's see we're which
a little bit of time so I think what I'd
like to do is we we could open up for
questions I don't know Matt how many
questions we have outstanding right now
and then I can come back and sort of
demonstrate the using this with Rancher
and the the you know multi cluster
management capability yeah cool thanks
mark um so there's about ten questions
asked at this point maybe list let's go
through those and then we can do a
little bit more demo okay sounds good
yeah okay cool so I'll just do the first
asked first so this is from meta I hope
I sure butchering your name but he asks
could you elaborate on how k3s is
different two recent projects by the
Linux Foundation like LF edge and
project Eve
or e ve yeah that's a great question so
the the LF edge
I don't so I I'm not sure I know project
EBE
the and the it's been a while since I've
looked at LF edge
okay so k3s is a kubernetes distribution
and and i know that some of the the
projects within the LF edge space a
really designed around process and in
sort of if i am you know if i am going
to build an edge gateway what what is
the template for building that and and
i'm afraid i don't recall which which
product is which within Aleph edge so
the the best thing i can say is that k3s
is a kubernetes distribution like to be
a DM cube spray rke and and so when
you're looking at those other projects
most of them use a you know they are
using a kubernetes distribution but they
are not them
kubernetes distributions right makes
sense thank you okay here's the next one
this is from sorem who asked us when you
were doing the k3s install near the
beginning and he says he said why do we
need sudo well so I I started k3s with
sudo because I needed elevated
permissions to to run k3s but if you so
when I when I installed it so when I
installed it through this process
through through the single node I
installed it with sudo but I didn't do
anything to give myself access to the
CTL to the coop config file so so I
could run k3 asks let's see if I can log
back into this device it may not have
some backup I probably have to restart
it so I could run k3s sort of with it
without sudo but because I started it
with sudo I I needed pseudo to run the
other operations you'll notice over here
I did not run k3s with sudo right so so
but under the hood we are getting
elevated permissions to to install some
components like into system D you can
see here we actually installed a system
D service and so you know I would need
sudo to start and stop k3s but for just
running like coups TL commands
I just need permission to use the config
I could generate using our back I could
generate coop config for you know a user
and then that user would have the
standard kubernetes permissions awesome
okay thank you
all right here's the next one this is
from Hans who asks how do I upgrade k3s
to a new version
from 1.16 to 1.17 for example are there
any risks mmm there might be risks
depending on what you know what version
you are starting with I know that we are
trying at this point now that is it's
been G a G aid we are trying to ensure
that the releases are at least one
version backwards compatible so for
example if I was running a 116 cluster
and I had four nodes running on 116 I
need to upgrade both my masters and my
worker nodes and I need to upgrade them
one at a time the the upgrade is
actually very simple
the the upgrade let's see if I can get
into this now so I don't know if I'll
see ya so I'm not even seeing the the
install command let's go back to the
slide presentation we'll go back a
couple of pages hang on just a moment
here let's see here we go okay so here I
did this environment variable installed
k3 s version so you can you can upgrade
to the next version just by changing
that environment variable or using the
flag on the command line when you run k3
when you you know and basically do a
reinstall so if you're running it
through this script where where we
actually install the init script into
system D you would just change the flag
you're gonna have to do one note at a
time
they should be backwards compatible up
to one version back the the challenge is
going to be one one stable version back
the challenge is always going to be if
you installed an unstable version so if
you've been playing around with latest
but it wasn't March stable it may not
be compatible but it's hard to say in
terms of upgrading a cluster I would
start with the server's do one server at
a time make sure that it upgrades it
would I should have for my next demo I'm
going to I'm going to install an older
version then we'll do an upgrade I think
that's a great great thing to do show
you how to do that but they basically
upgrade my server make sure it upgraded
right so I do one of them make sure it
upgraded and then come back and do the
next one and then do my agents once the
server's are upgraded we could actually
go in here I'm not gonna so I've got my
four nodes right in this in this box on
the middle box on the left hand side
I've got the two masters and the two
workers I'm gonna stop k3s on this
master and that will drop it out of the
cluster you'll see that the the it's
been show as as not ready in the status
right and so because I have this H a
mode right and so now I can do this sort
of thing where I can upgrade everything
this becomes a little bit more complex
you'll have some downtime if you have a
single node and you do an upgrade you're
gonna have downtime thank were you done
with the odds gonna say next question
yeah yeah next question alright there we
go alright here's the next question this
is from Soren who asks s who says SQL
Lite is written in C iirc are you guys
using C go to get to SQL Lite why not
our cue light which is go based hmm that
would be a question for the developers
and I would recommend you
the k3s slack channel - to ask that
question I I don't know why the decision
was made to use SQL Lite you know versus
a go based sequel Lite okay cool yeah
make sense
so yeah found k3s channel on the
ranchers Lac yes okay let's see so the
next one this is from Ludovic sure I'm
butchering your name but he says with
MySQL as the backend could we have
issues with bin logs like in Rancher one
because of many updates I am not sure
what the issues with bin logs were so so
I just don't know the answer to that I
don't know what the problems were
if you're using MySQL as a back-end it
it is external and so you do need to
manage it independently of the
kubernetes cluster okay cool yeah and
maybe another good one for for a rancher
general or the k3s channel so this is
from the next question is from the same
gentleman who asks could we imagine
running rancher two on k3s what a great
question it yes we can imagine it and it
is coming we are targeting I don't know
what the you know if we have a date set
yet but we are targeting running Rancher
two on k3s it would create a simplified
installation of ranch or two which right
now for those of you who don't know you
need to install kubernetes first in
order to run Rancher and this would be
sort of all-in-one simplified
installation okay cool thank you alright
here's the next one this is from Luke
who asks why not use
and rke style installation yeah so so
rke is the rancher kubernetes engine it
is a distribution of kubernetes from
rancher labs as well and the RK he I
think what you mean by the arcade style
installation is that that we have a
config file for our ke and I can I can
write all of my configuration into this
yamo file and then I point rke at that
config and say are ke up I tell it what
my nodes are and and what the
configuration should be for each type of
node so the width with this distribution
with k3s
you're basically configuring each node
at a time right there's no common
configuration however you can use k3 OS
k 3o s is the k3 operating system and k3
OS has a cloud config a cloud in it
config which will allow you to configure
the the entire system and will install
k3 s into that container operating
system the I'm not sure you know exactly
why it's done this way I think you know
part of it is the simplicity of a single
binary you could absolutely write a
script to install k3 s you know
basically using terraformer or something
like that to to install k3 s into your
nodes and so you really don't need that
config file and in the same way you
would be passing configure arguments as
environment variables or parameters
but that's an interesting question I am
really thought a lot about it but I'm
not sure that k3s lends itself to the
same installation model as rke where you
kind of blow in a whole installation
into multiple nodes at the same time
right okay cool well there's a few more
questions um do you want to take those
questions or do you want to finish that
that last portion of the demo that and
discuss today sure let's let's have a
little break we'll we'll go in and let's
let's restart this as you can see master
one is not ready so I'm gonna restart
this node and that'll come back up and H
a cluster again and then so so a little
bit about ranch or rancher it is a
rancher Labs is an open source company
we have a bunch of open source projects
and k3s is just one of a number of
projects that we have the we also have
projects called Rancher management
server which is actually a product so
for us we don't sell software we develop
software and then for certain projects
which the community has really sort of
taken so you know that the community
likes basically and based on the
adoption we then offer support for those
products rancher management server is
one of those products and we're in
version two of Rancher management server
Ranger management server is a supported
product so it means you can actually pay
to get support but the product Rancher
management server the project is freely
available just like k3s you can download
it use it there's no enter
addition of it but we can use that to
connect with all of our clusters and so
so we are moving towards building into
your extra management server additional
capability for specifically for edge but
right now I'm just going to show you
importing a k3s cluster there will be a
number of things coming along so one of
the things is you will be able to create
k3s clusters from branch or management
server right now you can create rke
clusters from rancher management server
in lots of different cloud providers and
that's what Rancher management server is
all about is running clusters everywhere
so I'm going to go to this import
cluster and I'm going to say k3s import
and we'll create this this is going to
give me a good CTL apply command I'm
just going to copy out that command
we'll go into just let's just make sure
that things are running here it looks
like the
back up it looks like coop CTL is
operating look my local path provisioner
we've got some some additional things
I've got a service load balancer most
likely running on multiple nodes here
right because it's a demon sets so you
can see that that in fact my service
load balancer is running on two
different nodes because I have only two
worker notes but also some other things
came up some other pods came up in the
interim while we were talking what I
want to do is run this command here that
that manager management server server
gave me and this is going to install
some agents into the system and allow me
to get visibility back into the Rancher
into the k3s cluster through Rancher
management server as well as used the
some of the capabilities to Rancher like
our back and deployments and things like
that
I could obviously do a coop CTL apply -
chef on any type of you know acceptable
kubernetes configuration actually do I
have one here no but I did it on this
Jamo file that's that's how that's
posted through my Rancher management
server if we go back and look at what's
in that what you'll see is some our back
so you'll see there there's a cluster
role there's a cluster role binding let
me make this a little bigger there's a
namespace there's a service accounts
here's a secret right so a bunch of a
bunch of kubernetes stuff and then
finally here's a deployment so I've got
this cattle cluster agent this is how
Rancher is able to communicate with
clusters everywhere is by installing
these agents and then they they
basically set up that two-way
communication similar to the proxy
server and there's a demon set and then
that allows us to basically have
visibility into
things in ranchero made everything
bigger alright um so here's my k3s
importer it's still working
let's see you can see that my 512 Meg on
the bottom you can see I'm I still have
plenty of space plenty of capacity as
these things come in but I do I'm
getting some use utilization there right
some of those cores are getting used a
little bit Oh
176 178 eggs there we go so that's
coming up if we do the coop CT I'll get
pods we should have some more detail
because we're going to start seeing
these agent it's creating the agents now
one of them was sat right the node
agents or demon sets so you can see that
those are getting created everywhere and
I've got the cluster agent which is just
landed on master - so waiting for all
those things come up and once they do we
will have this cluster imported back
into kubernetes into ranch management
server and we'll be able to see it so
and then once I do that through here
we'll wait till it comes up let's go
back to questions once this comes up
we'll take another look at it and see
what we could do with it
okay sweet let's see so okay here's
another sort of roadmap question this is
from Thomas who asks are there plans for
the ability to run Windows container
workloads on k3 yes
um so my understanding is that one of
our engineers got there is now an
executable a XE version of kts I don't
know if let's see that would be here I
don't know if yeah it's not part of the
build process right now but I know I
know we have done it and but the the
issue is you need you know dotnet core
containers to run on it so as far as I
know there's work being done in that
area and there's progress being made I
would check in this is another thing
that I would check in with poundcake 3s
in the slack user group and see where
that's at okay great thank you
alright couple more this is this next
one is from Ludovic who says how do we
were new certificates inside the cluster
do we just restart every node cert
renewal um I don't know what the process
for cert renewal is inside the cluster
another great question little vague the
the it is not something I've done and I
would defer you to the docks although I
don't even know if the docks get us into
that we you know it's worth probably
posting that question up through up
through slack pound k3s I'm not sure how
you know how you get that done how you
accomplish that okay no problem
lots to learn here so this is okay so
one more this is from Sorum who asks so
this is this is going back to the
privileges question from pseudo about
pseudo from earlier so he says so k3s
can run
user space with no problems systemd can
be tackled separately and I mean without
using you know rude pseudo at all so the
question here is let's see yes okay
yes can be run in userspace with no
problems so yes there is actually a
project a part of k3 s for no root where
is that in the in the docks and no there
there's like one individual who really
wanted that feature has worked on it I
don't know the status of it but it is
possible to run it in userspace without
root okay all right cool
that was the last question that has been
answered they've been asked if anybody
has another question posted soon because
I think we'll be wrapping up in a minute
so if there's anything else you want to
show us mark and yeah sure let's take a
look so let's see if we've got some
things running here yeah it looks like
we have the agents up and running and
we're utilizing 194 mags out of it's
probably 400 and you know shy of 512
right and then if we go back to Rancher
we should now see here here it is here's
our cluster we can see our nodes we can
see that two of these nodes are marked
as masters that you know they're no
executes and I can do things that I
would normally do with ranch or like
deployments and stuff like that so
rancher creates this wrapper around
namespaces for those of you that aren't
familiar with it and I can go in and
create a deployment this is just a UI
surfacing kubernetes capabilities so
I'll just do it on nginx deployments and
we'll do five pods just for the kicks
will create a new namespace and I know
it exposes 80 and go ahead and launch
that actually there's this I would need
to also create an ingress for this
because I don't expose my little private
network here so we probably won't be
able to actually view that unless we're
inside the network all right so it's
employing we should see in the top of
this screen we should see some changes
although there may be too many things
let's see just nginx namespace we can
see more utilization down on the bottom
one those contain creating yeah let's
get on - Oh wide now you know I'm I'm
viewing this through coop CTL it's only
one of them landed on the smaller
Raspberry Pi four of them landed on the
larger one and if I go if I go into the
UI I can also see similar things right
so I can come in and see that these are
all unavailable and nothing's come up up
here we go one of them came up on the
three A+ so that's the first one up
so that's pretty much it that's
k3s that is you know manager management
server we are working on as I said
before we're working on setting up
building basically a fleet capability
into master management server it's not
clear right now whether it's going to be
a separate project or whether it'll be
embedded into Rancher but the idea is
that Rancher will have the that you've
got all these edge clusters you're gonna
have a this plethora of clusters and how
do you manage them all and you know if
you have right now Rancher is used
because people have them in the data
center they've got them in multiple
clouds they want to manage clusters
across providers
that's what Rancher is used for we're
seeing that in the edge with the large
number of clusters
there's not really a data center per se
but lots of things to manage and process
and to work with in that environment so
that's all I've got
thanks everybody for joining today yeah
thank you so much mark awesome job thank
you thank you thank you for the slides
and the demo and the knowledge and just
a reminder to everybody this session was
recorded I'll do my best to get this out
to you all in your email later today in
the next couple hours just as soon as
the the video processes um so you'll get
the recording and the slides in your
email if you don't see it check YouTube
it'll be there you can also reach me on
email and Matthew at Rancher calm or on
slack at at Matthew and all that stuff
all those that info will be in the
slides
alright that's all we have today I might
see you all tomorrow we are doing an
intro to rancher rancher management
server and kubernetes tomorrow adrian
goings will be doing that director of
community so it should be really good
otherwise that's it thanks everybody
have a great rest of your week thanks
mark you're welcome take care