folks thank you very much for joining
this session about seress platform on
kubernetes uh we will be uh doing a
bunch of things here uh talking about
kubernetes mostly uh so let's start with
the basics kubernetes users how many
people using kubernetes already all
right that's that's good that's fair
enough most of the time because this is
kcd Spain uh it's you know it's about
kubernetes so I will not be going
through the basics but if you have any
questions please feel free to shout out
and we can stop and spend a little bit
more time there I will be showing a
bunch of different projects and I have
only 15 minutes uh so it's uh you know
it's going to be fast and the main idea
here is just to show things and then uh
you can go and research more you can ask
questions or you can ask for more
clarifications but I wanted to show a
bunch of different things um important
uh when we talk about platforms
basically we are talking about combining
a different uh set of projects to kind
like achieve something to enable
different teams and what we are going to
be talking specifically today is about
serverless on top of kubernetes which is
a specific thing that some people might
want and some people basically they are
not interested so it's not for everyone
but I think that it has some advantages
that you might consider at some point so
my name is Maurice salatino I work for a
company it's called Uh diagrid I will be
talking about the project that we're
working on a little bit and also the
products too not too much just to
mention kind like the the ideas Behind
These and other companies and other
projects I'm so sofware engineer I'm not
a developer advocate so my presentations
tends to be not funny and very technical
and and you know and Technical oriented
so it's it will be just very dry way of
showing different projects uh I'm also a
cncf Ambassador and I think that's
interesting uh mostly because I've been
just working with different projects and
I've been talking about this for for
some time now and I author this this
book I have two copies we will be
playing with the Wi-Fi in a bit uh just
to see if you can get one of the two
copies that I have here uh for free but
if you're interested in in platforms and
kubernetes this this book basically
covers like I think that like 17
different projects in the cncf space and
some projects that are not in the cncf
too uh and as I mentioned before I'm
collaborating with different projects
and I've been involved with the Dapper
project with the K8 project that I'm
showing today and also with Captain
something that I'm not showing today but
it's also like a a project that it's
very close to to my heart uh I've been
running a Blog for 15 years so if you
are interested check it there like salao
or salao at Twitter is my handle but
let's get it started let's take a look
into some open source projects so the
first thing that I will do which is
something that I usually don't is
showing a project that called open
function how many people here knows
about open function I see Zero hands
raising and this is there is a very good
reason for that uh open function is a
cncf project uh but it's a Chinese Le
cncf project that basically means that
it was created in a Chinese community
and donated to the cncf and it's a very
very interesting project to analyze
that's why I wanted to show it today
mostly because when we're talking about
serverless some people will think about
like function based you know
applications and platforms and open
function gives you exactly that so let's
take a quick look at how this looks in
in
practice let me see if you can see my
screen here I'm connected to a cluster I
basically install open function into a
kubernetes cluster this is running on
gke on Google Cloud so it's not in my
laptop meaning that if the Wi-Fi goes
wrong at some point I will just not be
able to do anything we will try 4G or
something else but it's it's kind of
working right uh when I just basically
list all the namespaces you can see that
I have a bunch of things I've just
installed open function which is just a
simple project and I have a bunch of
different tools installed there just to
be able to provide this like function
experience the idea here is to enable
developers just to write functions in
any language that they want and then
just by creating a
single kubernetes resource to be able to
get that function running into this
kubernetes cluster right but in order to
achieve that they actually integrated a
bunch of tools together in a very very
particular way the main interface that
you will see as a user it's something
called function of course and I don't
know if you can see this like in the
back but I will try to make it as big as
possible everything is in a reposto
there that it's called kcd Spain 2024 in
my GitHub reposter I will share the link
later but as you can see here let me see
if I can yeah as you can see here there
is just a new kubernetes resource called
function that's the thing that you
define now in order to actually deploy
function then uh basically you write the
function code in this case I have a you
know a go function which is pretty
pretty simple it's just printing a hello
world or something like that and then
you define two things here in the spec
uh definition in the spec you know
template here you define the build pH
how are you going to build this code
into a container and then you define how
are you going to serve this code for
people to access this function right as
you can see here the build side of
things you need to specify a builder in
this case you need to know that it's
goal and this Builder I think it's using
a cncf project that it's called build
packs to actually do the build and as
you can see here you start seen this
kind of stuff like okay if you're in
China maybe you cannot access the you
know go modules so you need a proxy for
that kind of like interesting stuff that
happens in the other side of the world
uh but another important part here is
not only how are you going to build the
the container but also where is the
source code and here I'm pointing to a
GitHub repos story that has the function
source code in this case again written
in go under this directory so no matter
where the cluster is it's going to be
able to pick up the source code of the
function build it and deploy it into the
cluster itself and it's going to then
serve it here we don't have much
parameters here in general it's just uh
the name of the image that will be
created On Demand by the build process
and then the fact that we will uh you
know we can configure the image here in
any way we want if we want to set up
environment variables or whatever we
just set it up there then the port that
it's being used by default so with this
thing um I will just apply this to to
the
cluster uh so basically not that one uh
this one functions go function functions
go function. jaml so I'm just applying
this resource to the cluster and
basically what I have now is you know a
function that is going to be built and
deploy inside this cluster by using a
bunch of different tools uh if I do I
can do get functions now because this is
a resource right like as any other
kubernetes resource and I can see kind
like the state of the function itself
right so it basically says it's been
buil it's building now uh and at some
point it will tell me if it's been
served if it's ready to receive request
or not and I will get some kind of
address here uh after all this process
happens I did build this function before
so I was expecting this to be built
again things that happen when you're
doing kind of like live demos right but
at the end of the day you will have a
URL there that you can basically
interact with just call it it will be
some sort of a public URL that you can
access uh if you have configured your
cluster correctly you will have a public
you know URL or like an internal cluster
URL that other functions can use to call
this
function one thing that I wanted to show
here uh which I think is important if
you go to their website like open
function. deev you will find this
diagram uh which for me basically tells
me a lot of things right it tells me
that to build an experience like this
where you basically expose an interface
the function interface in this case the
function resource and then you will have
different options to do different things
depending on what you're trying to do
right if you are trying to build the
container based on the source code you
have a bunch of cncf and open source
projects that will help you to do that
buildpacks is very like it's it's a it's
a complicated project it's not a simple
project but the main idea is that you
don't even need to specify in which
language your function is or your code
is uh buildpack will have a detection
mechanism to say you know this is a Java
function or this is a go function and
then we'll create containers based on
that which is a pretty interesting
mechanism and then the other ones are
are kind like more typical things that
you will use just to create containers
uh the main idea there is just not to be
playing with Docker fast right like
which are good they are easy to create
but they are also very easy to make
mistakes uh too and then you go through
you know the the facee of okay I have a
container now I need to serve this
function in a way that you know it's
serverless in a sense right like and the
main idea here is that I will be able to
upscale the function if it's getting a
lot of requests or I will be able to
downscale it to if it's nobody's using
it right and for that you know you can
see there that they are using a bunch of
projects and again it's not just using
the projects but it's combining them
together to achieve some use cases so
for some specific use cases you need to
combine them in in in a very specific
way you can see K native there you can
see kada you can see Dapper and at the
bottom they added also like a wasm
runtime too for for wasm modules and
stuff like that which is kind of
interesting and then on this side of the
the screen you can see events which is
again it's it's a way that they created
in order to to connect functions
together via messaging or Eventing right
it's kind of like an interesting thing
too uh that they created and again this
is where it becomes all about like is
this something that you really need like
do you need the functionality in this
way or are you willing to create your
own glue between the projects and Define
the use cases that you are trying to
Target in your company let's see and I
will just not wait for too long let's
see if this is
running I don't know demo gos are on my
side today so it seems to be running
here um I don't know if you can see down
there but like basically what I have
here is a URL that it's not a public URL
this is basically an internal URL and
this is where open function you actually
need to start understanding a little bit
about the tools that it's using in order
to use it because when things go wrong
abstractions start like falling apart
because if I need to troubleshoot or
figure out what's the public IP for that
function I need to know how it's being
served in a way and I will just run a
command because I know how this is being
served served and I know where the
public IP is uh but yeah at the end of
the day you don't really want to do this
so you need to make sure that whatever
you expose here it can be used right and
I can call this function Now using just
just sending an HTP request saying kcds
Spain for example right as you can see
the function will not respond pretty
fast because it wasn't upscaled yet so
there wasn't an instance of that
function running and it took like a
second to spin up a new replica you know
process the request and then it's now
waiting for most more request to happen
right if I call it again it will be much
faster right I can list the pots here
you will see that now I have uh let me
see if I can do that uh you will see
like I have that b running there and
again in the true serverless fashion in
in after 90 seconds or so which is the
theault time for this to be downscale if
I do not send more requests this will be
downscale to zero right and again as I
mentioned before uh there are some tools
that are basically implementing this
behavior and uh you
know it's actually up to you to Define
if the way that open function is uh
gluing things together works for you or
or not right open function gives like
for me it's a great initiative again
there are some you know language is
barriers that we need to tackle because
again all all the documentation it's a
little bit strange being translated from
Chinese to English there is tons of
possibilities there to contribute uh to
make things easier for non-chinese
speakers and and for you know for
Spanish speakers as well uh it provides
this abstraction based on a function
concept which is great and I think that
they did a good job there at gluing some
tools together but then of course like
when I see companies like large
companies creating their own
abstractions they probably have
something they need something similar to
that but not 100% right uh I think that
having an interface called function
actually limits the kind of applications
that you can deploy because you think
that you can only do functions like
lambdas or stuff like that but actually
no matter what container you put in
there it was going to be served and and
built in the same way and then you need
to figure it out you know like if the
tools that open functions is using are
you comfortable with those tools do you
know about those tools or not because at
some point when things go wrong you will
need to troubleshoot them so you will
need to maintain all that stuff together
and I see people you know using GitHub
actions to build their containers and
then using GTH ups to do the deployment
of things so having this tool that
basically you send a resource and then
you just get something built in the
cluster and then deploy in the cluster
might not be the right thing for you for
several reasons so you know it's it's a
trade-off right like I mean at least for
me just seeing how people is gluing tool
together uh these tools together it's
it's really important because it shows
me a set of use cases that are well
tested and well adopted but then to
choose this for real scenarios then you
just you just need to figure it out if
that's the good thing for you or not uh
and in order to go and talk a little bit
about the tools that are being used by
open function we created an example here
and this is where we the dangerous part
of the presentation we are going to use
HTTP and not https so if you scan that
QR code you will be able to access kind
like an application and I would love to
see if we can uh if we can play together
for a bit so let me know if you can
access you will need to accept that it's
an HTTP endpoint and not https you will
see the warning
there please accept it if if I have two
people pressing buttons I think that
that's more than
enough so I see phones app uh I will
take the QR code in a
second does it work somebody got it
working yes I get some thumbs up so let
me switch here and switch to the
application itself so the application
that you're are accessing basically it's
um it's just a simple thing it's a
simple dashboard uh to vote and we have
kind of like the real time events
popping up every time that somebody uh
submits a vote and then we have some
calculated views of who is winning cats
or dogs we have dogs people here in the
room so I'm I'm super happy this
application is really simple uh when you
voted you had like a like a hash code
generated so don't close that window
look at that that's going insane that's
awesome so don't close the window
because with that you can win uh a book
at the end of the presentation great so
the application is working again that
application is running on Google Cloud
the architecture of that application is
super super super simple right so we
have a a boat service that's the one
that you're using from your phones it
has a UI but also basically what it does
on the back end it just sends data to
Red's to store your boat like you know
you get the Json payload with the boat
then you store it and then at the same
time we send a rabbit mq message to uh
just to a queue that it's being picked
up by the Dashboard that you see well
all the cats and dogs are popping up
there in the middle here we have a
worker that doesn't have any user
interface and and it's doing kind of
like a chrome job right like every two
seconds is picking up data from BR and
translating that into a view to postgre
SQL and that's been read by the results
UI that it's basically showing every two
seconds you know the the percentage of
the BS pretty simple stuff and as you
can quickly see here there is no like
there is not I when I see this
architecture I don't think about
functions in general because I have user
interfaces I don't want to be waiting
you know to upscale a function to be
able to show a user interface that
should be up at least with this one
replica running all the time I have some
infrastructure like R rabid mq postgress
that needs to be running somewhere and I
need to manage and then I have you know
some uh web sockets going on back and
forth again another reason why a
function might not be the best thing if
I need to keep this by directional
connections open just to send
notifications so how difficult it could
be to build an application like this uh
it's actually it's it's a little bit
hard but like the main problem that I
face here is that okay we need to create
containers for all these things we need
to connect to all this infrastructure we
need to make sure that somebody creates
environments where this infrastructure
is is ready for me to to develop and all
that's stuff so let's talk a little
about the projects that are being used
by open function and the reasons why
they chose to use those projects the
first one k native how many people have
heard about K native before okay so we
have half half the room or a little bit
less so K native is usually associated
to serverless and to you know
autoscaling basically the main idea with
K native is to be able to go from
container right like I have a container
and I want to serve it in a URL so if
you give me a container I will just give
you a URL where this container is being
served and I will manage as a k project
I will manage the life cycle of that
container in a way that I can downscale
it to zero if nobody's calling it or
upscale it if I'm getting a lot of
demand uh so let
me this is something that happens with
Keynotes sometimes that you cannot get
out of the presentation mode when you
are presenting the screen which is super
interesting it's it's really interesting
and and then you said okay what do I do
one one way of dealing with this is like
maybe
that but not really so I'm just
connected again and just praying that it
will
work well and it doesn't uh react to my
uh to my clicks either right like it's
just going forward which is super
interesting uh this happened to me
before and I don't know
why so let's let's let's play with the
demo Gods this is not even demo Gods
this is like keynote Gods right like
this is is
insane all right all right uh think
think what do you do when nothing
works turn it off and turn it on again
right I've done this before let you go
oh
o let's see let's see so basically now
it's un blocking I'm blocking my my
screen right this is super
fun yeah there there that's that's the
thing that happens so what I can do is I
actually can continue without slides
which was my original
idea but that will not work let me try
let me try like hard hard reset we can
wait right so K native again it's
associated with that upscaling and out
scaling applications there it goes
off I will unplug this and then see if
it works yep so it's bootstrapping again
again K native is upscaling down scal in
applications how does it work it
basically works by injecting a sidecar
into your
application uh and basically monitoring
incoming request HTTP request so you
have a proxy in front of your
application basically looking for HTTP
request and it will uh basically extract
data about those requests and inform the
K native control plan the things that
you install in your cluster about how
many requests are you getting and if you
need to if you need more replicas or
less replicas uh to serve all those
requests it's it's a very sophisticated
mechanism and it's a very mature project
that uh it has been tested a lot and
it's been it's been adopted by a lot of
companies and a lot of products uh which
uh makes me think that it's mature
enough for people to use and now it's
reaching to a point where uh you know
it's uh it's been graduated in the cncf
which basically means that there is
enough adoption to justify the use of
these tools so no more keynote for me uh
and I will probably need to authenticate
to all the services again I don't even
know what that is that's probably slack
uh but the good thing is that we get my
computer back again so I can keep
showing demos and stuff let me see
if documents
maybe nah all
right yeah there you go not
there that's that's really good okay
let's try keynote again why not why
not keynote case this pain let's see all
right I was there so kened how does it
work do deploy a service uh they have a
new kind of resource I don't even want
to go in full screen anymore but let's
try why not so you have a a thing here
you have a new type of service basically
where again the only thing that you
define is two things the image name that
you want to deploy and basically K8 will
give you an name basically and K8 will
give you a URL with using that name and
it will run your image it deploys a side
car that called Q proxy that basically
will run very close to your application
and it will intercept all the requests
but it will also create a bunch of other
you know resources behind your back like
it doesn't really matter but it will
create that route resource that
basically is in charge of having a URL
Associated and then routing all the
traffic to the proxy of the application
uh the main idea with K native is that
it has a networking layer that will give
you access to doing other things like
traffic splitting and a bunch of other
crazy things that you will do with
something like a service mesh but but
the basic functionality is that it's
going to Route the request to your
application and the Q proxy will
basically inform the G control plane
about the requests if you have a lot of
people calling your application you know
the Q proxy will tell the control plane
hey we need more replicas more replicas
will be created and as you can see there
will be because there are multiple
replicas that basically means multiple Q
proxies so there is something load
balancing on top of this as well if
nobody's calling your route basically
what happens is like your service get
downscale after 90 seconds or so and
basically there is a route now there is
a URL with no replicas serving requests
which is a pretty interesting scenario
and I think that this is the most
interesting scenario of the entire k
thing is the okay what what do you do
when you don't have anything serving
your requests well you need a different
mechanism that it's called activator
that basically is waiting for request in
order to buffer them and then wait for
new replicas to be kickstarted when you
do that you wait for a second that's why
we waited at at the beginning because we
didn't have any replicas of the function
the activator kicks in creates a new
replica and then you know you have a
replica serving your uh your traffic uh
the main idea from K just to uh go back
in track and let's go faster to the next
one is go from container to URL and I
didn't show that because I was
restarting my computer but if I do here
the the ctive services that I have this
is my function K native service I can
describe the K native service type this
is a new type that basically provides
all these abstractions to go from
containers to uh to
URL you can see here that there is a
bunch of status reports about you know
how the function is being configured and
all that stuff but the only important
bit here is that if I have an image I
can just provide you an URL right you
can add like environment variables and
other stuff but at the end of the day
you want to run this image and then you
want a URL back so you can go this
container uh important uh thing to
mention about K native and and the K
native serving apis is that it's being
used by uh you know Google Cloud run
Google Cloud run provides this container
as a service mechanism where you can
just give them a container and they will
run it without using kubernetes or
anything and they expose the same API of
K native serving which is pretty
interesting to see you know it's just
the standard interface for container you
know container as service applications
but again this is just about serving
traffic right like it's about just
deploying applications and then just
making them AOS Scale based on demand
and only based on HTTP in this case
right like this is just using HTTP
metrics to know when to upscale and down
scale uh there is another project being
mentioned there in in open function
which is called kada which is basically
the other side of things when you do
when you want to do a synchronous you
know upscaling and down Scale based on
for example messages on our rabbit mqq
right so if you have messages uh in
Kafka or something like that that it's
more like a synchronous in nature you
can be monitoring these resources taking
a look at how many how many messages do
I have in the queue and then based on
the messages that we have in the queue
we can upscale or
downscale uh and again this is about
running workloads it's not about what do
we do inside of our workloads and that's
what I want to talk a little bit about
Dapper which is the project that I'm
currently working on that stands for
distributed application runtime this is
much more closer to developers and
usually I see people looking into this
project when they are working in a
platform team and they want to enable
development teams with like a set of
unified API that they can use to
interact with complex
environments so uh Dapper uh it's a
project that I'm using in the in the
cats and dogs example that I've showed
you before and for that I will
switch I will not switch to the other
cluster because it's uh closed now
that's good right things that happen let
me see uh it should be
somewhere somewhere here new window
uh and with my company profile so I can
show you all the secrets restore there
you go probably I need to log in again
okay so I have kind like the cluster
where the open function stuff was
installed we have a bunch of projects
installed in there and I created a
different cluster for serving the
application that we used
before and uh there you go so I can
connect to a different cluster now and
I'm using some of these uh uh some of
these you know tools that I mentioned
before so we have ketive Services that's
how I list my ketive services for the
application if it actually connects to
the internet there you go and you can
see that I have three services that are
being exposed the three uis that we saw
before the ones that you use to vote the
results and the dashboard that was
showing the cuts and the dogs right
that's that's the the side of things so
I'm using K there to scale things up and
down and as you will see and as I
mentioned before the vot service for
example because is um uh describe it's a
it's it's a UI I don't want to downscale
it right so one thing that you need to
understand about kinetic is that you can
set up boundaries right there is no need
to downscale to Z if you don't need it
in this case I want to maintain one
replica all the time so I can do that
and also what you can do is you can in
in can you can Define you know um how is
that called like how many request per
second your application is designed to
handle right so you can say you know
this container can handle 100 requests
per second if I'm getting more than 100
requests per seconds I will need more
replicas so I will need to scale up so
you can fine tune when new replicas will
be created using that something like a
common misconception is is about like
thinking that you know one pod one
container will handle a single request
at a time and this is not the case you
know the container can't handle multiple
requests at the same time and you can
Define when to scale up and when to
scale
down the next thing that I wanted to
show is Dapper uh because we were
talking about now let's go and try to
enable developers to do stuff uh inside
your clusters and the kind of stuff that
you want to enable developers to do is
to basically interact with uh you know
the environment that they are running
with and in this case Dapper basically
provides uh an obstruction uh that uh
gives developers apis to do things that
distributed applications wants to do
right so if you go to the Dapper website
which is
way right like with resilient with retry
mechanism secet Breakers and all these
things uh and then like stuff that it's
very common for applications to do and
that's why I was showing the application
like sending and consuming messages most
of the application will want to submit
and consume events right so if instead
of pushing developers to learn about
gafka or rabit mq I just give them an
API that they can call well let's give
them an API so they can start you know
creating their applications faster if
they want to store a state in a in a St
state store like a key value store or
like a database well let's give them a
database and let's not push them to
learn about drivers or where the
database is and all that stuff I will
just give you an API you can start
building your applications you have then
common stuff like reading configurations
or secrets from the environment that
it's very envirment specific so you need
to use bolt you need to use a cloud
provider service or what do you need to
use instead of pushing developers to
learn again let's give them an API and
let's lets them building applications so
if you see uh the application that I was
showing before like with the cats and
the dogs I'm using Dapper here to
basically store the bots in red uh
without pushing the developer to know
about r at all so what I have here for
example I have a go service right so I
have all the all the application modules
in different languages using different
languages on purpose just to connect to
the same Dapper apis from different
languages and I have some for example if
I want to save the vote in a persistent
store that I don't even know where it is
or what it is I will just use a client
in this case to connect to the apis so
what it does basically is just send this
request to Dapper Dapper will know where
to store it based on the environment
I've been working on some more
Integrations how many Java people do we
have here spring boot stuff yeah okay so
a fair a fair amount of people will
understand a little bit more this this
example so I've been working on this you
know Springwood integration where I can
show you uh you know more like instead
of just using an API using common spring
interfaces like this is a spring data
key value template that you can use and
also the messaging template which is
pretty similar to the Kafka template or
to the rabbit mq template this case uh
again I'm uh storing bats by just
calling the key value template update
method here I don't even care where that
boat is being stored I just want to
store it somewhere or if I send if I
want to send a message I'm using you
know the same messaging template send
and then I'm just sending my vat
somewhere right and it's going to be
sent and somebody else can consume it
from there interesting enough like now
because we don't have gafka r or rabbit
mq dependencies in my application my
application now can be moved across
environments even if I'm using for
example manage service provided services
for example for Google popsa for
messaging or or or Amazon sqs I can just
change the Dapper configuration behind
the Dapper apis just to connect to those
services without changing my
application so how does it work I want
to show you quickly some diagrams if
this works because I'm now super scared
that this will not work so how does it
work so you deploy your application you
can be using K native or you can be
using just the normal kubernetes
deployment then you annotate you know
your application with a specific
annotation saying this application wants
to consume the Dapper apis and the
Dapper control plane will basically
inject a side car that exposes these
apis to your application these apis are
exposed via HTTP and grpc so your
application can basically be sending
HTTP request to the daer side car or use
one of the sdks like I was showing with
go or with Java just to connect and do
that connection this is a VI directional
connection that basically means that you
can send data or receive data from
Dapper right in this case uh when you
connect to the Dapper side card Dapper
will read to some environment
configurations about how these apis you
know if I want to store state or send
messages are implemented with real
infrastructure so what I have in my
environment is basically configured that
for messaging I want to use rabit mq and
for storing State I want to use use R
right so the D side card will connect to
this infrastructure and it will allow me
to you know uh run my applications in
the cluster and because now I have
unified interfaces that basically means
that again I can just move my
infrastructure to Google cloud manag
services and my my application will not
change I just only need to change the
Dapper configuration for how these apis
are implemented the same with AWS I can
just switch to AWS or I can switch to
usher and I will have different
implementations for all these
environments making my application you
know a little bit more stable and
portable across environments it's not
that you're going to be moving your
applications from one cloud cloud
provider to another but think about like
running your application locally with
local infrastructure and then moving
into to the cloud with manag Services
the API is the same and because we have
side cars every time that you have side
cars you can do a bunch of things as I
mentioned before service to Service
invocations uh you can have you know
Discovery but you can also have retries
circuit breakers and a bunch of other
things like for example security you can
add mtls connection between the two side
cars and all the communications now will
be handled by that because you are
observing traffic between infrastructure
and other services then you can get like
a unified view of logs metrics and and
traces about how your applications are
consuming infrastructure how much time
infrastructure is taking and exactly
what your applications are doing against
that infrastructure so you can trouble
shoot easier because you have a single
view of what your applications are
doing from uh upper point of view again
I showed you a bunch of things usually
this project will not make any sense
unless you go and give it a try uh if
you take a look at the book it has a
bunch of reposto that are basically
showing all these projects in action so
you can run them in your own laptop and
experiment with an example application
not similar to the one that I'm showing
here but like it's close enough uh and
again this project makes sense when you
try to enable developers to just do more
stuff without learning about complex
environments or learning about cloud
provider stuff
uh this does separate you know the
infrastructure from your application
code and I didn't show that but if I go
here to the application uh I can list
all the daper components it's another
kubernetes resource
components another kubernetes resource
that basically is defined there I
mentioned before that I'm using R post
SQL and rabit mq so I have two what are
called State Stores configured to uh
connect to post SQL and to r i can
describe one of these
uh and you will see that it's very basic
configuration uh which has like two
things that are important like type
that's the implementation type so if you
want to move this to Google you know in
memory database store in memory data
store or something like that you just
need to change this type and then just
provide the credentials here so it can
connect to to that service in your
Google Cloud account right uh and then
it has a bunch of other parameters but
those are actually not important this is
how you index data here maybe you want
to add some hints on how to index data
and I have the same for uh for rabid mq
again I have a rabid mq instance running
here so if I I didn't show you that but
like I have a rabit mq instance a post
instance and a r instance running here
in the cluster that's red uh I think
that's postgress and that's rabid mq
right so the only thing that I'm doing
is I'm telling thater hey you know these
components are here just connect to the
local instances and if actually I want
to start moving my the services to
Google Cloud because my application is
going running on Google Cloud I can just
need I just need to change those
configurations there just for uh
completion let me show you uh components
the Rabid mq1 so you see that it's
basically connecting to that
instance again the only thing that I
wanted to show here is the the type
basically that basically tells you you
know this pu up API of sending and
consuming messages is implemented by
rabid mq from the application point of
view I don't care but from the
infrastructure point of view I need to
connect to Rabbit mq so I need to know
where you know the rabbit mq host name
is and the user and the password to
connect to it right that's just pretty
much what you need to know as like from
from an infrastructure side of things
again because it's a kubernetes resource
you can start defining environments in
git right like you have all these
definitions on how to connect to
infrastructure defining git and then use
something like Argo CD to replicate this
environment somewhere
else and I think that's kind of like
what I wanted to share about Dapper
again trying to share some some kind of
the main points and and some examples
quickly so you can go and research more
if you're interested in that space
specifically uh to finally arrive to
something that open function is not
using but I think that it's also
important to mention because uh I've
been talking about clusters I've been
talking about infrastructure like
databases message Brokers and also like
deploying the application uh but I
haven't been talking about creating and
provisioning infrastructure if you're
working with any kind of application
like the one that I'm showing that is
running on a kubernetes cluster you will
need to to manage and create Cloud
resources including kubernetes clusters
right who created the cluster that I'm
using well you probably will be trying
to automate that using a tool like
crossplane or terraform or pumi are the
the ones in the space I'm usually
concentrated on crossplane because
crossplane extends kubernetes and I
think that that's a very important
difference compared with all the other
competitors so for certain use cases
that makes a lot of sense so again uh we
had our application running in a cluster
we had G native and Dapper installed
there and we have a bunch of
infrastructure so who created all that
stuff somebody needs to create and
configure these environments in a way
that it's reproducible but also simple
to use so a platform engineer can use
something like crossplay that is
something that you will install in your
clusters in order to provision Cloud
resources or resources in general uh
it's interesting because crossplane is
not is not using kubernetes as most
people will use it like most of us will
use it just to run workloads with
crossplane you basically install
crossplane in a cluster where you are
probably not going to run your
applications you will have a management
cluster that is in charge of
provisioning resources but not running
your workloads your applications will be
not running in that cluster at least in
it you know you shouldn't do that I
think uh the main reason uh why is that
is because this cluster will have
credentials to connect to Cloud
providers and provision resources on
your behalf right so what I did for my
cluster is basically I installed
crossplane in a cluster then I installed
the gcp provider so actually crossplane
can provision new resources for me and
how does it do that it basically extend
kubernetes with custom types for cloud
providers right so you can have
something for example like the cluster
resource or the database resource or the
message broker resource for Google Cloud
then you create a jaml file that
basically represents the resource that
you want to create you send it to
crossplane crossplane will create this
resources for you and it will keep
monitoring these resources to see if
they are created and running all the
time and it will report status back if
you go and delete the resource
kubernetes will create it again in the
same way that it will create again a pod
if you delet it when you're running your
applications so it's a it's a a little
bit different model and it also opens
the door for more like multicloud or
cross Cloud uh kind of scenarios where
you can have multiple providers it's not
that you will only have your Google
cloud provider you can have Google cloud
AWS Asher and then send resources
process and create stuff across
different accounts which is kind of like
interesting uh I wanted to show you
quickly I think again I don't know if
this will work but let's give it a try
so I have cross plan installed here uh
and I have the gcp uh provider installed
you can get the
providers and you will see that yeah I
have a provider gcp SQL that basically
means that I have a bunch of resources
related to databases that are installed
here I have here uh the directory here
with just a simple Jamal file which
basically describe a database instance
for Google Cloud right so this resource
basically allows me to say hey I want to
create a new database in my Google Cloud
account and I want to send these
parameters you know I want the postgress
ul5 to be created and I also want to
have a way to connect to it so I need
the URL for that uh database and the
user and password that I will need to
connect the kind of database how big it
is is in which region all the stuff that
you will need to Define when you are
creating a database right and because I
have crossplane installed in my cluster
basically I can just apply this I think
that I need to create this is using some
weird stuff for generating names so you
cannot apply it you need to create so it
will just generate the random name and
basically what I do is just send this
request to the cluster and then
basically crossplane will provision a
new database in my Google Cloud account
in a way what crossplane is doing here
here uh and I know I think that I
just I have the screen
somewhere here so if I go to my Google
Cloud
account uh and if if this is working uh
which is my not but let's check so if I
go to Google cloudsql
what I'm doing with crossplaying is
basically yeah here there you go so um
I'm just codifying a way to create
resources into resources into kubernetes
into kubernetes resources so I create a
kubernetes resource uh which basically
allows me to enter pretty much the same
information that I will be able to you
know fill here into a form in order to
create this database but what crossplane
is doing is automating all the process
of creating and monitoring these
resources which is pretty pretty useful
in general if you are building complex
infrastructure right when I'm creating a
database usually I don't want the
database I want the database I want the
network I want probably some keys I want
a bunch of different things in order to
be able to access that probably I want
like a like a role somewhere so I can
have access to write tables and do stuff
like that so usually it's not that I
want to just create a single thing I
just want to create a group of things
and they need to be uh linked together
and that's where I think that crossplane
actually nailed it with their their uh
definitions and their mechanisms uh and
they created something that it's called
composition so if you go to their
website crossplane doio and look for for
compositions basically what they allow
you to do is to create you know this
composable resources when you can say I
want a CL cluster a database and a
message broker and that will be my
environment and now environment becomes
a kubernetes resource that only exposes
the thing that I I'm interested in
defining when I'm creating a new
environment for example if I'm a
developer and I want to test my
application the one that we deployed
maybe I just want to say I just want
like a development environment so I can
just send a single resource saying
development environment and you get all
the things like a cluster with K native
install Dapper and R and rabit mq all
running for you to deploy your
application I think that mechanisms like
this that allows you to create
interfaces and create abstractions
without actually creating a controller
are extremely powerful and I think that
that's the main reason why crossplane is
so popular nowadays into the cncf space
I strongly recommend you to check it out
again in the book there are like a bunch
of tutorials where you just will go and
use crossplay in different ways to
create abstractions and to deploy these
abstractions in in a local cluster that
uh will give you a different Insight
that when you see it in a presentation
it kind of makes sense in a way maybe
you're using terraform maybe you're
using some of the tools but when you
actually have some hands-on experience
with the tool you actually realize how
powerful this is and how other use cases
you can uh tackle with this and at the
end of the day I've seen many many
people using terraform for provisioning
some stuff and then going into crossling
for doing the management of these
resources that are a little bit more
more sensitive or more uh where you need
just to fine tune uh some things that
you can do with terraform but it's much
more easy to manage
here so crossplane again basic stuff you
create infrastructure using kubernetes
resources more Advance stuff you create
higher level abstractions that you can
use to expose your interfaces that are
more specific to your domain looking
into compositions and composition
functions is a a key thing on the
project and they have been doing great
with that and I've seen a lot of
companies just picking crossplay for
those
capabilities uh and the other thing that
you can do with this is now because you
have some kind of like packaging
mechanism to say all these jaml and all
these compositions and all these
abstractions can be packaged as
containers so I can just package
everything as an oci image share it with
another team that can install it in
their crossplay installation and start
using these resources make it even more
attractive for platform teams to share
knowledge and share these obstructions
across different installations so I
strongly recommend to check that out I'm
running out of time now uh but I wanted
to mention this because I think that
this is this is super super important if
you're building platforms don't build
the platforms on your own just go
outside and check what other companies
are doing I mentioned K serving here and
I needed to mention this because uh
again it's it's a very mature project
that does one thing and does it well do
the AOS scaling of HTTP uh based
workloads it's been adopted by companies
like red in their open shift suite and
BMW tansu they both bundle K in there
because again it's it's mature and it's
being used a lot for those particular
use cases and as I mentioned before
Google Cloud run runs the same apis for
for their containers as Service uh
Service uh where the main idea there is
just to simplify you know the experience
of you know running containers without
needing to know or needing to create
clusters that basically cost a lot of
money and you need to maintain them so
check that out the case of that I
mentioned uh you know the this unified
interfaces for interacting with
infrastructure and building distributed
applications I need to mention that
Dapper was created by Microsoft in 2019
and it's running as part of container
apps Asher container apps so if you're
running containers on Asher you already
have the Dapper apis already there they
running Dapper in as a manag service
there and again if you're are using aure
you just are half way to be able to use
this across across teams and in the the
company I'm working on right now I
agreed we offer two products for
managing you know daa at scale when
you're not running an Asher and you're
running daera yourself and uh Catalyst
which is basically okay a multi uh Cloud
approach for running these apis without
pushing you to manage this these
services and finally crossplane it's
again it's uh cross plan is been uh you
know has been created by abbound the
company which basically offers you know
managed services on top of crossplane
that you can run on their cloud or you
can run on your own accounts in your own
clouds which makes a lot of sense for
for for a lot of companies I've seen
very very large companies running these
Services inside their compute because
most of the time you don't want to
delegate you know this to an external
service like for example terraform
Cloud again uh building platforms is
hard I wanted to show open function at
the beginning because it's a very
complicated project that does a lot for
you but when things go wrong you need to
learn about all the tools that they are
using I wanted to show like each of the
individual tools that I've seen being
used by platform teams when they are
trying to to simplify their operations
uh for development teams or for uh you
know operation
teams uh and I keep saying this because
I think that it's the most important
topic you need to build your own
abstractions and you need to focus
really really hard on what to expose and
what not to expose to your teams if you
want to simplify their their job you
just need to make sure that you have
that right uh and again platforms are
not about adopting technology just for
the sake of adopting technology just try
to measure you know try to measure if
you are simplifying the life of users or
not and in order to just actually do
that you need to prioritize what are the
challenges that they are facing so
adding crossplane because you like
crossplane will not make sense unless
they are having kind like an issue with
provisioning infrastructure and again
don't do it alone just there are tons of
companies building uh products out there
uh and most of these are related to open
source projects so they are more than
happy to engage with companies
implementing these Solutions and help
them to integrate you know uh with
different tools and the entire ecosystem
so thank you very much uh there is a
discount code there if you're interested
in the book and I will do that now
because I have one more minute so let's
do that so I have two copies of the book
and I if you voted at the
beginning and if the window it's of
course it's not open anymore because
it's not
here but I'm using kubernetes so I
should be able to get this sorted out
right uh it should be here there's an
URL somewhere
uh and let's see if this works I just
not trusting my computer anymore from
now on uh so if you still have the you
can see that that's working I know that
like dogs win I think uh but drum roll
let's see if we can find a winner from
the voters check your hash code if
somebody has that hash code that I just
click and delet it there you go that
hash code if somebody has that one you
get a
book do we have it okay yes okay we have
one winner that's the the cats winner
let's do the dogs winner and my computer
doesn't have the mouse anymore there you
go dogs winner drum
rolls you cannot win two books that's
the only thing that I'm saying does
somebody has that one hey there you go
congratulations guys thank you very much
for your attention and apologies for my
computer freezing I cannot do anything
about it right the clust are working
which makes me happy so thank
you we
go any questions uh or things please
please feel free to come and and ask
directly right I will be around today
and tomorrow so I think that's it thank
you there you go