so I am Max
um and I work I'm a distinguished
engineer at IBM
and actually I was one of the people
after Google made k-native public
to uh start contributing to it obviously
lots of folks from Red Hat VMware you
know I'm sure I'm gonna forget some
names but the project has grown
especially the folks that created chain
guard most of them were from Google and
then they created a native
um and I worked on that for about two
years or two and a half years and then
now I'm working actually on sort of what
we call Quantum serverless
so it actually uses K native underneath
but my mission is bordered and just that
it's actually
um you know Quantum open quantum
so we're not going to talk about that
now that was the talk before that's why
I was late but I'm here with my
colleague David Harris
and actually I'll give a lot of credit
to David for this talk
not only for putting it together but
also it came from a blog post that he
had so David Works uh and startup Nation
anybody knows where that is
you all know Silicon Valley right but
there is a country called startup Nation
yes
I've never been but I've collaborated
with so many people from Israel that
it's probably true it's startup Nation
so anyway he's from there he worked 10
years I think trying to build startups
and then you give up and join us
and he's an expert in security and when
he contacted me to help in k-native he's
made a big difference so he's going to
talk about some of the work that he's
also doing but what's interesting about
this talk is that it tries to position K
native as the place you should start so
let's get to it
so obviously you know when you're
talking about cloud computing
um you know in terms of the big picture
right it's pretty much what everybody is
using so I'm you know here because you
know with this is cloud native
and people are using cloud computing for
all types of you know problems solving
problems even Quantum which is what you
know I just came back from a talk on
that
but there is some downside to it and we
wrote a blog post at least for some
aspects of this so starting from the
bottom for instance I think yesterday if
you are the keynote uh folks colleagues
from Azure are talking about this as
well as red hat where there is actually
a lot of energy that's being consumed by
those data centers
and if we keep going in that direction
uh it's not going to help the problem
that we all face I mean I don't have to
tell you we all
you know hopefully you're not a climate
denier but if you are maybe we can talk
about it offline there is quite of
issues with uh you know the climate
right now so what could we do for
instance as computer scientists as
people in a community to make for
instance those cloud computing centers a
little bit more energy efficient so
that's one of the downsides right
and the demand is going to keep going so
it's not a downside that we're gonna
have tomorrow it's a downside today and
it's going to keep going
right
so one of the things that we believe and
we don't have a proof of it so it's not
something I want to want you to bet on
but it's an intuition
and it's that essentially serverless so
the approach of
running software
for just the amount of time that you
need
just the amount of resources that you
need being very Dynamic and how you go
so instead of scaling
and trying to predict the scale you
Scale based on the demand
it's gonna help right partly because
you're using less resources you're using
you know just the amount of resources
that you need
and when you start multiplying this by
all the workloads we're all running in
the rest of the world
the intuition is that it will help
reduce
you know some of the energy pressure
that we're putting on cloud
so we would this blog post it's one of
the IBM Cloud on how we believe you know
K native for instance is a good
direction in that and also colleagues
have built on this with like for
instance Kepler as a model for you to
measure for instance the amount of you
know at least the con the carbon offset
that your computation is is doing so a
lot of clouds you're gonna see is gonna
expose this but that's just one one
um benefit there's a lot more so David
is going to walk you through
the benefits that we've identified of
using K native
not really instead of kubernetes but
using k-native as the way to use
kubernetes and then of course because K
native you can Form K native use
kubernetes if you need it you can also
use it so David thank you can you hear
me yes
so we will start with a question that
this old dog doesn't know the answer for
because every person I would ask would
give me a different answer and which
which is what is serverless now there
are different concepts about what is
serverless we will Define it for this
talk
for this talk we talk about serverless
when we talk about a situation when you
approach the cloud with your whatever
you need whatever service you want to
deploy there without telling the cloud
how many resources the cloud needs to
associate with that service so if you
take away step back and you give the
cloud the decision how many resources
are going to deploy be deployed for your
service and of course it means that the
clouds need to measure that and decide
that for you
then in this in this case this is what
we will call serverless and of course it
goes hand in hand with pay as you go
because if you didn't Define how many
resources you're going to use then you
need to pay as much as you're actually
using
so there used to be this um two options
for you you either use microservices and
you define exactly how many resources I
want 27 parts of this deployment
how do you get to that number is a good
question but that's what I want
and that's the other option which is
serverless which says I have no idea how
much I want it's Dynamic I'll I will let
the cloud do that and that serverless
but the truth is it's not really too
two options it's there is a whole range
of other options you may say Okay I want
at least three pods or at least one pod
running all the time because I want that
Dynamic service like microservice it
answers every every request I have but
then when I need more then please make
sure I have more and I don't care how
many if you want if I if I need 300 use
300. and and then I I may say Okay I
want between three and ten don't ever
use more than 10 because I'm never going
to pay for that
so this is this is a completely dynamic
range and it's uh
um leave the question what is serverless
completely irrelevant and that changes
how we see K native as well
so let's let us redefine what K native
is
K native is your way it's your
automation layer to deploy native
kubernetes services and what is a native
kubernetes service a native kubernetes
service is one that follows the best
practices
12 Factor up
if you are building micro Services based
on the 12 Factor up methodology then
you're probably good to go with k-native
um
serverless of course you as a result of
that any serverless application that
you're You're Building would also they
also comply with 12 12 Factor up and
there would also be considered a native
service and also if you're going for the
new K native functions which is a build
system that helps you create new
Services then those functions at the end
of the day are just container images and
those container images are running
serverless so it's a native
kubernetes service
so so now we make a distinction between
running against kubernetes and in that
case we talked to the cube API and do
whatever we are used to doing or we talk
to that automation layer which does that
for us
so it is like a layer that would
simplify things implement the best
practices for us and we have now less
complexity as a result
so instead of running all and and making
sure that we get all the kubernetes
resources right we essentially have one
important resource to manage
which is a service resource and that's
like a new obstruction layer that is
added to kubernetes to allow us to
deploy our services
um
so that reduces our complexity as a
result it reduces how much we need to
learn or our team needs to learn in
order to deploy and run and operate
those services
um
in a way you can think of kubernetes as
a non-opinionated system it allows you
to do everything deploy anything you
would like
unlike K native k-native is very
opinionated it defines it has embedded
in the best practices and it defines
what are the best practices that you
should follow
now that may be a good thing and that
may be a bad thing for in certain
situations so you don't have to use K
native for all your microservices but
for most of your microservices that will
bring you uniformity that will bring
view as you we will see later more
security it will bring you the ability
to operate faster with your services and
so forth
so this is like instead of getting all
the bits of pieces to create a camera
you get a ready-made camera you can
create great shots with it but you can't
make coffee
so by the way these are in in on the
bottom are examples of how simple it is
to deploy a kubernetes a k-native
service it's just a one-liner but of
course you can use the yaml to do that
and you can Define everything that a
service can have but that's just if you
just want to try to play with it and
create your service very quickly you can
also do that with the CLI
so let's talk a little bit about that
auto scaling that Max also referred to
as as part of our path for for reducing
energy
um so
I want 27 of these and 17 of these and
six of that
and how did you get to those numbers
well I don't know
how do you get to the right number of
resources you need how many pods you
need for each microservice
is that the magical number that you have
in your pocket no you probably over
provision you probably just say 32 that
should do it
and if it will not do it then I'll
increase to 48.
it's a good number why not
when you over provision everything just
everything all your microservices are
over provisioned and that's a very bad
thing for for
managing your resources of course
because it at the end of the day they
all introduce some overhead and they all
consume energy one way or another
um
so so you really need that magical thing
that would follow up with dynamically
with your load and would decide now you
need four now you need 40.
and change the number of parts for you
so Auto scaling is an essential part and
that's part of what k-native offers you
now one more
um very nice
um future that we would have for that
is look at the at that picture that we
see over here we see all those
provisioned pods which are on not being
used
of course when you have those pods
provisioned
you cannot reduce your energy and you
cannot reduce the number of VMS in your
cluster as a result
but if you are able to eliminate them
through some magical way which is an
auto scaler
then you only have a bunch of PODS that
you can control and you know that are
actively working this will give you in
the future as we move forward they'll be
able to do the scaling of the cluster
dynamically reducing now the number of
VMS keeping some VMS extra for your
growth and then growing those numbers
once you start using those extra VMS
always keeping something
because it takes time to bring up a VM
let's be honest
um
so that's another benefit that we have
um which comes with the with K native
the second thing is okay we we are using
microservices most of us are developing
micro services for kubernetes
microservices were designed in that what
in in this uh mindset that you take the
big problem you divide it into small
problems and each problem has a very
defined API such that you can change the
revision of that little piece and
continue growing it growing it
developing it iteratively
so to do that it's very nice to keep all
those revisions as images but you also
need the deployment system the
kubernetes system or the k-native system
to help you do that because there are
risks in in changing revision revisions
you may want to decide that at the
beginning you want to start off with
just one percent or then go to five
percent then go to 25 for this new
revision and over time
you're going to trust that revision
enough and throw out all the revision
and go to the new revision
so revision management is a crucial
thing that you we all need in in
kubernetes which comes as part of of K
native very natively and we will
demonstrate that also later on
um and and the next thing is my my pet
topic which is security
um so
first of all the first bullet
K native Community is presently working
very actively to add TLS to k-native
such that you would not be required to
to rely on your service mesh for TLS so
you could get you could either use your
service mesh or you could get k-native
with TLS without without requiring you
to deploy the
um service mesh
that's first thing second we just talked
about rolling out new revisions that
help you when you have a patch for
security reasons so it will expedite the
entire process of your teams getting new
patches to work because it reduces the
risk of each new patch you can deploy
the patch and see that everything is
okay very quickly and then continue with
that patch so that's another security
aspect of K native the third aspect
we're going to talk in the next few
slides so I'll leave it for now but
basically it says okay we have all those
Services deployed and they're all very
uniform let's use that
and do security and monitoring of those
uniform services because we already
Define how they are going to look like
in the as far as best best practices
we're going to use that for security
and then the the three points on on the
left side
right side if you're sitting
um then um our
um the whole issue which is a very known
problem in security which is a
configuration problems configuration
drift you know every time you configure
a system even if you got it right the
first time
three weeks later someone changed the
configuration now why is it such a great
thing to to do uh K native in in that
respect because most of your
configuration are not done by humans
anymore most of them are done by the
automation
so the humans Define the service the
automation does all the configuration in
kubernetes for you
and set all the configuration right so
even if someone tried to change that
then you have continual repaving and and
it will be redone to the right
configuration so you don't have to worry
anymore from security perspective for
configuration drift and so on
and misconfigurations
um okay so let's talk about the security
use cases that we all face
and the first is that there is a basic
assumption and very naive assumptions by
all
everyone that if you do everything right
then everything should be right
but that's not the reality with cyber
with cyber even if you do everything
right and you follow all the best
practices
your microservices are still vulnerable
well if
if you micro service
team and you say they are well trained
but maybe that's so maybe they followed
all the practices but then they use all
those libraries and you don't know the
people who wrote those libraries and
then those libraries use other libraries
and so on so and so and then it's not
only that you're using development
systems
and you don't know all the people who
developed those development systems
and those extensions that you're using
for your development systems
and your GitHub or your git sorry your
git that you're using and the image
repository and the cacd tools that
you're using and well you're using a lot
a lot of tools and back-end services
with your image
and all of these need to be perfectly
secure which is really unrealistically
by evidence but what we see in the in in
actual deployments
so assuming your microservice is
um safe is a very bad practice
so the right practice for you is we
always assume your micro services are
vulnerable
and that's like the normal situation you
have no idea what the vulnerability is
is but you know they are vulnerable so
someone may use may find those
vulnerabilities may use the
vulnerabilities you just have to keep an
eye on them just you can't just deploy
pods and assume they're safe you have to
keep an eye on them you have to monitor
them all the time and everything that
goes into your pods needs to be
monitored
and you have to have those Gates which
will block anything which is which may
explode your pod you have to have those
Gates which will delete any point that
you have which may become misused
and of course you have all these other
use cases where you already know a bunch
of CVS but it takes on average two
months to fix an average CV
so if that's the case then you are
running with CVS all the time because
you may have more than one you're
running with CVS all the time and you
need a way to
um deal with that maybe you also know
about an exploit which is uh compatible
with that CV so you exactly know exactly
what you need to protect from but you
need to have that protection in front of
every pod or every service that you have
if you put it at the perimeter
then it only protects
against someone who comes through the
perimeter if it's already in in another
pod somewhere then maybe it doesn't
protect you
so these are the use cases that all of
all of the space all the time and now
let's use the fact that we have a very
well designed system with the
microservices
to monitor those services in the old
days when you we were using monolithics
then the same all the requests came to
that monolithic entity and that
monolithic entity the behave in all
different ways for that request it is
that for the other work requested the
other thing and we didn't see everything
that's going on inside
that monolithic application but we are
using microservices right so let's use
that we know that every microservices
should have if it's well designed it
should have a very clear pattern of the
requests coming in
so let's look at what is coming in and
make sure that that pattern that we see
conforms to what we expect to see
let's look at the behavior of each and
every microservice and see the the
behavior of that microservice because
afterwards just code reacting to a very
specific request
so we expect the behavior to be quite
the same every time it processes a new
request
so that that approach which is security
Behavior analytics is implemented as
part of a k native extension called
security guard which you can get with
your k-native deployment security guard
is embedded into the Q proxy of create
native which means that you don't have
to to deploy anything special it is um
every request that you you have already
go through the Q proxy now it's also
being monitored and also we have the
chance of blocking any requests which is
off
we also sit very next to your user
container so at the same time we are
able to monitor certain aspects even
without privileges
even without having special privileges
we're able to monitor your user
container for example any attempt of
your user container to start approaching
IPS he never he's not supposed to
approach
and we also have a machine learning
component as part of k-native which
would learn the patterns so you don't
have to deal and create all those
hundreds of of rules for your hundreds
of services and maintain them all the
time so you have a machine learning that
helps you do that and it creates a
certain a certain rule set and if you
have an SUV you may decide well I want
to change that rule set because I want
to be more strict or I want to make sure
that this rules is fine for me and
protect against this cve and so on
um okay demo just in time
so we'll start by just deploying
um a k-native kubernetes we have the
list of services the list of revisions
and then going to cube CTL we go to the
get the number of PODS and we will
deploy a very just a demonstrate how we
deploy a new service very very easily
with a CLI we'll just need to say the
name of the service the image the
environment variables and we scale it
for one at least
so it can be any number but at least one
and we get the URL already for that
service and we can use it and we can
immediately access it and it will
respond and and we are fine we we
deployed a service
so next let's try to see if what
happened if we load that service
we will start 4 000 connections against
that service and then we will stop those
connections and we start them again so
we start we start increasing the load
the news as you can see the number of
ports just increase to overcome the new
load
um and then when we stopped it the
number of PODS will will adjust and
we'll start it again and we'll increase
again so okay fine that's that one works
so next thing is let's deploy a new
revision so the change that I'm going to
do in the neurovision in a second is I'm
just going to change the environment
variable but I could change the image
just as well
so we will give that new revision latest
is 5 meaning I'm going to give it five
percent of the traffic which means I'm
going to keep 20 95 for the older vision
and you see the number of PODS and the
number of PODS has changed I have up
there in the list of provisions and and
the five percent and 95 and the New Port
for revision two was created so let's
play with it and and change that to 50
and see that the system actually works
um and yes it changes the number of
ports accordingly
and of course at the end I will change
it to a hundred percent so we don't need
revision one pods anymore we have
revision two completely deployed
and
it we may reach a case
where we found after some time that
revision two is not working as we
expected and we want to go back to
revision one
so as long as we have revision one still
deployed on our system on K native then
all we have to do is tell K native okay
please give 100 of the traffic to
revision one
that's all we have to do right now
and the system will adjust
so it's all very nice let's go and see
the security features
which is my project so
not surprising
so we'll start with a simple service and
we're going to use that service and we
assume that already the system was
trained with that service so all the
rules are out there and what we're going
to do is start off with just sending out
query string or a header that was that
is not supposed to be there and we are
monitoring the log at the bottom and we
see an alert coming up and we if you
also notice we asked K native to block
the the requests which are which are
creating the alerts so these are blocked
but it's not only new keys that are
being monitored but also the values and
what's in the value so it could be that
the value is too long for example that
the system already learned what is
expected the length of each value or it
could be the actual content of that
value and I'll
stop for a second and what you see here
for example is that it's been detected
that we were using a curly bracket oh no
rounded brackets and rounded brackets
are being used in in all sorts of
attacks and if that specific value
of that specific service shouldn't have
brackets
then let's block it
let's not let that in
so
that's what the system did
and the next thing is that's let's let's
say that everything went sour
and we actually have an exploitable
service and someone is able to run a
remote shell on that and we will just do
an exact as an example
so we were running an exactly against
our service in a second and
normally when when you're going to to
you you have a remote share the first
thing you're going to do is try to
install something on that pod
so we will try to install in that case
uh
um wget doesn't really matter and the
system detects that there is now a
connection to an IP that is not supposed
to be addressed from from this pod and
there is an alert and there is a block I
mean that that sorry there is a
this uh um pod was deleted as you can
see here it was deleted by the system a
new pad came to replace it because
that's done automatically by by
kubernetes once you delete the Pod
um and um the the attacker is not very
happy because everything that he did
until now
to get to that point is destroyed
so you he start he needs to start over
the attack and it will just repeat so he
will go elsewhere
okay so
um limitations as we mentioned
um it's an opinionated system
so you can't do everything with it you
can't deploy an um SQL database with it
it suits your homegrown microservices so
what do you do how do you handle those
situations when you have something to
deploy which is not
suitable for k-native
um
well you just use kubernetes to do that
it's a mix and match
well
you can use your kubernetes for your any
service which doesn't fit the pattern
and then use k-native for everything
which fits the pattern and normally your
homegrown microservices should fit the
pattern
so I'll ask Max to uh
yes so if all of this wasn't enough for
you in terms of why you should be using
k-native there's actually another reason
and it's a very important one and it's
the fact that K native comes built with
a Eventing infrastructure
and this is important because if you can
imagine a lot of your problems or the
applications that you're building they
are not just a bunch of microservices
it's also which microservices you need
to run what event is going to trigger a
execution of a service
etc etc and when you have to do this you
need it to scale you need to have your
events be I guess you need to to to keep
them in a queue you need to be able to
consume them so you need sex and sources
Etc and the good thing is the designers
of K native so this is uh give credit to
Matt and the rest of the team now at
chain guard they built in Scott
they initially created key native with
an Eventing infrastructure so that comes
in and more and even better you can plug
in your own so for instance at IBM we
put login mq and you can plug in Kafka
for an open source version Etc so
everything else that David told you
there's also even more but to summarize
and conclude
if you think of different actors
in a running system whether it's
kubernetes or k-native you can think of
the developers most of us here operators
probably some of us that are operating
the system and then the users right so
what are the benefits Azure summary for
operators it's more secure because you
can deploy it with guard and add the
rules that you need for the services
that you know you're going to operate
you don't have to deal with scaling it's
going to do it for you it's gonna
hopefully optimize and it's going to
help you reduce costs and reduce energy
right so that's the advantage of
operators what are you operating at a
large scale or small scale you'll get
those benefits for an end user it
definitely will help you scale nicely
maybe reduce cost
and certainly it's going to be greener
so if that matters to you you know this
is something you can mention
and then finally for developers it's
everything that David mentioned so using
for instance a CLI it's super easy to
start training your developers to use
k-native you can do blue green Canary
deployment in a breeze you don't have to
deal with the kubernetes objects
underneath because it's doing it for you
you can scale obviously a lot better and
you can add a security layer that comes
built in so with that let me stop and
invite David back so we can get your
questions
okay
so any questions I think you might have
to yell because yes
yeah go ahead I don't know if there's a
mic so
let's repeat the question so I think you
asked about comparing Dapper with
k-native
uh not familiar with Dapper is it is it
another serverless environment for
kubernetes
okay
I see no I'm not familiar with it so
yeah I don't think we're gonna make that
comparison here but uh
any other questions
yes
I'll repeat it so good
how do you see
[Music]
can can you change grab the rules from
from a developer environment the
cardboard yeah
so the question is about uh the the god
rules and can you put them into cicd for
example
um and and the answer is yes God learned
the rules they are placed in a crd
object so you can take that C or D
object and you can run it through your
CI CD you can read them from from the
cloud you can write them to the cloud
you can define whether to God whether it
who needs to continue learning or stop
learning uh whether it needs to use the
Learned rules or configured rules so you
have a lot of control there that you can
uh they can you can use
for to do that another question yes
so the question is how do we detect the
misuse part this is for the auto scaling
yeah so the auto scaling went through a
lot of revisions and uh you know the the
algorithm is pretty complex but there is
a
part of the code that's actually
monitoring uh the usage
and it's using that to compute it
yeah pretty much but it's it's not
heavily configurable but there is some
parameters that are exposed so you can
you can you know tune it a little bit
yeah the thing that we did really well I
think NK native is that we've had a lot
of uh tests bad so whatever you get out
of K native is tends to be pretty good
and it scales meaning you could run it
for a very large systems and it's in it
and it will scale where they will really
well but you can actually tune that too
if you need