hey everybody welcome to today's
kubernetes masterclass really happy to
have you all joining us today kind of as
usual we have just a massive number of
people who are interested in this topic
and there is a lot to go over so we're
gonna we're gonna dive right in here but
while we're we're just at the beginning
I want you all to know that this session
is being recorded and you will get the
recording and the slides after the
training and we're talking about
understanding and implementing service
mesh today and there's a lot to go over
so let's let's jump on in as a way of
introduction my name is Matthew Shearer
marketing manager here at Rancher I
helped put on these advanced trainings
and our intro trainings as well which
I'll talk about a little bit more as we
go please use me as like a point of
contact a resource at Rancho I'll do my
absolute best to respond to everybody
you can reach me on the ranch or user
slack which I'll also talk about in a
moment a little bit more and on email so
don't hesitate to reach out but the man
who's really gonna be doing the heavy
lifting today is is Eamonn feel engineer
here at rancher Amon are you are you on
the line are you there I think I'm here
good morning everyone huh all right
awesome I'll let Amon introduce himself
a little bit more as we go I also want
to give a big shout-out to a couple
engineer other engineers who stepped up
to help us out Jason and Sheldon because
we have a lot of people on and we want
to absolutely be responsive to
everyone's questions make sure that you
all get what you came here for so on
that note we have you know about 75
minutes scheduled we might go a little
bit long if needed because you might
have questions or for whatever reason
again this is meant to be responsive to
what you all want to learn so please do
put your questions in the chat ask
passive questions that you do have we
just ask that you keep them to the best
of your ability sort of on topic if for
whatever reason they're a little bit
outside the scope of the of the training
then we might refer you to another
resource we do have you know fantastic
Doc's other training sessions and things
like that that we can point you to go to
webinar has a really cool chat feature
so just put your question
into that tab and we will get to them as
we are able to will also have a lot of
time scheduled at the end to just answer
you know all the questions aloud for
everybody's benefit so on that note if
for whatever reason you want your
question to be private just let us know
otherwise we will we will answer it
aloud for everyone's benefit because
this is educational as I said in the
beginning this session is being recorded
we put all of our sessions all of our
trainings on YouTube so you can check
them out there on the rancher youtube's
channel we go have trainings that go
back you know a couple years we put our
online meetups and our intro trainings
there so there is just a ton of learning
available and as I mentioned there is a
slack channel just for these master
classes where we can post slides or you
know answer some additional questions
later on but rancher user slack is a
huge huge community there are thousands
of members and hundreds of people asking
and answering questions every day our
engineers are on there as well so if
you're not you know part of the
community I think many of the people
here already are but if you're not
highly recommend joining and answering
and asking your questions they aren't
just getting plugged in and finally
there are a lot of other fantastic
classes coming up our monthly online
meetup is next week which should be
super exciting because we just drop
Rancher 2.4 and it has a ton of awesome
features a lot of a lot of stuff is
going on there and Shannon Williams who
is the president and co-founder of
rancher and Darren Shepherd who is the
chief technology officer I'd be leading
that one so it's gonna be super super
interesting a lot of Engineers will be
on there asking and answering questions
as well and then we have a master class
the following week and I also put here
the the intro to rancher and kubernetes
training which happens every week so
please do check that out if you are new
to kubernetes if you're new to rancher
if you want to understand you know how
Kublai's works architecture components
things like that that is a fantastic
resource and it is free and happens
every Thursday so again I'm gonna turn
this over to Eamon and just remember
that if you do have questions please do
put them in the chat
we have some engineers who might help
answer there and we'll take a couple
pauses during during the presentation
and mainly at the very end to answer
your questions so without further ado
Amon I'm gonna pass this off to you tell
me so see here all right let me go ahead
and share alright perfect do we have my
screen yep you're good to go excellent
so thank you for the introduction Matt
and getting everything you know set up
and set the stage there my name is Eamon
Bauman I'm a fuel engineer here at
Rancher labs and today we're going to go
through understanding and implementing a
service match so jumping right in
without too much talking to do here
understanding service match we've got an
agenda here the first thing we're gonna
do actually it's right in the title of
the presentation is to understand
service mesh talk about what it is why
we may need it in certain situations
what problems the service mesh solves
things like that we're gonna go over
some basic service mesh concepts as
probably most of the audience knows
there are a large number of service
meshes out there so I'm gonna try and
touch on points that are common to all
or at least most service meshes
specifically SDO is the one that we're
gonna spend a bunch of time with today
because that's the one that the ranch
42.3 product and we're now on 2.4 so
it's been out there for a little while
now that's what the rancher product
integrates is is do during our demo
we're actually going to set up and
configure sto using Rancher so we will
walk through live and unscripted and
installation of this do into a rancher
provision kubernetes cluster will do a
bunch of setup and talk about how the
integrations work within Rancher and
then I've got some final points and wrap
up you know some next steps and things
to talk about there so jumping in let's
understand service mesh we're gonna go
through a brief timeline here so if we
put on our you know Dolby surround sound
theater voice in the beginning there
were monolithic applications and then
there's a big picture of this giant
monolith and the weird little people
down in the corner who I'm assuming have
now
discovered this magic monolith but
unfortunately to their demise the
monolith runs on Java no I'm kidding
Java was a perfectly fine language had
to drop in the joke there anyways
monolithic applications so whenever I
think of a monolith I always kind of
think of the Washington Monument
honestly I always think of that that
well I mean there's the picture right
there on the previous slide right this
giant sort of towering thing of stone
rising up into the clouds right so I
always think of the Washington Monument
in software engineering though a
monolith is a and this is a quote from
Wikipedia just so you know I did my
absolute best high school research here
a monolith is a single tiered software
application in which the user interface
and data access code are combined into a
single program from a single platform in
typical Wikipedia fashion that is a long
explanation with a lot of words to it
I'm a much simpler person than that
so it's an all-in-one piece of software
a monolithic application is one code
base for everything in your app so the
user interface the data access layer the
datastore itself and sometimes you can
get a little fungible with those those
concepts so maybe not there's a user
interface because you may have like a
web application for instance right and
your back-end side of that web
application has the business logic and
the data access layer that in itself is
a monolith even though the user
interface is separate right so a
monolith is a single tiered software
application or like a one to two tier I
guess it's kind of what I'm gonna add as
a wishy-washy bit of definition there
there's a great link that Chris Nova put
together back in the original FTO days
before they were acquired by VMware and
this blog post has an awesome what is a
monolithic application diagram and
explanation that shows you how different
pieces fit together into a model list
you could kind of understand exactly
what that monolithic thing is now this
is how folks have written applications
for years and years and years and years
and years and decades and for so on you
know until the beginning of time right
that we have built tradition
the applications to be all part of one
cohesive unit one stack one however you
want to describe the collection of those
things so if we've done that and if
we've been building our applications
that way for so long what's the problem
well it turns out the problem kind of
depends on who you ask so issues with
monolithic applications become apparent
typically as the application and I don't
have it here in notes or is the
organization scales so you're really
going to start to see issues when you're
scaling up a monolithic application and
typically these issues arise if the
monolith isn't prepared for that scaling
or isn't capable of it natively the
first point really is vertical versus
horizontal scaling so if we've set up
our application to be a monolith a lot
of those monolithic applications are not
set up to be scaled horizontally
vertically then is usually the first
option that organizations take when we
start talking about scaling a monolith
so instead of adding more instances of
this monolithic application we're going
to toss more resources at the server or
whatever is running this model it's
right so we're gonna scale up CPU we're
going to scale up memory maybe we'll add
more bandwidth for traffic to that
single node but we're still scaling you
know a single instance of the monolith
because a lot of those are not prepared
to be scaled horizontally right
horizontal scaling often requires
changes to the application to make it
horizontally aware the reason I say that
is that a lot of monolithic applications
are not stateless horizontal scaling and
kubernetes if you're familiar and if
you're looking at service much probably
you are are a lot of those applications
that are stateless are very easy to
horizontally scale there's no state that
needs to be shared amongst the different
instances I can scale out one two three
five hundred and instances in my
application to get the scale that I need
because I don't typically need to you
know share that state between the
instances monolithic applications and
and sometimes you can also include a
legacy definition in there as well are
not horizontally scaling aware scaling
vertically then is the best
and usually the first option
organizations take but you hit a limit
where it starts to get expensive or may
not solve the problems you need we're
adding more resources to the single
instance may not be feasibly because of
some other constraints like you're
hitting a bottleneck at the database or
you're hitting a bottle back in the
number of threads and there's no more
CPU you can add right where you have to
horizontally scale so that's one issue
another issue you may run into his
deployment velocity so as mano lists are
getting bigger and remember that all
these issues are as the application
scales so as your monolith is getting
bigger your time to release for features
can slow down and that can be an issue
for an organization where if you are
expected to be nimble with this
application and respond to changing
market trends which sounds like such a
marketing thing you're gonna have
challenges with that as a model that
gets bigger some of these challenges are
technical right like it could be a
compile time where your application
because of its size and because of its
code base takes 30 or 40 minutes to
compile a full set of the application
that's possible but oftentimes it can be
organizational policies and play to
where any changes to the application
require a full change control board
review require you know a sprint to be
set up and all these things where your
velocity is sort of dampened when you're
trying to be nimble with new feature
deployment because the organization has
put different things in place and and
and rightfully so with the scale that
you're seeing another issue as the
application scales is a choice of
tooling so a monolith almost by
definition is built on a single
technology so we had in our picture
there just before that Java logo you
know a Java EE application it could be a
dotnet application could be C++ whole
bunch of different things but almost by
definition your monolith is going to be
built on that single technology the
challenge there is that there's only one
toolset to lean on it's also a strength
because then there's only one toolset to
learn but if you remove that are there's
only one toolset to lean on so you can't
use the right tool for the job
where if you have a new feature you want
to add or have some sort of optimization
you
want to do that some other language or
some other technology may be well-versed
for you have to sort of wedge that in
using whatever technology or monolith is
built in so that can be a real challenge
and the final point is developer
understanding so really just this can be
summarized as the bigger the application
the more difficult it is to grasp so
grasping the entire application is
something that can be necessary
especially as developer gets up to speed
and they want to start making changes
but they don't understand how those
changes are going to impact other areas
of the application and the bigger the
monolith gets the more difficult it's
going to be to ramp up developers in
order to be productive and understand
all areas of that application it may
even be impossible at some point where
you just have to start limiting the
amount of impact that new developers can
have on your application so that's one
of the challenges are actually rarely
for the challenges with monolithic
applications and again these all become
apparent as the application or the
organization scales what I'm going to
introduce to you now is a sample
monolithic application and the reason
I'm doing it here has become this this
is gonna help illustrate what we're
talking about when it comes to micro
services and how we're going to break up
a monolith and how some of this is going
to impact the service mesh discussion
we're having later
so our first application that we're
introduced in this monolithic
application is a book information
application now if you've ever messed
around with this do or deployed it or
done anything like that this is probably
pretty familiar but in case you haven't
booked info is the ISTE Oh introduction
basically to service mesh so what I've
done here is sort of abuse that example
and turned it into our monolithic
application the book info app has
several components the first of which is
a product page the product page is the
user interface that grabs information
from a bunch of different data sources
those data sources are detail data I
should I should back up and explain book
information is a simple application that
shows a review and ratings of a book so
if you go in your web browser and you
open a
the product page I get to see the name
of a book its author its ISBN number all
that kind of stuff I get to see details
about the book I get to see reviews and
ratings about the book that's our
example application so all of those
pieces of functionality are brought into
our monolith here so I have the book
info with its product page I have
detailed data so the product page will
pull in details about the book like the
author and the ISBN number and stuff the
product page will pull in information
from review data so how did someone like
this book they've given it a review we
can view that information in the UI and
then finally ratings data so if a user
leaves a rating how many stars out of
five did a particular book get so again
we're displaying information about the
books this is the data access and logic
layer for getting details about our book
this is data access and logic layer for
getting reviews about the book and this
is data access and logic layer for
ratings about the book so let's talk
microservices we have our sample
application and might I'll back up one
last I we have our sample monolithic
application in mind so let's talk about
micro services and why they may make
sense the goal of micro services is to
build an application as a suite of
services hence the name micro services
services are independently independently
excuse-me deployable and scalable the
goal being that in a micro service
architecture each service because the
services are separate is going to form a
boundary with the other services that
boundary is typically the form of an API
that each service offers so typically
though not always services are
accompanied by an independent codebase
sometimes you can do a mono codebase a
model if the codebase I think is what
they refer to it as but typically there
are separate code bases for these micro
services the process of converting a
monolith to a set of micro services is
called quote breaking up the monolith
with a suite of micro services what
we're really doing is taking the
different functions of what was a
monolithic application distributing them
amongst tiny little applications
I mean each one itself you could
consider it if it was a full application
to be a monolith but really it's just a
component of a distributed application
now each one of these services then is
going to offer
well a service or a function right the
boundary that's formed with the other
services are rather the contract that's
executed between these services is
typically the form of an API so it could
be a REST API we may be talking G RPC
something like that but the services are
meant to almost by definition of Micra
services to act independently of each
other so let's take a look at what's
splitting up this model if we look like
so we have our book information monolith
over here I've got the product page
detail review and ratings data on the
Left all as components of this
application if we split this up we're
going to move the product page out into
its own component so we may take that
set of functionalities for the user
interface split it into its own code
base and then offer it as an API maybe
this is just the browser arriving at
this UI and the UI we'll make other API
calls to other micro services well by
doing so and by moving this component
out of that monolith we've built our
first micro service which is the product
page let's take our business logic and
our data access layer for book detail
information we'll move that out into its
own code base now the product page is
going to be able to query for
information about books from that
detailed data micro service so then
we've built our second micro service
we'll do the same thing with review data
we'll move it out into its own code base
and we'll build a micro service around
it same with ratings data out into its
own code base and now we have a micro
service built around it so what we've
done here is we've taken our monolith
and we've taken the different areas of
functionality in this monolith we've
moved them out into their own code bases
and again that's typically what you do
but you can have one code base of deploy
micro services from them it is an option
but we've moved all of these out into
their own instances and created micro
services from them thus our book
information application ceases to be
that monolith on the left and actually
is the collection of all of these
micro-services so now we have a
distributed application where each one
of these micro services can be
independently deployed distributed built
scaled they all have their own velocity
of deployment you know kind of searching
for four different examples to tie into
right so if I go let's step back here a
bunch of slides now that we have there
are a lot of animations to slide back
through here we go so now if we have
each one of these feature sets in its
own bucket a bucket being its
micro-service now our vertical and
horizontal scaling issue is solved
because we can take one instance of that
micro-service and horizontally scale it
out or vertically scale each one of
those instances so we have easier
ability to to scale that piece of
functionality of our application our
deployment velocity is accelerated
because now areas of functionality can
be rapidly iterated on without
necessarily impacting other areas of the
application where if we're going to do
work now let me slide over here if we're
going to do work come on just on like
the ratings data section here if that's
split out into a micro service we're not
going to affect review data or detail
data or the project page by making
changes to that micro service so we sort
of insulated different areas of the
application from changes from one
another so long as we adhere to that
contractor that API that we have as a
boundary between the micro services then
we're safe our choice of tooling now is
open so if we have our areas of the
application split out into micro
services I can write one piece of
functionality in Python I can write one
piece of functionality and dotnet I can
write another in golang whatever works
best for that specific approach we've
also now added developer understanding
because a developer may want to know
sort of abstractly how the entire
application fits together but concretely
they only need to know the micro service
that they're working on and you can now
accelerate a developers I guess you know
mean time to production if you will I
mean time to productivity
allowing them to just have that abstract
concept of how the application fits
together but the concrete knowledge can
be slowly introduced through allowing
them to work on different micro-services
and they can remain productive even if
they only have sort of a brief
understanding of the application as a
whole so let's jump ahead back so we
split up our monolith got our different
micro-services here so if we've got all
these micro-services where does a
service mesh come in or quote why do I
need this thing this slide and and what
we've gone through so far have been okay
monoliths are great what's the problem
with them why do I need microservices
service mesh why do I need that enough I
have micro services if micro services
are an approach to solving monolith
problems at scale a service mesh then is
approach to problem excuse me an
approach to solving micro service issues
at scale one of the micro service issues
we're going to run into is routing and
terminating traffic so as we distribute
different areas of our application into
micro services we need to make routing
decisions across things like versions
for instance or if I'm deploying
different versions of a micro service if
my details version has V 1 V 2 V 3 V
whatever I'm going need a way to make
routing decisions across different
versions of that micro service because
maybe some of my clients still need to
use V 1 functionality maybe we want to
do you know sort of a sample deployment
of V 2 functionality I need to make
those determinations based on different
criteria we also may need to terminate
different things like TLS certificates
so what happens if my micro services are
expected to be hosted for different
tenants maybe I need to do TLS
termination across different host names
so that's another option we also may
want to enable features like weighted
deployments canary blue-green deploying
things like that we need a way to be
able to split separate and route that
traffic between our different
micro-services another issue that
happens when micro-services sort of ramp
up an end and we're scaling
micro-services is load balancing it's
essential to load balance micro-services
now there's a whole definition in the
whole site about how micro services are
built
many sites actually and a lot of how you
build a micro service is to remove state
from that micro service so you want to
give your micro service the ability to
scale horizontally well as you start to
enter the world of scaling horizontally
you need to load balance your traffic
between instances of micro services so
load balancing becomes really an
essential operation as we're
horizontally scaling different instances
of these micro services so as part and
parcel of load balancing we're going to
need to understand that architecture but
not only understand it we need to know
how to implement so doing things like
round-robin load balancing least weight
equal weighted that kind of thing we
need to set up those sorts of approaches
for load balancing we also may need to
do something like circuit breaking so as
applications become distributed it's
really important to prevent cascading
failures this is easier to do in a
monolith because your business logic is
so tightly tied together that you can
sort of write in logic where if this
error happens then you know return right
and and your your control flow of a
request through to response can be
broken by that simple return from the
execution before another handler accepts
that that flow of traffic through the
application with micro services and
that's not so often the case so a micro
service each independent section may not
be aware of failures in a prior section
so if bad data comes from a prior micro
service as part of your your flow of a
request your instance of a function here
may not know that it was bad data from
that prior micro service call so a
circuit breaking functionality needs to
take place where you can then stop
cascading failures in your application
and and and basically have that return
function that says up sorry our
applications unavailable right now so
circuit braking really prevents these
cascading failures by shutting down
portions of an application depending on
certain criteria and this could be
things like 500 errors this could be
things like bad output bad data things
like that there's a whole bunch of
different options but but searching
great circuit breaking really prevents
those cascading failures the other part
that can be really important
in service meshes mutual authentication
now when we have a bunch of different
services at play it's really important
to verify that both sides of a
conversation are who they say they are
and that can really certainly have
security implications because I want to
know and ensure that there are no
malicious actors you know that everybody
is who they say they are so I'm talking
in a secured manner with folks but it
also can be part of authorization
authentication as well we're mutual TLS
can't say I verify that this person is
who they say they are so they are
allowed to take these actions right so
mutual authentication or EMM TLS can it
can really check a couple of boxes in
that security thing I can make sure that
there is security between the
conversation of multiple micro services
but then that authentication and
authorization can also come into play
and make sure that different folks are
allowed to perform different actions so
let's jump in all those things can be
done without a service mesh that's the
kind of the part that's missing here
so routing a terminating traffic load
balancing circuit breaking em TLS all
these things can be done without using a
service mesh a service mission I forgot
to animate this the service mesh
infrastructure Eliza's these things i've
coined that word that's my word you have
to use it now the service mesh
infrastructure Eliza's these different
concepts so instead of a developer
having to independently or team of
developers having to work together to
implement routing you know and traffic
termination to implement circuit braking
temperament all these different things a
service mesh takes these components and
makes them part of the underlying
infrastructure layer the goal then is
that the application developer does not
need to spend cycles on building these
things for their micro services that
they need only to configure the mesh to
provide this functionality for their
micro services so I've got a next slide
here this is a caveat and this is that
quote-unquote who you ask part there are
exceptions to all the rules so
everything this is the throw everything
out the window that I've just said slide
there are exceptions to all rules so
don't believe that just because your
application is getting bigger that it
needs to be broken up
in other words just because you have a
monolith doesn't mean you need
microservices in that same vein just
because you have microservices doesn't
mean you need a service mesh monoliths
have existed for years decades without
issue micro services are great and and
really this applies to service mesh as
well it's great if you meet the use case
both technically and for your
organization so these are technologies
to solve a problem like so many other
technologies they're an investment they
require care they require feeding they
require talent devoted to working on
these technologies it's like bringing
kubernetes into an organization it's
like bringing a virtualization tech it's
like bringing a new software stack it's
like anything right you should not use
any of these things just because just
because this is shiny and pretty and I
want to and mess around with it that's
fine if you want to do that at home but
if you want to use these make sure that
you meet the use case both technically
and for your organization so don't use
this just because because service mesh
adds such another layer of complexity to
your infrastructure that you may run
into issues if your organization is not
prepared for it okay that's my last
slide where I talk about like a teacher
and take to the teachers office here so
let's talk about service mesh concepts
there are a lot of service meshes out
there I've got a few on this slide so
we've got sto linker D I don't know how
to pronounce this that's mesh or Maish
because I never learned if traffic was
traffic or traffic but it's something
it's mesh or mash one of the two there's
consul and there's kuma at least now
these I of course lifted shamelessly
from the CN CF landscape on service
meshes but there are a lot of other ones
out there netflix has built some
Facebook I think has some there's a
whole ton of them out there what we're
going to be talking about in common
concepts for the service mesh are things
that most of these service meshes
implement so I say most in in little
stars or little quotation marks there
because some of these service meshes may
not have exactly every concept I'm about
to share but most of them
to the things that we're talking about
the first one is traffic management so
back on that that microservice issue
slide traffic management is one of the
big things that a service mesh brings to
the table with a service mesh we're
going to infrastructural eyes again
there's that word I've defined we're
going to infrastructural eyes the
concepts of routing load balancing and
ingress I've listed egress as a
sometimes there because that's again one
of those features that some meshes
implement some don't but routing in load
balancing ingress these are concepts
that almost all service meshes are going
to implement egress is the concept of
taking traffic and having it leave a
mesh from a predetermined node so having
that as a functionality can allow you to
make interesting security decisions like
all traffic from this node should or
should not be denied or and it's it's
mostly a firewall and sort of outside
the mesh security concept most meshes
are going to implement some level of
security so we're certainly going to
have authentication authorization
probably as a part of a mesh so making
policy decisions based on who and why
and then most meshes are going to
implement some sort of mutual security
which typically takes the form of M TLS
so verifying that you know both parties
in a conversation are who they say they
are client verifies the server and the
server verifies the client the third
pillar of these common concepts is
observability so in a service mesh we
want the ability to monitor to log and
to instrument our micro services now
again there's that term infrastructural
eyes we can monitor our applications
outside of the mesh because we could
just tie in you know Prometheus exported
metrics or with logging I can just grab
standard out and standard error from
some container running an application
that's fine but observability
infrastructure realizes this and says
okay let's monitor our applications as
part of the infrastructure let's let's
instrument them and do distributed
tracing across the infrastructure for
all these different micro services so if
we break down traffic management
the first one is routing so we want to
make sure that we have the ability in a
service mesh to get traffic from service
a to service B so this is the intra mesh
traffic so we're going to make
determinations on where to send the
traffic these will
routing decisions that we can base on
things like HTTP headers that we can
base on things like TCP ports and TCP
destinations and sources then we can
base on really any number of criteria
but the core is that we're sending the
traffic from one place to another so
we're making a routing decision also
part of traffic management is load
balancing so when I use a service mesh I
want to have the ability to do
round-robin weighted least traffic
different kinds of load balancing for
our micro services if a development team
implemented those pieces of
functionality independently they maybe
into the application itself integrating
load balancing concepts you know
integrating health checks things like
that where if we infrastructural eyes
these things we can have the service
mesh load balance for us we can have the
service mesh in the case of least
traffic determine which instance in a
micro service set is receiving the least
amount of traffic so I don't I don't
need to build these concepts into my
application the ingress resource this
would be bringing non mesh traffic into
the mesh so this is how do I get
requests from end users how do I get
traffic from outside external services
into this mesh we have this concept of
ingress if you've used kubernetes this
is a very similar concept because
there's the HTTP ingress in a lot of
kubernetes clusters and that's bringing
non cluster traffic into the cluster so
it's the same kind of thing with the
mesh ingress is bringing non mesh
traffic into the mesh then sometimes we
also have the concept of egress so we
want to send traffic out from this mesh
through predetermined nodes and again
that's typically a security piece of
functionality but it also may be
something for end user usability right
where let's say in our fantasy world
that we have a service mesh that spans
the globe I may want to dedicate egress
nodes force excuse me for certain bits
of traffic that send that traffic out
through exit nodes that are close to my
end user so we can do like geo-located
egress nodes where someone may send
their traffic in or a server may send
its traffic in in California
but it may aggress the mesh in Germany
close to a user right so that could be
one of the use case
under security for a service mesh often
is really the first concept and this is
who are you who am i who is this thing
usually it's service based so instead of
it being this is an independent person
who's with the mesh it's typically this
is a service so often takes the form of
setting up that this service is who they
say they are when they are communicating
on the mesh now that ties directly into
our Xia our authorization piece which is
why or what are they doing so I guess
it's kind of what and why again this is
usually service based thing so now if
we've completed our authentication and a
service when talking on the mesh can say
I am service a then the mesh can
implement authorization and say ok
service say you're allowed to do XYZ
actions right so authentication is who
are they
authorization than in a service mesh
what and why mutual TLS then services
mutually verifying each other
typically this happens via common CA
where the certificate is issued for the
client and the server is sourced to a
common certificate authority thus the
server and the client have a common
reference point to verify each other
that's kind of glossing over em TLS
that's a little deep for what we're
doing today but know that a lot of
service much does have that
functionality and it's something worth
exploring more the final pillar that
we're talking about is observability now
this slide with apologies to the whole
observability industry is going to kind
of abuse the term there's a great line
from honeycomb their website honeycomb
dot IO and there are an observer ability
organization and they say in the world
of software products and services
observability means you can answer any
questions about what's happening on the
inside of the system just by observing
the outside of the system without having
to ship new code to answer new questions
observability is what we need our tools
to deliver now that system complexity is
outpacing our ability to predict what's
going to break that's a whole great
paragraph and and I'm about to abuse the
term observability like I said again
observability is a discipline unto
itself
it is observing the outside of a system
without adding anything new to that
system in this case our observability in
the terms of service mesh is we can add
in monitoring so we're gonna take a look
at metrics about our traffic flows we
can monitor different incoming requests
outgoing requests take a look at the
return codes for those and start
building metrics about the performance
of our application simply based on the
traffic flow so instead of monitoring
application instances themselves which
you also should do you now have the
added ability to monitor the traffic
flow under logging we can capture
traffic logs as a sampling of the
traffic flow instead of app based
logging or actually that instead should
be in addition to so capturing traffic
logs now we can capture when a request
comes in where is that request destined
what is the request ID if we want to do
things like distributed tracing what is
the content of the request so if
something goes wrong in our application
or in our micro service we don't have to
rely on that micro Service working well
enough to output a log we can see that
traffic arrived at that micro service
and something went wrong so it gives us
sort of an enhanced visibility into the
traffic flow
finally instrumentation is the third
idea under observability so we can
perform distributed tracing that the
service mesh will link together for us
now what we're saying is in the service
mesh if I have a request that starts at
one micro service and bounces to another
and bounces to another and bounces to
another before returning to the end user
I can tie all of those requests across
the mesh together and perform
distributed tracing so in a monolith
this would just typically be a normal
tracing action a normal debugging action
where you would trace the flow through
different functions that are being
called in the app there's direct
handoffs of function calls and returns
and you can see all of that within your
software when you are working in a
distributed application in a micro
services world it's not as easy because
you cannot directly debug one
application and have introspection into
a completely different application when
your micro service is finished executing
so having this ability to do distributed
tracing and tie together these requests
as they float around the mesh is a
really powerful technology that really
enhances your ability to know and really
observe what's going on inside this mesh
okay pause for just one second I'm gonna
take a drink of coffee because I've been
talking a lot okay I'm sorry you had to
hear that
now it's tio concepts so we spent all of
our time so far talking about monoliths
and micro services and what is the
service mesh let's actually take a look
at what is a service measure what is is
tio how does this tio work there's a
bunch of core components to sto we're
going to deploy them today you're gonna
see them in action the first section is
the data plane in this do sto is built
like a lot of different service meshes
on envoy envoy is a proxy server it is
build independently of all these service
meshes so sto didn't build envoy envoy I
think was actually built by lyft if I
recall correctly envoy is a proxy server
that is controlled in this instance by
Sto so envoy is this proxy server runs
is a sidecar to service containers in
kubernetes so when you deploy a pod Sto
injects envoy as a proxy into your
deployed pods and then sto controls
envoy which in turn helps you route
traffic and so on the control plane is
collectively what controls Sto so in
this control plane here we have pilot
pilot is coordinating service discovery
traffic management and resiliency
features so pilot is sort of one of the
big core components of ISTE au which
helps you do all of the traffic and
routing decisions within your mesh if
that handles all the traffic and routing
then Citadel handles the security so
Citadel is the security component for
sto that we be used for mutual TLS we
use it for encryption and credential and
policy management so Citadel is the
control plan component responsible for
implementing auth end of the mutual to
LS things like that that we've talked
about so far galley is the final
component of ST O's control plane and
that's a configuration
Lading processing and validating layer
the goal of gali and this is actually
lifted directly from the SEO Doc's
the goal of gali is to isolate sto from
the layer that it's running on or from
the infrastructure that it's running on
so sto shouldn't have to be vulnerable
to any particular Mis configuration in
kubernetes gali is going to ensure that
any configuration passed into is do by
way of kubernetes
is valid that that configuration is
translated into internal sto
configuration where in kubernetes it may
just be you know a yam a manifest or a
custom resource definition right so
Galle is a processing validation
translating layer that that isolates the
underlying infrastructure from isolates
this do rather from the underlying
infrastructure and translates user
configuration the final component on
this page that that's not really an sto
component but it's really valuable is
something called key Olly so key ally is
it's not a true as to your component
it's a third party integration and what
it gives us is visibility for the
management of this do so Kyoya is an
awesome tool that allows us to see
traffic flows in sto so seeing what goes
where it allows us to configure
different pieces of functionality to you
know track metrics if we have for me FES
and Griffin and enabled Cal is just this
great tool to manage sto ok so if those
are the core components of this do what
are the building blocks then well the
first building block is a virtual
service a virtual service is a thing it
is a a concept is an item that defines
how requests are routed to a service so
as you see in parentheses what goes
where when we talk about virtual
services what I really want folks to
focus on is the concept of virtual an
sto virtual services not a real service
so a real service for example there is
something that answers requests a
virtual service it's an abstraction that
helps us define routing policies we'll
get to in a second how we actually get a
request to a real service endpoint but a
virtual service is the first stop that
abstraction allows is if I'm going to
keep
new words today abstractions is a
service a destination rule then is what
happens when we want to connect to a
real service endpoint so a destination
rule defines what happens to requests
when they arrive at a virtual service so
if we compare a destination to rule to a
virtual service DRS are used against
real service endpoints so a destination
rule is going to define things like load
balancing for instance where if I send
traffic to a virtual service when that
traffic arrives at a virtual service the
destination rule determines how the
traffic is load balanced across actual
real services that are providing you
know well a service it's kind of an
overloaded term but that are providing a
function right so a destination rule is
real implementation against real service
end points where a virtual service is
how do I get traffic to a service we
have a third cup or excuse me a third
component which is a gateway a gateway
manages how traffic enters which is an
ingress and how traffic leaves or egress
is the mesh we have service entries
service entries are a method or a thing
by which you can add endpoints to the
service mesh that exists outside the
mesh so this is important especially so
I have an example there databases let's
say we're running inside of a service
mesh we have our micro service and that
micro service needs to call a database
that maybe it's a legacy database or a
third party it doesn't exist within our
service mesh the service entry
functionality allows me to add endpoints
to the service mesh so that my traffic
can traverse the mesh and egress to that
database without having to well not take
advantage of any of the surface mesh
concepts finally often and off see
policies so these are who do what and
where in a service mesh so Austin and
Ozzie inis do is what allows us to
define who can do what things in the SEO
service mesh we're gonna take a look at
book info as Anna Steele example here so
I'll show that a picture again this is
our micro service application that we've
up again remember we went from a
monolith to a microservice we moved all
of our functionality out into these
micro-services book info is SEO sort of
hello world example application we're
going to deploy book info into SEO and
SEO itself will be deployed by Rancher
so as you're gonna see here Rancher
makes it super easy to deploy sto and
manage its capabilities um if you've
ever done the book info deployment
through is do you know that deploying a
steel can be a little challenging you
know that deploying the book intro
application and setting up all that
stuff is typically done by manipulating
Yambol manifests and doing a bunch of
cube control execution Rancher has a
bunch of helpers that are going to make
this easier for us one word of caution
here is that this is not going to be an
exhaustive demonstration of book info so
I'm not going to go through any of the
advanced concepts in book info because
there are a lot of different steps in
the sto documentation on how to set this
up and and use different pieces of
Ischia functionality but really what
this is is helping us understand how
Rancher implements this do and how
Rancher can help manage the sto service
mesh so we're really only going to go
through a couple of examples here so
it's not going to be an exhaustive
demonstration okay I've bored you enough
with slides so now it's time for a demo
as with all of my webinar demos I'm
going to need everybody to raise their
right hand so you're all sitting at home
all in quarantine maybe enjoying a
quarantine II that would be nice maybe
I'll have one later raise your right
hand and repeat after me
i webinar attendee do solemnly swear
not to hold a man bow man responsible
for any mishaps that occur during this
live demo so help me kubernetes okay now
that everybody has sworn that othon it
is legally binding just don't ask a
lawyer we will actually go through and
do our demo so let me move my slides out
of the way here and we have our let me
log back in here instance of rancher
let's go ahead and get this set up so
I'm going to click on my aim and ISTE ol
earning cluster here and this is a
sample cluster that I have set up and
this is running kubernetes 117 for it's
a little ec2 application that I've
deployed
straight forward a little you see to
cluster I should say that I've deployed
pretty straightforward not much to it
it's got one control plane one Etsy node
for worker nodes as you can see here
just a basic simple cluster what we're
going to do now is deploy SDO into this
cluster so this is using rancher too far
to which is our latest release of
rancher if I go under the Tools
drop-down here at the top I can go to
ISTE oh when I click on SDO we have a
bunch of different configuration options
for deploying sto into this cluster
first of all we're going to a need to
enable monitoring monitoring will deploy
as a rancher feature Prometheus Angra
fauna there was a great masterclass by
some person last week on monitoring so
go ahead and check that out if you'd
like to what we're gonna do here is
enable monitoring and then we have
different configuration options for
deploying the different components of
Sto I'm gonna scroll down here to this
ingress gateway by default ingress
gateway has not turned on when deploying
is do through Rancher so we're going to
enable that
now this cluster does not have the
capability of setting up load balancers
so we're going to fall back to our node
port functionality here and we'll send
HTTP and HTTPS traffic through on three
one three eighty and three one three
ninety so now that I've enabled that and
set it to node part we can hit enable
here and Rancher will go through and
install this do for us so let's take a
look and see what's happening jump to
our cluster drop down here and we'll go
to the system project inside the system
project then we can see first of all the
cattle Prometheus namespace has been
created and all of these monitoring
components are being set up
so Prometheus and Gravano right off the
bat are being deployed on my behalf
just by clicking that enable for iste i
functionality so I'll wait for a second
for those to deploy but while those are
playing I can scroll down and see
there's an sto system namespace that's
been created here so all the different
sto components like Citadel and gallium
pile of things that we talked about
those are being deployed into this sto -
system namespace so we'll give those a
second to deploy but once everything is
completed we will have a fully
functional sto service mesh installed
into our cluster just
by hitting enable pretty cool so wait
for those to become healthy scroll up
let's take a look and make sure I don't
think that will go healthy because of a
what's saying oh no it's just not ready
that's all so we'll wait for that to
become ready scroll down here wait for
this STL piece to become ready so then
once that's set to go we'll be able to
deploy our book info application and do
some basic configuration steps cool so I
have three one three eighty and three
one three ninety as my node ports that
have been deployed here and that should
become ready in just a second so we'll
let that go now let's jump back into our
default the echos jump back into our
default project here and the first thing
we're going to need to do when we deploy
the book info application is make sure
that our default namespace is ready for
sidecar injection it already has been so
I'm gonna just disable it for the time
being what this takes the form of is in
the background in the sto instructions
it asks you to label a namespace and and
you add sto - injection enabled as a
label to the namespace with in Rancher
we've made that just a button click so
you can enable sto auto injection so by
doing so we get a little sailboat icon
that shows up there so now our default
namespace is ready for is do to
automatically inject sidecars now that
we've done that let's actually go and
deploy our book info application let me
grab that workload here real quick just
you know and grab our book info yeah Mel
this is the only portion that I'm
basically gonna use cube control for so
we'll open a cube control so I can get
nodes we've got our running STR cluster
so let's K apply - f and then this
manifest so this is from is Tio's actual
instructions for installing book info
and it's a Yambol manifest that sets up
the services and deployments for our
book info application so I will apply -
after this and all these different
things will get created when I close we
can visualize in Rancher that all of my
different micro services have been
generated so that's our picture of our
micro services right here's our product
page functionality
here's ratings details reviews v1 v2 and
v3
these are all microservices that
together are providing our book info
application so we'll wait for that to
come up now because we have deployed
this using no port I should be able to
actually browse to that node port and
see our product page so let's go to our
system cluster our system project here
scroll down into Sto and we can see I've
got my ingress gateway running on part
three one 380 so if I click on that
here's part 3 1 380 let's go to product
page and is this using HTTP because it
should be what cluster is that what
that's running on that one why is not
loading 3 1 3 83 1 380 that should be
loading a thing interesting flash
product page come on let's take a look
at the logs and see what's going on here
we have a few seconds to poke around a
bunch of warnings bunch of things let's
just kick it I'll delete it we'll kick
it we'll set up a new instance deploys
on the same post I was nice so I'll copy
that and see if that interesting that
should have worked on that maybe we can
schedule it on different node real quick
this is why I have everybody swear the
live demos that won't blame me for
things that go wrong because things that
googly do go wrong so we'll run all pods
on a specific node we'll run them on
worker 3 save that and that'll restart
that ingress gateway run it on a
completely different node so we'll copy
that so our node port 3 1 380 doesn't
work excellent
what about 3:1 390 what about HTTPS
let's see if that works
HTTPS interesting totally doesn't work
that's not cool
give me just one second I'll keep
messing with this may have to just
redeploy a couple things in this geo
here to get this working let's take a
look at our services here so under
workloads what a service discovery this
do ingress gateway 3 1 3
let me refresh that hard refresh and see
that note port updated still on that
same endpoint weird okay I am going to
redeploy that workload so let's check
and redeploy see if that updates that
node port functionality
what's that upgrade whew this might be a
CPU utilization thing interesting oh
that is not good let's see if we can
jump into a different cluster that has
sto enable I think we have another one
as a helper here so ec2 cluster let's
take a look yes do is enabled okay cool
let's go to our system project I think
we can still get away with doing this
here system project that is not deployed
darn that is really unfortunate see if
we can fix this one then just you
learning background of the system
doo-doo-doo-doo in grass gateway still a
bunch of failed pods okay let's delete
those huh get rid of all that garbage
see if we can scale that down and get
those running down this was work
little bit of God's unfortunate let me
see if there's any other workloads that
are using too much CPU okay that looks
right back under systems or anything
that's taking up too much I really would
like to get this do you work for you
folks here must just be a bad cluster I
was messing around with it a bunch today
I must uh those are going away we have
that one running okay where's that
running on let's change our node
scheduling and allow it to float here
pick node scheduling rules save that
will allow it to float somewhere else
you can get this working okay that one's
running on that IP so let's go there
call on through and three eighty still
unloading make sure the right part maybe
I'm using the wrong port here tools sto
scroll down and grass gateway three one
three eighty that should be the right
port slash product page no-go
interesting that is unfortunate I wish
that was working let's disable sto I'm
going to try one last-ditch effort to
get this working so let's disable a sto
and monitoring and will redeploy here
real quick so I'd love to be able to
show you folks this this is a cool demo
let's let everything unda ploy here
remove that sto gateway go into our
default project
our workloads can stay deployed that's
totally fine our namespace can stay with
the injection that's totally fine will
redeploy is do here so removing that
okay so the namespace should be gone now
almost that namespace get rid of the
finalizar on that name spell namespace
yes do - system oh gone perfect okay
let's redeploy this teo tools sto go
down here ingress great way enable that
use node port let's change the node for
it 3-3 380 all right three two zero
eight zero cool three two zero nine zero
okay let's try that will enable those
different ports we will go back and let
sto redeploy into our system project
resources and workload scroll down here
and wait for that to deploy there's
monitoring Cal Prometheus and we should
see us do up here a second amps you can
see under apps there's this do being
deployed there's cluster monitoring
being deployed so they actually are just
installed as chart applications back
under workloads there's this do coming
up swole wait for the ingress gateway to
come up and all that related tooling
when we go to that URL we should see our
product page so the ingress gateway
should take care of routing that traffic
on to our page so we'll wait for that to
get set up if I go back under default
here we've got details we've got our
project page we've got all that stuff
I'm going to redeploy this stuff real
quick so we will use our URL to delete
and redeploy so okay delete that chef
and there's our URL we'll get rid of all
those deployments and services so that
we can redeploy fresh so we'll wait for
sto to come back up and be healthy back
under system ok looks like SDO is up if
I go to 3 208 oh I still get that but
let's still deploy those workloads and
see if that makes a difference maybe I
deployed too
okay so let's deploy this so okay apply
- F and then our book and foot IMO we'll
deploy this so now that we've deployed
that we should be able to reach our
instance so we've got product page
running here okay if I click on the
product page we see ISTE oh there's the
proxy that's been injected so that
sidecar injection has occurred as
expected if I go under my drop-down
where in the system project here let's
grab three 208 oh can I go to slash
product page No
that is disappointing I apologize
everyone that had been working the seven
times I tried it prior to just now but
unfortunately it didn't let me walk you
through what we would have been able to
do so if that had worked what I would
have walked you through here is back
under the default project we would have
deployed our workloads here as you can
see so we have our book info application
when book info is successfully deployed
you get this web interface that shows
you information about the book it shows
your reviews it shows you ratings
details all that kind of stuff what the
book info tutorial has you do through
the ISTE Oh instructions is set up on
the first thing is set up traffic
management so we configure request
routing to say when someone logs into
the book info application show them
rating information when they don't log
into it don't show them rating
information what we can do is under the
resources drop down an sto we can
configure destination rules and virtual
services to set things things excuse me
these things up there no virtual serve
that's weird
I wonder if that's what's going on hang
on one second let's deploy the virtual
services could that be it I thought they
deployed with that okay resources work
if this works I'm gonna kick myself
scroll down my on the right cluster yes
system 3 208 Oh TCP product page I was
hoping that was the case okay so anyways
back in the default project under is do
you would be able to manage creating
these virtual services so again the
virtual service is where does or let's
define abstractly a service so we have
our four services details product page
ratings and reviews and while I created
those through Yambol just there we can
add a virtual service using ranchers
interface so I can define in my virtual
service well let's pick a host to send
this traffic to and now we can make
routing rules based on incoming headers
or the method or the URI or even the
scheme here if I want to to send traffic
to different subsets like v1 v2 v3 of
this rating service so I can configure
that application so now under
destination rules I can change and add
things about destination rules which
allow me to define where I want to send
the traffic to a particular service
endpoint so if I want to say that I
wanted to find a subset there's my v1 as
defined in the virtual service how do I
want that traffic to end up at a
particular destination well under the
ratings here I can add subsets and
define different versions for this
destination rule I can also add gateways
so if I want to add an ingress gateway
here or an egress gateway I have that
option through is Gio's functionality
and Rancher here traffic metrics and
draffa graphs are functionality that's
imported from key Olli so we're this to
be a healthy cluster and again I
apologize I wish it were were this to be
a healthy cluster the metrics and
traffic graphs would show up here
imported from Cali so we could see those
pieces of functionality so here's that
graph showing up
there's my different services that I've
deployed so there's if I scroll in
there's my details virtual service my
product page ratings and reviews all
that kind of thing those show up here
inside Rancher so you don't need to
necessarily go out to that ISTE or
excuse me that key alley instance
troubleshoot those things okay since
there's not a lot else I can do here
without history of working I'm gonna
jump back to the slides I again I
apologize folks I wish that had worked
in it and it did you know those 300
times I've tried this before so I run
that wrap up in summary so we deployed a
steamer using Rancher we certainly did
do that so in the cluster tools and sto
at the cluster level is how you would
deploy sto into your kubernetes cluster
Rancher will deploy and manage those sto
components for us so we installed sto as
a helm chart under that system project
and now we can configure basic as to
your resources using Rancher so as you
can see under the resources and sto
drop-down Rancher has manageability of
gateways destination rules and virtual
services so the first portion of the
book info tutorial within isseo is
deploying gateways destination rules and
virtual services and we're our demo and
was our demo had to have worked we would
have been able to set up those different
resources directly from within Rancher
Rancher then we'll import traffic graphs
and metrics from key ally so we can
visualize those things advanced topics
that we didn't get to cover well really
any topics we didn't get to cover on
circuit braking is something that ISTE
offers we would have been able to stop
traffic or even redirect it when certain
situations occurred so this would have
been things like if we had too many 500
errors that were showing up over a
period of time if there was a specific
response from some kind of health check
on a service something like that we can
define different criteria by which we
would like to break the circuit yes he
also gives us the ability to do fault
injection so if I wanted to inject
faults into the traffic flow to
troubleshoot and prepare for any issue
should they happen if she allows us to
do that so if I want to say hey let's
test what happens when 50 percent of my
requests yield 500 errors yes you will
inject those 500 errors and we can test
what happens when our application fails
then another thing we wouldn't have
gotten a chance to look at what about
observability so disturbin tracing via
Jaeger would help us uncover complex
service to service issues and again
that's that functionality where I'd be
able to see a request as it flows
between different services in my mesh
and be able to trace that request from
point A to point B
finally mutual TLS would be able to
verify both client and server are who
they say they are so where would we have
gone with the demo have worked on SEO
has a great set of documentation on
their website so sto Denio that's where
I've spent a bunch of time doing more
research and learning about it there are
plenty of other service meshes in this
category so if you check out the CNCs
landscape you can see all the different
service meshes that CN CF has on they're
well on their landscape and then finally
ranchers sto functionality is available
in our documentation sotius Rancher comm
slash Docs and then on that website if
you go into our ranch or 2x
documentation and look under the cluster
admin section you can find information
on this deal for whoops didn't mean to
click on that for rancher itself let me
go back here where do you want to learn
more and get more help with the rancher
user slack
so check out slack dot Rancher at i/o
I'm on there so if you want to come
badgering me about this not working
you're more than welcome to find me and
yell at me rancher forums this is one of
the most active forums I have seen in
the technological community at least in
the cloud Native community we are
constantly posting help topics issue
resolution with clients with open source
users new product announcements forums
features all that kind of thing those
are available forums Rancher com finally
we have a github repo github become
slash Rancher slash Rancher that is
where all of our application code lives
everything the rancher does is
completely open-source so please come
check out our code file issues file
requests for assistance anything you
want
check it out github calm slash ranch or
slash Rancher so thank you again I
apologize I wish that demo had gone as
you know prepared maybe I'll put a video
together for the next time I do this but
find me on github if you want I'm Eve
almond on github you can find me on
Twitter and aim and be or don't find me
in real life and I mean that even
without the quarantine so thank you I
guess Matt I'll I'll answer questions if
they're already yeah there are there are
a lot of questions Amon and thank you so
much for going through all that is
bummer that demo didn't work but you
know that's life so it's live approves
that it is live for everyone yep so and
thanks Jason and Sheldon for answering
so many questions in the chat even
awesome so
let's let's start going through here um
let's see let's do this one is from Jew
who says what do we know what do we need
to know that we should deploy and use is
geo and our micro service environments
how do we know we need service mesh in
our system you're typically going to
know you need service mesh when you
start running into either repeated work
or issues with doing sort of the things
that I listed on that so let me actually
scroll up and find where's that that
slide here we have a great slide so
where does service mesh come in let me
get my notes out of the way so if you're
starting to as you deploy your service
mesh do a bunch of repeated work for
setting up load balancing doing a bunch
of repeated work for routing and
terminating traffic really that there's
a lot of toil you know and not
meaningful work being done a service
mesh can really help take care of all
that so you don't have to do it
yourselves
another thing is where maybe you're
starting to have issues with doing this
and and issues as sort of this broad
term because it could mean really any
problem top to bottom right but if like
for instance you're having issues
bringing up you know new devs and
getting them used to the idea of setting
up routing and terminating traffic maybe
take that out of your new developer
training and make it part of the
infrastructure or if you're really
running into a challenge with how to
appropriately implement something like
circuit breaking in your application or
mutual authentication instead of having
to actually do that work yourselves at
scale again let the service mesh handle
that now this is all fine stuff I think
to learn and to implement at a small
scale right like if you've distributed
your monolith and you've broken it up
into micro services you're going to do a
lot of this by hand and that's totally
fine because that may be all you need to
do right like if you have one monolith
and you break it up into micro services
and you implement routing and
terminating you implement circuit
breaking you implement all the stuff
independently and then you don't have to
do it again you just scale your
application you may not necessarily need
a service mesh right like it adds so
much more overhead for work that you've
already done but if you're adding new
micro services you're constantly sort of
reinventing the wheel every time micro
service comes out or you're doing this
work over and over again that's where a
service mesh can
help awesome and a kind of a follow-up
question I think you sort of at and
answered this but just answer it
directly so Oladipo and several others
have asked you know can't he basically
says can't kubernetes do the things
service mesh solves like load balancing
using services and self-signed
certificates it can yes and in fact
there's a great presentation by Tim
Hakan who says that kubernetes is the OG
or the original service mesh right there
are a lot of these pieces of
functionality that already exist within
kubernetes but there's also a lot of
pieces that don't exist within
kubernetes so like circuit breaking is
not a functionality that kubernetes
offers out of the box while it may offer
load balancing and decisions like that
advanced traffic routing doesn't
necessarily exist within kubernetes
because with like HTTP traffic for
instance I have ingress options for
sending my traffic based on a host or a
path name but when I'm inside my my
measure inside my cluster right I don't
necessarily have that same option unless
I'm integrating it directly into the
application so yes kubernetes does do a
lot of this stuff but it also doesn't do
a lot of this stuff - cool ok makes
sense all right
more questions on implementing service
mess mesh when you decide that you do
want to use it so this is from Sammy who
asks should we enter the service mesh
directly via the ingress controller or
is it more recommended to enter the
cluster using ingress like nginx in
route to the isseo ingress
I've seen it done both ways honestly in
my opinion I would just do it on the
service mesh ingress and hop on the mesh
as as quick as possible because you you
sort of get all the features of the mesh
like the observability and the logging
the second you get on there and if
something's going wrong on a layer
before that mesh you'll lose those
troubleshooting features it also just
helps from a simplicity sake where if as
soon as I enter the cluster I'm also
entering the mesh I don't have other
things to troubleshoot and other things
to worry about
you can also declutter if I and this is
again inventing a word declutter if I
your ingress resources just by allowing
the service mesh ingress to take care of
it where you may have other applications
using ingress that are not serviced mesh
aware so you can sort of simplify that
configuration it's a little hand wavy
there but I would try and get the
traffic on to the mesh as quick as
possible but everybody's gonna have
different needs yeah next time thank you
okay here's the next one and a few
people have asked this you know what's
your opinion if you could compare and
contrast this do versus one dirty sto is
more mature and linker D is lighter
weight so SEO has a lot of features that
linker D doesn't necessarily have yet so
linker D is gonna be newer but liquor D
is also a lighter weight implementation
of a service mesh um it's the reason we
used it for our reo application because
REO itself was designed to be a
lightweight thing and n SEO has a lot of
components that need to be installed in
order to make us your work where where
liquor D doesn't necessarily have the
concepts of pilot and Citadel and galley
and all those things that's just a
lighter weight like a link or D
basically they're runs um in terms of
feature completeness
you know linker D is going to give you
sort of everything that I showed on this
common concepts may be - like egress and
MPLS I had though I don't remember if
this linker D has that it has most of
everything else here SEO has some other
advanced concepts that aren't listed on
this page and the SEO Doc's have all
those details so it really is just a
maturity versus lightweight comparison
at this point
though now in each one of those favor
sto is being rewritten for sto to which
they're going in a much more lightweight
direction I think they're actually
taking the ISTE o components and
monolith the sizing them again I keep
inventing words today they're there
they're sort of D breaking up they're
there they're distributed approach for
their service mission they're making sto
D as a single monolith which will
hopefully be able to take advantage of a
bunch of performance improvements and
linker D because the velocity of that
software is going to certainly mature
rapidly as time goes on and become more
feature complete so I think you're gonna
have answers to both of those comparison
points where it should be an interesting
horse race kind of in the next year so
to see who's going to be better at what
makes sense okay cool thank you all
right here's next one and I'm probably
gonna butcher your name sorry oh yeah so
while it goes from Jehosaphat who says
what's the performance impacts if we use
sto MT OS with authorization and
authentication I'm gonna be perfectly
honest and say that I don't know
I have not implemented that in one of my
applications I would imagine that it's
non-trivial mainly I'm saying that based
on the fact that sto itself that impact
is non-trivial I don't know the specific
performance implications of enabling M
TLS though I would be very interested to
see graphs and comparisons you know
against some sort of baseline to
determine what that is so unfortunately
I don't have a direct answer for you but
I again I'm gonna kind of hand wave and
say non-trivial but I'd like to see more
okay cool
sort of related this is from Nikolas who
asks and it's kind of this is a kind of
a coup grantees compute resourcing
question he says do we see minimal
footprint in terms of computerization
relative to a non SEO deployment you
know versus an SEO deployment
can you read the question to me one more
time I'm sorry I think I lost the
trainer yeah no problem and there's
other people who have asked asked a
similar question I think so I might try
to find another phrasing he says do we
see minimal footprint in terms of
compute utilization for a non sto versus
sto deployment I think he's maybe he's
asking like what is the computer
utilization of using sto versus not
using um each one of the components has
a document I think - they're they're
compute utilization I'm gonna say it's
heavy and I'll actually show you inside
here inside Rancher so if I go to the
sto learning and I go under sto here
like if I look at pilot we've got like
one CPU and four gigs of RAM as a
limitation for pilot and these
limitations I think we're really born
out of a moderate usage level so I don't
have an exact minimal amount but just to
say that we're limiting it one by four
which is almost the size of like a t2
not small right I think it's like to my
4 is it teacher dot small so pilot takes
up a lot of resources mixer is sort of
an older technology they've they've
deprecated the use of it I think in
favor of galley but the mixer telemetry
here we're limiting at four by four so
these components are actually really
heavy and if we deploy all these and
let's say they use up to their limit
that we're in a heavy configured thing
we've got a one by four of pilot a four
by four of mixer and distributed tracing
we've got a half by one and then I
didn't even talk about out of the
galleys listed in there so almost we're
talking probably about five or six CPU
by what what I'm guessing would be by
five or six gigs of RAM which in bigger
clusters probably not the end of the
world but then again in bigger clusters
you're gonna see scaling up of those
components so really take a look at what
is Tio's documentation has in terms of
scaling but it's going to be heavier
than you think awesome
very helpful and um since I think you
might have just answered this with with
five to six gigs but David says I've
been testing monitoring sto and logging
on my clusters but I keep running into
memory or CPU limits what is the
recommended cluster size cluster I will
say that that largely depends on other
workloads if you're installing just
monitoring and just sto into the cluster
I think that what I've developed here is
probably the baseline because we've had
issues with this one and this is a four
node each with two by eight that we've
been running into pretty heavy
utilization on so you could maybe go a
little smaller than this I could maybe
do a three node of to buy a these are
all teacher Don larges you could maybe
do a three node you know of two by eight
nodes here but I certainly wouldn't go
much smaller than that so you could
probably establish a pretty simple
baseline of worker nodes as at least six
core and what's three times eight 24
yeah
24 gigs of ram which is pretty heavy
when I think about it yeah cool thank
you okay there's there's several more
questions and I know we have gone over
kind of our schedule tiny'mon are you
able to stay on a few more minutes and a
couple more markets okay cool okay well
we'll wrap up let's find couple more um
this last one is from Jude says can we
run elastic search in is teos in service
mesh is to your service mesh I don't see
why not
though that's such an elastic search
specific question I'm not qualified to
answer it um my understanding is that
you would be able to so long as you're
logged collectors are able to hop on to
the service mesh and you know insert
their traffic into elastic search so as
long as that traffic can occur because
elastic search from my understanding
speaks mostly HTTP for the log trans for
the log transiting um that it should
work but again your mileage may vary and
I am far from knowledgeable about
elastic search okay cool all right here
what will have this be the last question
naman this is from since you have to go
this is from
who says I'm still a bit lost on the
application example itself what do I do
and how do I route to the service is
there anything to do on the application
code itself yes so let me go back to my
screen here and that's one thing I I
definitely could have explained a little
better so splitting up the monolith
we've got this picture over here on the
right what would happen typically in
this case is that your micro service for
the product page would went broken out
from the monolith be basically rewritten
from the ground up
so you'd probably reuse some of the code
and certainly the logic from the product
page but you would rewrite it so that
instead of having a direct dependency on
calling like a a details function like
maybe you have a details class that has
a bunch of different things and then
there's a method you can call on some
details class and the product page calls
that method to get information instead
you would have the product page call out
externally to some sort of details micro
service and this is where the mesh
really helps and this is and I think
this is great this is what I should
change these slides up to explain a bit
more the product page micro service
should call out to some generic detail
service it shouldn't have any idea of
the existence of a specific micro
service it should just know that
somewhere out there being outside of
itself somewhere externally to the
product page there exists a detailed
service so the product page simply
queries service at some predefined API
endpoint now that may be G RPC that
could be just some kind of you know REST
API whatever you want but the product
page makes an external Network call to
get something from a detail service so
the act of making that call is what
service mesh concerns itself with where
the mesh will be able to say okay a call
from the product page to the detail
service should go to this virtual
service in terms of this do or we're
going to be routing some amount of that
network traffic from the product page to
the detail service to a new instance of
our service so that would be where like
the traffic management component would
come in so yeah basically every micro
service here should
be making Network calls to other
microservices depending you know
completely on protocol on things to
retrieve the information now that would
be compared in a monolith to making like
a direct method or a function call I'm
in a different area of that monoliths
application code okay
awesome thank you okay I think since
we're you know since we're over time
we'll end it there there are some more
questions in the chat we've gotten to
many many of them if you didn't get your
question answer then please join us on
on the user slack on the Masterclass
channel and we can we can follow the
follow up with you and afterward but I
think we will over there is there is
there anything else you want to leave us
with Eamonn before other than to say go
out install Rancher on your own and try
this obviously the live demo failed and
that wasn't great but it does work it
did work for me last night it did work
for me this weekend so please go through
try and set up the book intro tutorial
on sto don't let this failure shy you
away from the functionality that we have
this was just some sort of transient
thing that got messed up sorry I really
encourage everybody go try this on your
own you're gonna have a cool experience
awesome
yeah I agree and we do a intro to
kubernetes in Rancher class every
Thursday so this is a great opportunity
to join one of those we'll talk a little
bit more about server smash there so
that's a that's a good next step next
week also is the 2.4 online meet up with
a walkthrough Darin Shepherd or chief
technology officer is gonna be on there
and Shannon Williams as president of
Rancher will be on they're both kind of
leading the way explaining 2.0 or 2.4
there were quite a few questions about
you know whether 2.4 is production-ready
in it and all that that is the place to
get those questions answered
this is 2.4 just dropped this past week
otherwise thank you all so much
Eamonn thank you for your hard work
really appreciate it and Jason and
Sheldon great job answering questions in
the chat too so we could save a man's
voice box a little bit here and we will
be posting the recording on YouTube and
sending out the slides to everyone so
don't worry you'll get all that later on
today alright everybody have a
rest of your week talk to you soon
thanks Amon thanks everyone
bye