so hi everybody
welcome to today's introduction to
kubernetes and rancher class
so you are well hopefully you're in the
right place if you thought you were like
on a plane to las vegas or this was a
cooking course or something like that i
can
cook but that's not what we're teaching
you how to do today instead we're going
to teach you
in the next 90 minutes everything you
need to know
about kubernetes well everything you
need to know to get
started to get off on the right foot and
um
and start doing stuff teach these
classes they're super chill
um and it's only me so i'm allowed to do
kind of whatever i want
so that's me i'm the director of
community and evangelism for rancher
labs
and if you tweet about the training
please use the hashtags ranchertraining
and rancherkates as far as all of that
stuff about how to contact me don't
worry
you will get a copy of the slides at the
end
and a link to the video and so if you
feel like reaching out to me after that
great you can
we have stuff to do see i was getting
ahead of myself i was doing the intro
and housekeeping and i hadn't even
gotten to the agenda that's how excited
i am to be here today
all right so we're gonna do all this
stuff intro and housekeeping we're gonna
install k3s
we're going to then go through
kubernetes and customize and get you
that good solid foundation that you need
and then we're going to install rancher
and then we're going to go through how
to use rancher but that part is actually
really short
and then if there's any questions left
we will answer them
this is the part where i say ah but if
you look at that go to webinar panel
over there
there's a section for questions as you
think of questions
please put them there
and then i'll answer them you don't have
to know anything about kubernetes to
enjoy today's class you should know a
little bit about docker but honestly
we don't really use docker either you
just need to kind of understand what a
container is but if you don't understand
that
you'll probably still walk out of here
with a lot of really valuable
information
everything that i do today is actually
in
a repo that repo is here and let me
change the little news crawler to a
different one so if you don't copy this
down fast enough it'll scroll across the
bottom of the screen in a second
clone that there's a readme in there i
literally copy and paste from the readme
so that i can give everybody the same
training every single week except for
days like this where i'm super manic
uh and so yeah you can follow along
rancher has tremendous documentation
use it don't use it well use it don't
use it during the class
pay attention to me but pretty much
everything you want to know about how to
use rancher
k3s rke and the various other things
that we have going on you will find in
our documentation
this is also all open source so if you
find a mistake or a typo
or something you can edit it you can
submit pull requests and we love
it when the community does that we also
have
resources for you we have the rancher
users slack
which has about 20 000 people registered
right now
at any given moment in time 24 hours a
day there's several thousand people
logged in there that's the primary place
to go if you're looking for community
support
but it rolls off the top of the screen
and disappears into the slack ether
so there's also the forums and the
forums is a place to post questions
where
there needs to be more conversation or
to go search for stuff that that might
have a longer life
myself and other rancher engineers
monitor both of those and they're both
very active
community places so use them both
we get people in this class who don't
actually know what rancher is
so i've got a couple of slides that's
just going to very quickly explain
our approach to kubernetes in the
enterprise
and what you need in order to be
successful
in your kubernetes journey
we make software our software is 100
free and
open source so everything you see me
doing today you can do
it's not like open core you pay for
something you get more features
it's all out there for you
we do sell enterprise subscriptions
which is a support contract and has some
other stuff but it's not related to the
features of the product
ultimately i would love for you to use
rancher's products
but what i'm about to describe you can
apply to anything that you're doing with
kubernetes
it basically says that there are two key
pillars of a successful kubernetes
strategy
there's pillar number one which is a
certified kubernetes distribution
and there's pillar number two which is
centralized management and that can get
broken down into shared tools and
services
security policy and user management and
consistent cluster operations
let me close that little news crawler
there so it stops getting in the way
now we of course make software that
satisfies these requests certified
kubernetes distribution we have two of
them
one is rancher kubernetes engine also
known as rke
which takes all of kubernetes and runs
it inside of docker containers
that's it it means that you have fewer
host dependencies
all you need is a host with a supported
version of docker
and you just do a basic config and run
rke up and blam in about 10 minutes
you've got a multi-node ha kubernetes
cluster
we also have k3s which is our
lightweight distribution of kubernetes
it runs all of the kubernetes components
in 512 megabytes of ram
so it works really well in
resource-constrained environments like
iot
and the edge there are also
cloud provider kubernetes distributions
if you're just starting out these are a
great place to start they run the
control plane
for you which means that you can just
focus on running kubernetes workloads
and it's important when you're starting
off on this journey that you have the
fewest number of obstacles the control
plane usually runs fine
but when it doesn't
it sucks so having somebody else
responsible for that is helpful now you
do pay for that
obviously these solutions do cost money
if you're wanting to run stuff locally
on your machine
k3s is a great place to start
once you've got that layer settled then
we move into the
management layer and rancher which is
our flagship product
is the most widely adopted kubernetes
management platform
it has over 30 000 installations it's
got over 100 million downloads
it's 100 free and open source
and it focuses on production quality
kubernetes
anywhere everywhere by delivering on
those three things
so for consistent cluster operations it
gives you provisioning version
management visibility and diagnostics
monitoring and alerting and centralized
audit
for talking a lot for security policy
and user management
you've got automated processes for
applying a consistent set of user access
and security policies for all of your
clusters
no matter where they're running and for
shared tools and services
it provides a rich ecosystem catalog of
services for building deploying and
scaling containerized applications
this includes app packaging ci cd
logging
monitoring and service mesh a bunch of
other stuff it's a multi-cluster
management solution
once you have these these these these
these these
swap something else out for rancher if
you want you can swap something else out
for a certified kubernetes distribution
but once you have that foundation well
then whatever you put on top of it is
going to be successful
i already told you about k3s it's
lightweight it's fast
it's designed for production
environments it works great for
developer environments
but it's different from mini cube micro
cades kind and those ones that are
designed just for dev environments
you can run k3s locally on your machine
do all your development against it
and run it just fine out in a data
center just fine in a resource
constrained environment
the documentation for installing k3s has
you sshing
into it and then running some some k3s
startup commands
but alex ellis who's the guy behind
openfast and inlets and arcade and a
bunch of other really cool open source
projects created a tool called ketchup
that is designed for installing k3s over
ssh and that's what we're going to go do
right now
i have here a node sorry that's totally
not true
i have here a terminal session
and we're gonna go install k3s so you've
got ketchup install is that too small
i usually run this at 1280x720 i feel
like that's too small
now i have to resize the window hold on
a second
there we go that looks better
all right so ketchup install pass it the
ip of the host that we're going to
do the installation and tell it who
we're ssh in is and
ketchup by default is pinned to a
particular version of k3s but they don't
move at the same pace
so there might be a newer version of k3s
that you want to use that's different
from the pinned version
that's the case here we're going gonna
install 117.7
there's actually newer versions than
that but uh i live in the central valley
of chile which is really far away from
everything
so if i don't pick something that i
already have locally in my cache it just
ends up taking a long time
all right we press enter on that it ssh
is out
pulls down the k3s binary sets it up
sets up all your systemd stuff and in
less than a minute
we will have a onenote k3s cluster oh
wow
really
huh i've been having internet problems
today youtube is broken
okay what the heck just happened there
let's try that again
huh now we enter into the
troubleshooting phase of the class
that's
billy bizarre hold on a second here
raw github com just like a dns problem
succeeded okay
hopefully this works
okay hey there we go thank you internet
all right so assuming that the internet
is working
in under a minute you'll have a one node
k3s cluster now a single node cluster
isn't really a cluster
but it's important for so there's two
types of nodes
in in kubernetes there's a control plane
nodes also called the masters and then
there's or the servers
i guess because we're all using new
terms now and then there's workers or
agents or minions or whatever
things that aren't servers or masters
you can separate these into control
plane
and worker basically now within control
plane in a standard kubernetes cluster
there's actually control plane and data
plane so control plane is all of the
kubernetes components that are the brain
and the data plane usually is an etcd
data store but with k3s it can also be
an external data store like postgres or
mysql
xcd or an internal data store using
sqlite
that makes it really really small and
you end up with a single node cluster
it brings down a kube config file which
it printed out to the screen there
but then it also saves it locally and if
we simply
set our kubeconfig environment variable
to point to that file
then we can run kubectl get nodes
and we have a cluster there we go
let's talk about how we use it
these are the things that make up 99
of the stuff that you'll be doing in
kubernetes i don't know 99
i made that up these are the things that
you need to know if you know just these
things
you'll be fine and then you'll be free
to learn
the things that you need to know when
you need to know them
obviously there's more here there's more
in kubernetes than just what's here
but for today don't worry about those
things pods
replica sets deployments config maps
services and ingresses are the things
i'm going to teach you today and at the
end of this
you'll be all set pods are the smallest
thing that you can deploy in kubernetes
they're a logical representation of
one or more containers that are always
scheduled together meaning they always
go on the same host
together they share the same network
space the same process space and the
same
storage so if you've ever had containers
where you tried to talk to another
container like
apache and a fast cgi php server or
something and they want to you know the
docs i'll say talk on localhost
and if you've got separate containers
that that's a struggle
pods solve that problem by grouping them
together
and the pod has a unique ip and then
containers inside can talk to each other
on localhost
here's an example of a pod with two
containers you've got
a file polar that brings down content
from some cms system
that was redundant brings down content
from some cms
saves it to a disk and then a web server
that responds to requests
from consumers and serves that traffic
app
this is a good demonstration of how each
of these independent things when
combined
provide a function it's important when
you think about how
to build your pods that you
make sure that the things inside are
closely related you don't want for
example to have a pod that has a web
server and a database server because
when your application needs more power
you're
going to scale up the number of pods to
handle the requests coming
in when you need more web servers you
don't
linearly need more database servers and
that's a really bad example because
obviously those database
containers wouldn't be able to talk to
each other and it just it would be
horrible
so don't do that
much of the time you will have one
container
per pod and that's fine
everything in kubernetes is built well
okay there's lots of ways to talk about
the things that are in kubernetes you
might hear me talk about workloads
you might hear me talk about resources
and there's also lots of ways to
do things in kubernetes and throughout
the class today i'm going to show you
lots of different ways
not to confuse you but so that you
understand
so that you understand what's available
and you can make the decision
that is best for you so we've got a
couple questions in the chat
uh peter asks is an internal database
advised for production
for a production environment it depends
on where you're doing production stuff
if you're doing kubernetes in a data
center and you want
high availability and you do then
you can run k3s using an external data
store and the high availability
feature comes from the aha datastore so
if you have a
an h a mysql database great if you've
got a
an ha cd data store then great but if
you've got
just a single node database or scd then
no
the internal sqlite data store is not ha
and there are places where you'll just
you don't have much horsepower you don't
have much
infrastructure so you know you've got a
raspberry pi or some small
single board computer and you don't have
the ability to build a cluster
so in that case it's still production
but you don't have the ability to do ha
the sqlite data store that's inside is
great
and you just need to architect your
solution such that if that box failed
you can recover to the exact same state
very quickly
and we'll talk about how to do that in a
little bit
uh michael asks where and how to install
ketchup google
it's your friend you find it faster than
i can
so back to this everything is written in
yaml now resources are
resources so every single thing an
object inside of a kubernetes cluster
technically is considered a resource
workloads are the things that you run
that actually do work
it's all it's all configured by yaml
nobody wakes up in the morning and says
i can think of nothing better to do with
my day than write a bunch of yaml
that's not true the people who work for
google i think actually do get up in the
morning and they have like yaml for
breakfast
so when we're going through the yaml
don't freak out you're not going to have
to remember all of this or recite it all
from scratch i'm going to show you how
you generate this and over time
you'll end up just copying and pasting
stuff and using packages and stuff but
it's important
to understand what it is from the
beginning so you've got
four top level keys api version kind
metadata and spec
api version tells kubernetes where in
its api
it can find information about how to
create the thing you're asking it to
create
in this case that's a pod metadata we
talk about in a little bit
spec is the definition of that thing for
the pod spec
there's a key called containers
underneath which is a list of containers
there are lots of other things in here
but for a bare minimum
pod declaration all you need is api
version
kind metadata with name spec
with containers and one container in
there that at least has
name and image and that's all the rest
of it will be picked up by defaults or
just doesn't matter for today
we are also overriding the command so
that it says hello kubernetes
and then sleeps for a second and then
exits we're going to go and run this now
and i want you to think what's going to
happen
to that pod when it exits
you apply manifests to the cluster using
a command called kubctl
that's what we set the coup config
environment variable above for
qctl apply dash f and then
where the actual file is if i cat that
you'll see it looks exactly like what i
just had up on the screen
this applies it to the cluster
and then we can say coup ctl get pods
and it tells us it's being created
that's exciting
and we can actually watch that happen
okay completed running completed
we have a new state crash luke bacca
when you tell kubernetes to do something
unless you specifically tell it
that the thing it's launching is going
to run and then exit
it will try to restart it and then it
exit and then it restarted it
and then it exited and then it restarted
it then it exited and kubernetes was
like okay
hang on clearly you've got a problem i
don't know what your problem is
but i'm going to give you a couple
seconds to think about and it waits
and then it starts it again and it exits
and it's like okay clearly you need more
time
and it waits longer and every time it
exits
instantly kubernetes
increases that back off timer it'll
increase it all the way up to 10 minutes
you can't even see my hands anymore
all the way up to 10 minutes between
restarts
so that something that's going crazy
doesn't consume resources on your
cluster when obviously it's broken
maybe it's waiting for a database that's
not up yet maybe it's waiting for a
cache maybe the internet's broken maybe
something who knows
kubernetes doesn't care it's just gonna
protect the cluster
eventually if it doesn't get fixed it
hopes that a human being will come along
and be like
okay we gotta fix that and then it can
go back to being happy
let's delete that
ctl delete the pod called my app dash
pod
and
done that will return in a second i'm
actually going to ssh into that node
and change some piece of its config as
soon as this comes back
i uncovered a container debug over the
weekend
and
don't worry about this this is not part
of the class
container t inserts a default registry
mirror for docker.io to pull from the
internet
i have a local cache that runs inside my
house and so
they are ignoring the star and i have to
actually override docker.io
as well
so we'll just bounce k3s real quick and
now it will
pull from the cache and when we get to
the part where we're actually installing
containers that have some size
this will be much faster okay back on
track
what we just did not the changing the
registries thing but the the application
of the pod
going to do that and you're learning
you're going to be applying a lot of
manifests but in reality
that's not what you want to do you want
to make sure that everything
you do on a kubernetes cluster is
repeatable
and declared this is these are
properties principles from
infrastructure
as customers cover as covers covers
cover as cover as code like that you're
familiar with this
it's config management stuff the idea is
that if i make a change to the cluster
i close my laptop like i'm out i'm on
vacation then i go on
a sailboat in the middle of the ocean
and i'm scuba diving and the cluster
crashes
nobody who works with me has any idea
what was done unless i like wrote some
documentation and stuff and i'm not
going to do that
so they don't know how to fix the
problem instead
we want something that allows us to
template our configuration
and put it in a source code repository
and then
the cluster is built from the repo the
repo is then the source of truth
and if the cluster melts down spin up a
new cluster
apply all the manifests and pow you're
back in business
who asked was peter who asked about an
internal db being advisable for
production so in a resource-constrained
environment where you only have an sbc
and and that's it you would use this
type of declarative model so if that
thing melts down
you just ship another sbc out there and
bob the janitor goes and plugs it in
and you just whoop you blow the life
into it from the repository
there was no really good way to do this
with kubernetes until somebody created a
tool called
customize customize was so awesome that
back in version 1.14 they baked it into
coop ctl
so you can get access to it via
kubectl-k or you can just use the
customize command itself
it allows you to template your manifests
and then do patching and overriding and
there's a whole bunch of shortcuts
and it it makes it great for keeping
them inside of source control
you can do stuff like now the separation
of concerns where developers can write
this part
but operators can write that part since
apparently
we all care about different things i
don't know
if you want to know more about customize
there's a link to it and
i'm going to start including customize
in what you're learning how to do today
and by the end of the class you'll
understand why you don't have to use it
but like when i go and i buy a book on
how to do something with technology
you get these books right they're like
this thick some of them are good and
some of them are bad
i don't know how you can write a book
that's this thick and have it be bad but
somehow people are able to do it
so i take the book i flip it open i look
through the table of contents
now i know the subject matter and i flip
to the index if the index is
seven pages long and it's in font that's
this big then i know that the quality of
the book is
bad if the index is 46 pages long
and the font is and the subject is like
they're indexing every use of the word
the
but the subjects in the index are
actually you know diverse
then i know that the quality of the book
is good what i'm teaching you today
follows the same model you're going to
know lots of different ways to do things
which allows you to make a decision
you're never going to make a pod that's
it class is up
you're you're never going to directly
make pods because by themselves
pods like there's there's no real way to
interface with them and make them
useful the thing that manages
pods is called a replica set and there
used to be there still is a thing called
a replication controller and we would
actually make replica sets manually but
we don't do that anymore either instead
we make deployments which is what you're
going to learn about next the deployment
creates a replica set a replica set
creates a bunch of pods
and then the replica set manages the
pods and
controls how many of them there are are
they running or not
this is where we learn about state
management
i need like buttons i can press that
have like you know applause or like the
crazy fill noises this is different from
stateful and stateless we're going to
talk about that as well
then you'll be super confused state
management
inside of the kubernetes cluster
consists of two things
the actual state and the desired state
here we have three hosts 12 replicas
replicas just means copies so 12
replicas of a pot
kubernetes has spread them across the
three hosts
the actual state is 12 replicas the
desired state
presumably is 12 replicas but when one
of those nodes dies
well now there's a difference the actual
state is eight the desired state is 12.
kubernetes sole purpose in life is to
reconcile
the desired state and the actual state
and it will do
whatever it has to do to make that
happen
in this case it's pretty easy it just
spun up four more replicas
on the remaining two hosts if those
hosts didn't have enough resources for
it to do that
then it would just continue to try and
it would alarm and it would be like i
can't do what i'm supposed to do help
and then you would spit up another host
or you could have kubernetes spin up
another host for you
to reconcile those states
where you're going to spend a lot of
time
not just today but as you're learning
about kubernetes is with
deployments deployments create replica
sets replica sets create pods
deployments give you a really nice
interface for managing
the version the container image and the
scale and a bunch of other stuff
we spend a lot of time here today
because if you understand this
then you'll understand a lot about
kubernetes
deployments are handled by a thing
called a deployment controller
everything in kubernetes
is pretty much handled by some type of a
controller
it's an ingress controller there's a
replication control they control things
deployments handle stateless
applications
a stateless application is something
like http
you have two web servers the web server
doesn't know who you are the web server
doesn't care who you are it doesn't know
that just a moment ago you requested a
different page
it doesn't get jealous if on your next
request you talk to the next web server
that's over there
it just doesn't matter the only thing
they can focus on is what they're doing
right now and then
it's gone never existed that's a
stateless application
there are some things where it does
matter take a database for example
you've got a master and two replicas
well it matters who the master is it
matters what its ip is it matters what
its storage is it matters what its name
is
it matters that it comes up first so the
replicas can find it
if you have an application where things
matter
you have a stateful application that's
handled
by a staple set inside of kubernetes
there are also demon sets where you get
one copy
of a pod on every node so if you have
three nodes
you get three points if you add a fourth
node
it automatically gets a fourth pod there
are also
cron jobs and jobs a job is kind of like
what we launched at the beginning where
it just does one thing and then it exits
and kubernetes doesn't try to restart it
and there's a whole
set of logic around there about retrying
failed jobs and things like that
and then there are cron jobs which allow
you to launch
jobs on a schedule
today we're only going to talk about
deployments
the best use case for a deployment is
when you have a version of an
application running
and you want to upgrade it so here let's
just say we have version one of our
application
and now version 1.1 is available so we
tell kubernetes hey
deploy version 1.1 and it begins doing
what's called a rolling update
so it first will launch in this picture
it launched two new ones you can control
it you can have it launch one two five a
thousand whatever
it launched two new ones and then it
killed off two of the old ones
and then it launched two new ones and
killed off two of the old ones and then
we have now
reconciled the desired state and the
actual state
if for some reason this didn't work you
can roll it back
because it understands where it came
from you can even roll back
like to versions way way way way a long
time ago
somebody asked in an earlier class what
if you upgrade a database or you upgrade
an application and it does a database
migration and then you go to roll it
back your database migration is
screwed like it doesn't undo that that's
not kubernetes magic
that's your application magic and
there's never a time where you can
upgrade an
app do a database migration downgrade
the app and have it undo the database
migration
your recovery path in that situation is
always
make a backup makeup you should make a
backup before you upgrade
anything where data is going to change
because if something goes south
you recover by restoring the back anyway
let's go look at deployments
all right this is another way to create
something inside of kubernetes coupe ctl
create
deploy we're going to call it nginx and
all we need to pass it is
the image and it will
go and create it and we can now say cube
ctl get deploy
and it will show us the deployment and
we can say a coup ctl get
replica set everything in kubernetes has
abbreviations and in fact you probably
are noticing that sometimes i type like
kgno and it gets automatically replaced
you're going to get so sick of typing
kubectl get
pods that you're going to create an
abbreviation for it
and i have those so i type kgpo or kgno
but for you sitting in this class it's
confusing when i type kgpo and you type
kgpo and nothing happens
so i literally have another tool that
extracts the shortcut and turns it back
into the full command
just for this class
to see everything and we're both happy
notice the name of the replica set is
the deployment dash
some eight character identifier
and if we were to look at the pods now
you would see that that carries through
so we have one pod running you can
quickly see what deployment and replica
set
are responsible for it now
let's look at a different way to do this
we'll just delete that
and instead
what if we didn't want just the default
yaml what if we wanted to
modify it somehow well you can
provide
dash o yaml and dash dash dry run equals
client
the equals client part is actually only
in coop ctl 1.18
and higher so if you don't use that it
complains but if you
do use it and it says it doesn't
understand upgrade your coupe ctl
if i run this it will take the manifest
that it would have applied to the
cluster and it will instead print it out
to the screen
and i could save that to a file and then
i can edit it and then i can apply it to
the cluster
so this is a way that you can get
default yaml
prepared and then modify it and put it
in a source code repository before
applying it to
the cluster use qctl create whatever the
thing is
dry run n-o-n if you don't want to use
yaml
if you're a sucker for punishment you
just do dash oh
json
all right
let's actually i need to update i'm
looking at my
my instructions here and i don't want to
do what it says there because it's a
little bit confusing and i end up
deleting some stuff
um so let's just create this again and
then we'll go
and look at it so we've got
and our pod is running cool so you see
i'm using coop ctl get
pods and it's telling me that there's a
pod
but i could pass it it it it it
oops that's not what i meant to do i
could say koop ctl get pods and i can
pass
it the name of the pod
and say dash o yaml and then i'm just
going to pipe that to less
and coop ctl reaches out to the cluster
gets the manifest for the thing that i
asked it to get and brings it back and
shows it to me
so if there's anything running in the
cluster you can just look at it and look
at
how are you created you could save this
to a file and you get
all of the additional defaults you could
start looking at this and say well
what does termination grace period
seconds do
and then you can go and look it up in
the documentation and now you're
increasing your knowledge
without being held back by things that
you didn't know you needed to know
that's the definition of the object
itself
so that's like you look at a car and
and the car has an engine and seats and
a door
and steering wheel hopefully more parts
than that tires i mean unless you live
in the south and it might not have tires
then it would have bricks blocks um
that's the definition of a car but what
if you wanted to know
how the neighbor saw the car or how the
car interfaced with the
environment when you need to know how
kubernetes
sees a resource instead of coupe ctl get
use cube ctl describe
the coup ctl describe the pod nginx you
see sometimes i put a slash sometimes i
don't
it doesn't matter now what we get
is kubernetes understanding of the
object
from the outside and you get a bunch of
other information about it like
who controls it information about its
internals
uh is it initialized is it ready and so
on and so forth but down here you get
this events section
this is everything that happened to this
resource since it was born
and we can see that it was created it
was
the image was already present um sorry
it was assigned it was the image was
present it was created and then it was
started easy enough
when you do troubleshooting however this
is where you're going to go and look
to find problems
sorry that's where you're going to go
and look to find why the problems exist
because when you're doing
troubleshooting you already have
problems you don't
need to go find more but qctl describe
will tell you
more information so for example there's
qctl logs
which will show you the output from the
container but if the container never
started
the pod never started you don't have
logs which means that there's a problem
with kubernetes to use qctl describe
so what can we do we can update this
thing so we do cube ctl
scale and let's just take it from one
replica to three replicas
we have three replicas now let's update
it
so we can update it to nginx 1.17 alpine
so we're running 1.16 now
and then you can watch the rollout
happen
with coup ctl rollout status and then
the deployment that you care about
this will show you when it creates new
replicas terminates old ones
and so on
the idea behind watching this is that at
some point you'll be like
it seems like it's taking a long time
i wonder why it's taking a long time
shouldn't take that long
let's go see what happened so you type
coop ctl get pods
and you see there's a problem
oh my gosh but notice that while there's
a problem
the original three replicas are still
running the site's up
customers are using it they're buying
stuff boss isn't mad
board of directors isn't pissed i'm not
going to get fired
so i can take the time to troubleshoot
this
and in reality you want to test all of
this stuff before you go rolling it out
on your production clusters but come on
pretend with me all right so what do we
do
well we have a problem with a pod
so we're gonna go look at it
and we're going to jump down to the
event section and we see
okay so it was assigned it's got an
error and
there's an error message and the error
message says
failed to resolve reference ah
i misspelled alpine
i do this every week you'd think that
after
weeks and weeks and weeks of this i'd
remember how to solve
output all right so how do we fix it
we do coup ctl roll out undo
now if if it had completed its rollout a
rollout undo would just undo the whole
thing
but because it never completed it all it
does is
just kill off that thing that was trying
to start and we're back in the state
that we were in before
what's another way that we can do this
we can use coop ctl edit
this much like coupe ctl get reaches out
to the cluster
brings back the manifest and loads it
into
my case vi in your case it might be nano
or vim or god forbid i hope not emacs
just kidding anybody who uses emacs got
that joke
i use vi uh so we can jump down to the
image section here where's that there it
is
and we can just change from 116 to 117
and we can save that
and now we can watch our rollout happen
and we'll see one out of three replicas
have been updated and this will continue
to update the replicas and then
terminate
the other ones oh deployment engine x
successfully rolled out
look at that
so what else can we do
let's nuke that and
let's talk about customize
so we're going to delete that all that
work just to delete it
terrible
all right if you have the repo checked
out if you don't
i'll start scrolling that again so that
you can go and check it out
in there there is a directory called
deployment and then a directory called
base
that is the base go figure
in there is a manifest for
our deployment and it's it's got a
couple extra things in there that aren't
in the
default one but they're not important
the resources is one section and volumes
we'll actually talk about here when i
get to the config map
but basically it's the same it's going
to be nginx 1.16 output
now there's a file in here called
customization.yaml
custom customization can be complex but
when you're starting out it doesn't have
to be
you can look at this file and understand
what it says
it says okay resources well here's two
files deployment.yaml and service.yaml
i want you to go and just deploy those
and then i want you to make a config map
you don't know what a config map is yet
but that's okay we're telling it to go
make one
we want it to be called index and we
want it to use
the value of that
file configs index.html which is just an
html file that says hello from nowhere
this is the default environment
you use qctl apply-k and you point it at
a directory that has a
customization.yaml file in there
and it says okay and it created
three things for us a deployment service
and a config map
you don't know what a service is yet
either but that's also fun
okay it's like so what
like okay so it made a thing great but
where this becomes
valuable and basically all we've done is
we've just we've done the thing that we
were already doing but it seems like we
did it with more steps because there's
more files involved
i'm actually going to just delete this
again
with qctl delete dash k and i'm going to
point it at the same directory
and let's jump up and look at this
overlay directory
in here we have two directories that i
want to talk about now
staging and production
inside of staging we have
customization.yaml
if we look at that well
now we get some interesting stuff so you
see name prefix
everything will be prefixed with the
name staging dash every name will be
prefixed with the text
staging dash everything will get a label
of environment is staging
you don't know what labels are either
it's cool hang out we're gonna get there
i like talking about things and then
showing you them because your brain
makes an association
and it's through associations of data
that we retain knowledge
it's going to start with the contents of
that base directory that we were just
in and then it's going to patch those
files
with these two files here then it's
going to make
another config map or it's going to
replace the index config map with the
file that's in this directory
that file says hello from staging
this is the staging environment if we
look at
image.yaml you can see that it's going
to
modify the deployment to run 1.17 alpine
and if we look at replica count you'll
see that it's just going to set one
replica which the
other deployment had one replica anyway
so that's an item potent change
we'll apply that and now
you see that we have a staging nginx
and we have a staging engine x
and we have
you guessed it staging configmap let's
go look at the production environment
customization.yaml it's set up for
production you get prod dash
labels of environment as production same
base directory
different patches different config map
generated
from a file that says hello from
production
if we look at replica count you'll see
that it gets three replicas
and if you look at image you see that
it's it's conservative it stays on 1.16
alpine
but the base image i mean that could be
1.64 alpine we don't know
but we do know that our production
environment is going to get 1.16 alpine
because that's what we want
this is a declarative configuration
and when we apply that
we get a production environment
with three pods running 1.16 alpine
service config map all of that
what we've now done is we've created a
staging environment and a production
environment
from the same core definition and then
we've just made the modifications that
are necessary
for the two environments that's
templating that's reuse
that's declarative and if you pretend
that this was in a git repo
that actually was responsible for the
deployment then it's repeatable
as well that's what i want to show you
about what customize can do
and now you can just make changes and
apply those changes and it picks up
which of the resources changed and needs
to be modified
let's talk about configmaps
let's say you deploy nginx nginx it's a
web server
so it comes with a configuration file it
comes with a default configuration file
i
100 guarantee you that their default
configuration file is of next to no use
to you because you're deploying your own
application you want your own config
file so how do you fix that
do you make your own container from the
nginx container and put your own config
file in there
okay sure you could but now you have to
track changes in upstream rebuild your
containers
what if there's an incompatibility
between a later version of nginx and a
config that you're using it just sucks
so you could deploy all of the
containers the pods and attach a volume
that has the config file and then you
can just change that
and reload and yeah maybe you could do
that with like nfs
but then you introduce another variable
something else that can break
so it's okay kubernetes solves this with
config maps
config maps let you override
configuration data inside of a container
with
stuff stuff is simply key value pairs
it results in either environment
variables where the key is the name of
the variable and the value is the value
of the variable
or you can override a file where the key
becomes the file name
and the contents of the file are the
value of
are the value that's what we just did
here where we have the
index.html that has some html in it or
you can override entire directories
where if you have a config map with
multiple keys
then each of those keys becomes a file
in the directory and the contents of the
file are the value for each of the keys
what's super amazing about config maps
is that they're managed independent of
the
the workload itself so when you change
the config map it's updated
in place inside of the container without
it having to be restarted
it's like magic your application is
responsible for picking up on those
changes
and here we get into a bit of a debate
there are two schools of thought here
one is
that's amazing and i totally want that
the other is that's not amazing because
it
opens up the possibility that what's
running
inside of the pod in the config map is
not
directly connected to how the workload
was launched which means it's not
repeatable
so the get ops customized cam
would much rather that changes to the
config map
results in a new config map which
updates the deployment which causes the
deployment to re to be
recreated it basically triggers a
rolling update
then you know exactly what's in that
resource
and you know how to repeat it
that's yes the other is also fine
whichever one you want to believe in
is totally fine it's whatever works for
you if you want to use customize
but you still want to have those
config maps updated in place you can
tell customize hey don't make new config
maps and it's going to be like
okay and it'll just update them in place
let's talk about services let's check
chat see if there's any no questions all
right you guys are like glued to the
screen i love it
services you've got a pod or a bunch of
pots and now you need
a way to talk to them services are
essentially layer for load balancers
pods have ips but you don't know that
that ip is going to stay there that that
pod isn't going to get rescheduled or
relaunched or upgraded
at which point it's going to get a new
address so you just you don't you don't
you don't worry about pods you let other
things worry about pods
services give you a stable dns name and
a stable ip address
that is then routed to a group of pods
and they're not a real thing they're a
logical thing that happens inside of ip
tables
you have three types of services
each one contains the types that came
before it you have a cluster ip service
which creates
uh all of those things that i just
described and it creates them
inside of the cluster so it's only
accessible from in the cluster imagine
you've got
web servers and you've got a memcache
cluster well you don't need to talk to
memcache from
outside the cluster so you just slap a
cluster ip service in front of it and
call it a day
then there's a node port service which
creates a cluster ip service
then it opens a port on all of the nodes
in the cluster that port
sits between thirty thousand and three
two seven six seven
randomly assigned but you can tell it
which one to use if you want
and traffic that lands on that port is
then routed to the cluster ip service
and then routed to the pods
you'll use node port services with
external
load balancers so if you have an f5 or a
netscaler or an h.a proxy or whatever
you would terminate your traffic on that
possibly even doing your ssl termination
and then
it would route to all of the nodes in
the cluster on that
node port that was assigned and then it
does the health checking so if you take
a node down the load balancer is like oh
that node's gone and it just sends the
traffic somewhere else
if your cluster is in a cloud provider
and it knows it's in a cloud provider
and you've done the magical song and
dance that cloud providers require so
that your cluster can talk to them
then you can create a load balancer
service
this first creates a cluster ip service
then it opens up the ports
then it reaches out to the cloud
provider over their api
and it configures a cloud load balancer
it programs the load balancer with all
of the nodes and the ports and all of
that stuff
and then it maintains that configuration
for the life
of the service as you add and remove
nodes those get added and removed to and
from the node pool
and everything's great in amazon for
example you will get an elb
or an nlb these are still layer
four load balancers actually that's not
true you get an
elb or an nlb um
yeah and they're layer four so they they
still get passed back through to the
service they don't do intelligent stuff
um by default
specialized got confused there cause we
talked about ingresses in a second and
so whatever
um if you're in a bare metal environment
and you want load balancer services
you can use one of three different
things there's a tool called metal lb
that does layer two arping and we'll
create load balancer services
and assign them an ip and then start
arping for them it will also
inject routes into a bgp fabric there's
another one called
porter that does just bgp i haven't
looked at that one and there's a new one
that i found a couple of days ago called
kubevip
that just does the layer 2 arp version
you can't use these inside of cloud
providers because
either they don't allow you know arping
or they don't let you schedule multiple
ips and move them around
but if you're in bare metal you're good
to go and what happens is take metal lb
for example it you give it a
pool of addresses like a dhcp server
when you create a load balancer service
it snatches one of those
puts it out there and starts arping if
that node goes down
the metal lb configuration in the
cluster realizes that the node went down
and it starts announcing that ip
out of a different node so then you just
point your stuff at that ip
and good to go
they look like this they're layer four
load balancers they don't make decisions
they just bring traffic in and send it
to where it's supposed to go
expecting that the thing on the other
side will understand it
we have some services that we created
when we did the customized thing a
second ago see i snuck those in and you
didn't even know
let's go look at the
service definition from the base
so we can understand a couple of really
important things
api version kind metadata and spec look
at that there you go
api version v1 kind service spec
metadata in a second spec ports it's
going to listen on port 80.
it's going to send to the destination on
port 80
and oh there's a selector thing there
and type this node port
selector app is nginx if you look up at
the metadata section
you'll see that metadata there's labels
and one of the labels is
app is nginx metadata is just metadata
it doesn't mean anything but you can use
it to define
unique characteristics of the resource
everything needs to have a name
at a bare minimum but beyond that it can
have an infinite number of labels
arbitrary key value pairs that you
assign so that you
can identify your application but that
you also use for kubernetes to identify
the application if we were to look at
uh
staging nginx if we looked at our
staging service you would see that it's
selector
its selector is actually app is engine x
and environment is staging remember from
customization.yaml that everything got
that additional label
if we were to look at our deployment
staging engine x you'll start to see a
pattern
notice first of all the deployment has
environment
staging but then as we scroll down here
you'll see that
under the spec
sorry under the template for the things
that it's going to create you'll see
that
it also has a label of app ascension x
and environment is
staging and then up here you have a
selector
that says match anything with the label
of appdis engine x and environment is
staging
so you've got a deployment that creates
a replica set that creates a bunch of
pods it labels all of those pods with
environment staging and app is nginx and
then it says i'm going to watch
everything that has those two labels
and there they are and it watches them
you could theoretically create a fifth
pod or something that has those two
labels and the replica set will be like
oh come here baby you are mine
but you just don't do that ordinarily
unless you want to create trouble for
yourself but
it the the replica set doesn't know it
just looks at whatever has the label
and it's the same with the service the
service will route traffic
to any pod that has those two labels
easy peasy that's how
many many things in kubernetes find the
things that they're supposed to care
about
so if we look at our services again you
will see
that they are node port services as
recognizable by the fact that they have
these high ports
and if i were to just fire off a curl
command
at one of those you see hello from
staging that's our config map that
overrode the index.html file
inside of the nginx container if you
look at the other one
well hello from production
it's not so hard right like we're
starting to get the hang of this
the thing is you're not going to create
one-to-one
do you love it i teach you things and
then i'm like you're never gonna do that
this is like this is the crash course in
kubernetes
you're not going to create one-to-one
load balancer services for all of your
services
because if you have a cluster that has a
thousand websites on it
you don't need a thousand load balancers
each of which costs twenty dollars a
month
like we already figured out how to do
this back in the 90s with name-based
virtual hosting in apache before nginx
was even around
you can do the same thing in kubernetes
with a thing called an
ingress an ingress is a definition
that does layer 7 load balancing
configuration for http
so that means it'll do routing based on
host header
path primarily there are extensions to
ingress in certain ingress controllers
that can do routing based on all sorts
of other stuff but by default those are
the things that people use so traffic
comes in for this host for this path
send it to that service
and then it goes to those pods now you
can start to break things up
into microservices you've got these pods
that handle
products and these pods that handle
store or whatever slash profile
and you can start to do routing around
them
the normal way to set up http in a
kubernetes cluster is
you set up all your services you set up
an ingress
controller so the ingress controller is
a software load balancer
that handles it here's the ingress
request that you made to the api
and it configures itself to serve that
request
ingress controllers are nginx a proxy
uh i found one this morning called
skipper
there's lots of them you can use api
gateways you can use
service mesh there's lots of things that
provide ingress controller functionality
k3s ships with traffic by default it's
another one
um a lot of kubernetes clusters use the
nginx ingress controller but whatever
there's lots of them pick the one you
like
throw it away find another one use
different ones if you want you can run
multiple ingress controllers on the same
cluster
so the normal way is you have your
workloads cluster ip service
ingress controller operating at layer 7
your cluster ip services are at layer 4
and then outside of your cluster you
would put a layer 4
load balancer or you would use something
like metal lb
um to have that roving ip
so traffic lands on that address gets
routed to the ingress
controller gets routed to the service
gets routed to the pod
and it you know partridge in a pear tree
and all that stuff it looks like this
layer 7 load balancer layer 4 load
balancer
let's go set one up
in the directory above so let's see if
we look in that overlay directory
there's also
an ingress directory and in there if we
go look at single
because we're running out of time
there's
a customization.yaml file
name prefix dev common labels dev
load the ingress.yaml use the same base
directory
but patch the service we're going to
patch the service to make it a type
cluster ip different from node port
we'll apply this
and now if we look at our deployments
you will see that we have
dev staging and prod
we look at our services you will see
that we have our two node port services
but we also have this cluster ip service
for dev
notice that it's only listening inside
of the cluster there's no
node port there
and if we look at our ingress
i was ugly let me just show you the the
ingress here um this is the definition
so it's name is demo ingress it's
listening uh for requests to training
dash a dot cl dot nucleus that's my
internal domain here in the house
anything from slash is going to get
routed to nginx
on port 80. now customize is smart
enough to figure out that
it's the service name is actually dev
engine x and it modified it's called
mutating
it mutated the config before it applied
it so if we were to go and say
coupe ctl get ingress you would see
oh there we have an ingress and now if
we were to curl
this we get
the default configma
that's kubernetes that's it let's jump
back to that first slide
and do a quick recap and then we're
going to dive into some questions and
then we're going to dive into some
rancher
the rancher portion of the class is
actually really small because
this is the meat like i would really
rather just teach intro to kubernetes
but i want to show you like what you can
do with rancher to accelerate
your your productivity with kubernetes
so let's go here remember pods smallest
unit of anything you can deploy in a
kubernetes cluster they're your actual
workloads that do things replica sets
manage pods
you don't really care deployments manage
replica sets
you kind of care configmaps allow you to
override configuration information
inside of a container to customize it
without modifying the original base
image
services are layer for load balancers
that sit in front of
workloads stable dns name stable ip
address
they're not going to go anywhere they're
very faithful and ingresses
layer 7 load balancers that allow you to
save
money you can do
with most ingress controllers you can
also punch through
tcp ports it's technically not an
ingress
but you can make them act at layer four
so so
so so so but what if you have something
that's got its own tls certificate or
what if it's mqtt
or mysql or something like that
most of them allow you to configure a
tcp port and say hey don't look at this
just when traffic comes in
send it to that service and it's happy
to oblige so they work for layer seven
and layer four
just technically i got into a big debate
with somebody at rancher once about how
technically it's not an
ingress and i was like but please apples
oranges potatoes
it gets you traffic where it wants to go
uh peter asks if rte by default has
nginx ingress that is
correct um so it has the nginx ingress
controller
k3s has traffic uh just because traffic
1.7 is really small
rke ships with nginx by default and
you can just stand up an rke cluster or
a k3s cluster and then start
deploying ingresses and they'll just
start working automatically
no extra configuration is needed
if you wanted to do anything like
put metal lb in for load balancer
services
uh then you'll need to uninstall the
ingress
controller or deploy without it put
metal lb
in and then redeploy the ingress
controller so that it's
behind metal lb
i have videos on how to do that on my
youtube channel um and i'll show you
where my youtube channel is near the end
of the video so you can actually go and
follow along with those
by the end of this class i never have a
voice
all right moving on to the rancher part
this is good this is good we might we're
totally not going to end on time we
might end on time
uh okay here's my slide for rancher
let's just get busy first let's look at
the docs
in the rancher documentation don't don't
play around with this rancher 1.6 thing
this is our old version of the product
and brancher 2 is all kubernetes we
still keep this up here because there
are still some
legacy installations don't just ignore
that
come over here to the rancher 2 side and
and inside of here you will find
information on how to
install rancher there are two ways that
you can install ranch
one is h a and one is not h
if you want h a rancher then what you do
is you build an h a kubernetes cluster
and you install rancher into it using
a tool called helm which is the package
manager for kubernetes
we talk about how you can do that you
can
do it technically you can install
rancher into any kubernetes cluster but
we know and support our kubernetes
distributions we know it will work there
you can put it in aks and maybe
microsoft changes something and it
breaks and we have no control over that
so when we say that you can only install
it into rke or k3s
what i mean by that is that's the
supported configuration if you do it any
other way and you come asking for help
you're not gonna get help because you
put it somewhere where you're not
supposed to put it
so if you have an h a rke cluster or an
h a k 3s cluster
you install rancher into it rancher uses
the h a functionality of kubernetes to
itself bha
the other way that you can do it which i
do not recommend but which is what we're
going to do today is you can install it
on a single node using just docker
the reason we do that in this class is
it's fine for like demos
and quick tutorials and stuff because it
comes up really quickly the other
version takes about 10 minutes and
that's 10 minutes that i don't have
the problem with doing it this way is
that you can never go
from this to the other they're two
completely different
architectures so if you think that you
might ever put production workloads into
your rancher environment
but you don't want to commit multiple
nodes for ha right now then just stand
up a one node rke cluster
rke is amazing for many reasons but one
of them
is because you can build a single node
cluster right now
and then you can later add two more
nodes to it and rerun the command rke
up and it will convert itself from a
single node cluster to a fully ha
cluster
and all your rancher stuff just becomes
ha so that's the way to do it
if you think you might do production
stuff for today
we're not going to do that let's jump
into my
training server node and
let's get
docker run d for detach restart is
unless stopped
if you do restart always our
workflow for backups and upgrades has
you stop the container and then do the
work and then start the container again
uh if you do restart always when you
stop it doctor restarts it and you guys
will go to war until the only thing you
can do is delete the container and then
you have nothing to start again if
something goes wrong
so restart unless stopped save your life
punch through port 80 and 443
and then i like to bind them out to
directory from the host in this case opt
rancher one i always use to the
persistent location in the container
which is var lip rancher
if you don't do this you still get a
docker volume it's still persistent
but docker volumes are a little harder
to get to to make backups and i'm
lazy so i like just stop the container
tar off opt rancher or make a copy of it
into option.back
and then start the container again and
it's just so much easier easier easier
easier easier easier easier
2.4.5
that's probably up if not it will be
shortly so in a browser
we can just go to training s
and by default it comes up with
self-signed certificates
uh you can use self-signed certs you can
bring your own certs from a real ca or
an internal ca
you can also tell it to generate
certificates on the fly
using let's encrypt set the admin
password
and then it asks you for the server url
this is important when you
manage a kubernetes cluster with rancher
it will
reach out to that cluster and we'll do
two things one it connects to that
clusters api
so the kubernetes api so that's an
outbound connection it also installs
agents
on the cluster itself that reach back
into rancher
and they reach back in on that address
so if you put an ip address there and
then your rancher server moves to a
different ip
all your downstream clusters don't know
who to talk to and it's really really
difficult to update that
in the cluster so it's far better to use
a dns name
and point that to an ip it's also
important that whatever you do put there
is accessible from outside so you can't
have this in like your basement and be
running clusters out on amazon
unless you've got like an amazon direct
connect into your basement in which case
i'm moving into your house
not really um
this is the default screen so here you
would see all of the clusters
that you're managing and you have no
clusters so we're going to say add
cluster
you can deploy a cluster using a hosted
provider in this case
by default we have these three enabled
eks aks
gk we have others available just the
drivers merge enabled by default
this will reach out you give it your
credentials it reaches out
builds the cluster installs the agents
wires it back to the rancher server
and you're good to go you can also use
infrastructure in which case it reaches
out
provisions infrastructure installs
docker onto it
installs rke wires that back into the
rancher server
and you're good to go if you have
a cluster running anywhere already out
there in the wild
you can just import it we're going to do
that for our k3s cluster in just a
second
you are given a coup ctl apply command
that you run against the cluster
and it installs the agents wires it back
into the rancher server and you're good
to go
and if you do your provisioning via
anything else ansible terraform puppet
chef cloud init shell scripts
manually whatever all you need is
to make sure that your provisioners
install a supported version of docker
and then if you use the custom install
method you'll be given a docker run
command
that you just put at the end of your
provisioner or you go run manually on a
host with docker
that will install rke and wire it back
to the reactor server and you'll be good
to go
so let's import our k3s cluster we'll
call it demo
we'll say create you're given a couple
of different commands here
if your rancher server uses real
certificates then you can use this
second one down here which is a cube ctl
apply
but ctl will not talk to an end point
that doesn't have a real certificate so
in our case because we're using
self-signed certs
i need to copy this second one
and then i will just jump back over to
my terminal here
and i will apply that since i reuse
these machines the first one always
fails
uh i will apply that to the cluster and
it will now go out
and proceed to install all of its stuff
while it's doing that let's talk about
the global level
stuff available in rancher
first of all under tools here you can go
to drivers and you see that you can
enable
or install additional cluster drivers or
node drivers these are just docker
machine drivers some of them are written
by members of the community
so that'll give you access to you know
if you deploy in someplace else
under security we have authentication
rancher plugs into
backend identity providers like all of
these ones that you see here
rancher is designed to be an
authentication proxy
so if you trust me if you
go anywhere that manages kubernetes for
multiple people they have clusters all
over the place
people have clusters under their desk
one group wants to use gke
one uses amazon one uses packet one uses
eks
and they're all really particular about
what they use
fun but now you're in the business of
when somebody joins the organization you
got to go to all these different places
and configure
access credentials and worse when
somebody leaves the organization you got
to figure out what did they have access
to
and there's always the shadow i.t
problem of people spinning up clusters
that you don't know about
and you know next thing you know you're
you're equifax
by plugging rancher into a back-end
provider everybody connects to their
clusters through rancher
they authenticate here rancher sets
impersonation headers and passes the
traffic through to the downstream
cluster where it does all the
authorization and everything else
if somebody joins the organization you
just put them in the right group they
get access to all of the clusters that
group has access to
and if somebody leaves the organization
you just disable their account
and they lose access to everything it
makes your job as an operator
for those of you who are operators
infinitely easier
if you don't have a back-end provider
you can get the same functionality with
users and groups directly inside
of rancher by now
well it's not up yet that's sad
still loading okay so apparently i don't
have those images in the cache so let's
continue to talk about global level
stuff
other things that we do at the global
level are pod security policies these
are configurations that determine what a
cluster
what how resources in the cluster have
to look so for example can pods
can containers run with privileged mode
or can they run
you know with root as the user and stuff
like that
we do these things at the global level
because that allows you to make changes
and apply them to
multiple clusters a single rancher
server installation can manage
thousands of kubernetes clusters so it's
important that you're not
going here and here and here and here
and here here and there and there and
there and doing on the same thing over
and over again
because a it just makes you you hate
yourself
and b any task that requires a human to
do it will eventually
fail we make mistakes it's called human
error i don't care how awesome you are
you're gonna screw it up and the cost
the consequences potentially could be
quite large so just
do it in one place have it reliably
duplicated everywhere and then go back
to playing quake
or whatever people play these days
animal crossing or whatever
our cluster is up you see that we have
two projects default and system
i don't talk about namespaces in this
class except for a little bit right here
a namespace is a logical grouping of
resources inside of a kubernetes cluster
it means that everything has to have a
unique name you can't have two
deployments called nginx because how
does it know which one
you're talking about but you could have
two namespaces one called production and
one called staging
and inside of each of them you could
have a deployment called nginx
because they're logically separated
namespaces are the boundary for
role-based access control in a
kubernetes cluster
that's just a fancy way of saying you
can figure who can do what at the
namespace level
imagine once again you've got lots of
clusters or you've got a cluster with
lots of namespaces
you've got to make a change on 35
namespaces that sucks
so rancher has this thing called a
project
which is a logical it's basically a
namespace of namespaces
it's used for grouping and for
role-based access control
you make a change to the project and it
propagates to all the namespaces
underneath it every kubernetes cluster
that you build has
some system namespaces and a default
namespace for user workloads but you can
create as many namespaces as you want
we give you two projects system which
contains
system level stuff that you probably
just should leave alone and
default which contains the default
namespace
but you can create other projects and
add namespaces to them and stuff like
that all day long
you see here the stuff that we created
and
okay that's cool so we've got workloads
we could come in we could edit them
but you know what let's just delete one
of them because i wanna i wanna
burn through this really quickly um
so let's delete one of them and recreate
it inside of brancher so you can see
just
how easy it is to do things from scratch
so we'll nuke our dev environment
poof it's gone ingress is gone service
is gone
and let's just recreate that now i could
first of all i'm still you know i'm
connected to rancher right now
but if i wanted to change my local coop
config i can come up here to this coop
config file button
in the top right you can't see my mouse
and here's the coop config file
for my user inside of rancher i can copy
this to the clipboard save it on my
local machine and now
all of my connections will be routed
through rancher this is what you want to
give
you would create user accounts or assign
users they would log into rancher they
would get their coop because big file
for their clusters and then that's how
they would connect
so back over to the default namespace
rancher doesn't hide anything it makes
things easier
so everything that i'm about to do well
you could do outside via the cli like we
already did it'll just show up here and
as you'll see in a moment
we can import yaml directly we can edit
the yaml directly
but let's just go let's do this wrap
we'll call this demo
i want a scalable deployment of three
pots
i want it to run menace rancher demo
i know that this listens on port 8080
and i want it to be a cluster ip service
and i know that i want the environment
variable of cow color
equals yellow but i could for example
add from secrets config maps you know
any other type of resource
in here but i just want that let's set
up a health check
so we want to check that slash returns
good on
port 8080 and
we could click this show advanced
options link in the bottom right
and set a whole bunch of other security
things and advanced stuff but
in most deployments you don't need to
set these things
and we'll just say launch this is now
going to go and spin up
three pods you can see that it created
the demo service for us so we don't have
to go and do that that's nice
and while those are spinning up let's
just create an ingress
we'll call this demo we're going to use
training dash a.cl.noc.us
we will point it at a service so we want
slash to go to the demo service
it automatically picks up the port and
we'll say save
ingress is active come back over here
those are still deploying that's
lame i don't know why it's not pulling
from the cache
uh but while that's happening then let's
go and note how you can get to the yaml
for
any resource whether you want to look at
it or whether you want to actually
change it you can make changes here and
they'll propagate out automatically
this is up so now if we just click on
this link
we have a site we got three replicas the
cows are yellow
you can see the little green badge
moving across them showing the load
balancing that's happening
and let's say that our client calls up
and they're like
our boss is allergic to the color yellow
no problem
we can come back in here and we could
edit the yaml directly if we wanted to
or we could edit the workload the thing
i really like
about rancher and wait wait wait
wait wait wait wait you can already see
that if you just
know how containers work you don't need
to know very much about kubernetes to
deploy
really powerful stuff because the ui
makes all of that really easy
and the last thing that i want to show
you today besides just highlighting that
rancher has all this day two stuff built
in
alerts logging monitoring notifications
pipeline system
horizontal pod auto scaling istio
service mesh
all sorts of stuff to make day two
operations are
the thing where it's like okay you got a
kubernetes cluster now what
so backups monitoring alerting workload
monitoring all of those
things were things that you would have
to go and figure out yourself
but you just want to use kubernetes so
we give you all of that stuff
it's all open source tooling that we've
just bundled with the product so it's
prometheus and grafana
and a stripped-down version of jenkins
and then notifiers
you can send logging to kafka and splunk
and and various other
back ends with our goal being let's get
you up and running as quickly as we can
so that you can then just go back and
learn the stuff on your own time
and the best example of that is the
application catalog
i told you that helm is the package
manager for kubernetes
so by default you can pull in anything
from the helm charts
but helm uses key value pairs and if you
want to deploy something you start to
kind of know a little bit about what
you're doing
let me describe a scenario i'm a
developer i'm building an application my
application needs to talk to hadoop
i don't really know anything about how
to deploy hadoop i don't know how to
deploy it in containers
certainly don't know how to deploy it in
kubernetes but my company's using
kubernetes
and you know most of all i just don't
really care
about figuring all of that stuff out
that's not my job my job is to build
this app
so rather than making it harder for the
people who are
using your cluster let's try to make it
easier
as a developer i come into rancher i
click this launch button over here
and i say hmm hadoop okay
instead of being presented with a blank
field that i have to put key value pairs
in
i'm presented with a form a form that
has
same defaults and that if i want to
change i can understand if i know a
little bit about how kubernetes works
like oh
do i need persistent volumes no because
i'm just going to build this and tear it
down so it's fine to have temporary data
all of this information is converted
into
variables that then get assigned into
all of these manifests that you just saw
here and they get applied to the cluster
we're on a little tiny one node cluster
here so i can't apply this
but i have applied it before it takes
about 10 minutes it builds a five node
hadoop cluster and it hands you back an
endpoint
so literally in 10 minutes your
developer me
can get back to work with hadoop cluster
focusing on the things
that i actually care about that's
one of many examples of how rancher gets
you moving faster everything you want to
do in kubernetes
you can do here if you can't do it in
the ui you can do it via the command
line
everything here that you see is actually
talking to the rancher api so you can do
all of this stuff programmatically as
part of your ci cd system
or whatever it is infinitely flexible
and infinitely powerful we have two
minutes left
and depending on how many questions we
have we don't have very many questions
we might finish close to on time
uh can k3s be made ha from one node
sort of it's a great question i
specifically said rke because rke is
built
using etcd as part of the cluster but
remember that k3s for ha functionality
points to an external data store
so if you have a master slave mysql
instance or postgres or a three-node scd
cluster
and a single node k3s cluster
then it's ha sort of
if you if you deploy k3s using the
internal sql sqlite data store then no
you can't
so if you want to deploy k3s but be able
to
grow it later basically you need to
deploy a single node k3s cluster that
points to
some external mysql and probably you
could
make that mysql running on the local
machine um if you just wanted to keep it
on a single node
and then if you want to make it ha you
would just move my sql out just dump the
database and restore it over here and
point it somewhere else
um which you can change on the fly in
k3s and then
you would make that mysql ha and then
you would scale up your k3s modes
uh can you use rancher os as a worker or
control plane rancher os
is our container based operating system
it's old
it's a little long in the tooth i
recommend that if you're looking to do
stuff now use k3s
and keep your eye on k3 os which is
still alpha
but it we're building it as a part of
the upgrade path
for rancher os fresher os is docker
based
and there's so many other container
engines out there like k3s uses
container d
that that it's important that we have a
solution that is
that that's more inclusive that's even
the right way to say it
a solution with more options
if you want to know more about rancher i
built the rancher academy
this is a an intensive hands-on
course that ends in a certification on
rancher
it's if you spend three to five hours a
week it'll take you five weeks but it
goes through everything about installing
rancher installing rke
making it ha and then all of the ways
that you use that to deploy and manage
kubernetes
clusters it's called the certified
rancher operator level one course
and it's completely free you can go to
academy.ranchour.com
and sign up for that i launched it in
may
we rancher launched it mma i finished it
and we launched it in may
we had more than a thousand signups the
first day and i checked the metrics this
morning
and we have almost 10 000 people
registered
and we've issued almost a thousand
certificates so it's very popular
and uh and will give you everything you
need to know about rancher
remember that you could join other
rancher users in
slack uh just go to slack.rancher.io
and if you do want to connect with me i
am the director of community and
evangelism i am here to help you be
successful
so you can find me on the rancher user
slack and then i
also have additional content
so for example here's the rancher
academy
there's the rancher youtube channel
which i was going to show you live but
like i said youtube has been
having issues uh here we have advanced
training on kubernetes master classes
these trainings end up there not all of
them but the ones that i think are
really good end up there
you can look at previous ones they're
all basically the same
rancher meetups it's a great place to go
for
intensive content not just about rancher
but about how to do things with
kubernetes and
rancher and then my youtube channel
uh you can find from adrian.goings.tv
and
about three weeks ago i started a daily
live stream called
coffee and cloud native every morning at
7 30 eastern i spend a half an hour
going through what happened in the
previous 24 hours in the cloud native
world
so talk about updates to major things
new releases for cloud software
tooling we end with a thing called the
tool of the day where i find some cool
thing that we didn't know about
it's a great place to go and learn about
what's going on in kubernetes and cloud
native so it's live i hope to see you
there
every morning get up drink some coffee
and we're off to the races
so let's
come back and see all right we have no
more questions so
okay so that's it i want to thank you
all very much for coming
and i hope that i will see you
in the future at a kubecon or
something i don't know when we can all
get together and hang out again i'm
really looking forward to meeting you
all
i'm here to help you be successful let
me know how i can help
welcome to kubernetes we'll see you all
later
you