hey everybody welcome to today's
kubernetes masterclass really happy to
have you all join us today as we go
through monitoring and alerting with
communities from Griffin we have a lot
of people joining today and so we're
just getting started while you all are
arriving I want you all to know that
this session is being recorded you will
get the the recording and the slides
after the training we're doing
everything live here we have about an
hour hour and a half with you all so if
you need to drop don't worry you will
still get the recording and the slides
after we have a lot of material to go
through so I'm gonna go ahead and jump
right in here so as a way of
introduction on Matthew Shearer a
marketing manager here rancher I host
these training sessions and and others
which we'll talk about in a moment I
mean you can kind of use me as a point
of contact at Rancher if you are looking
for educational resource maybe an e-book
or you know one of these recordings or
something like that for whatever reason
you don't get the slides afterwards
please reach out to me at Matthew
Rancher comm or you can reach me on the
user slap just simply at Matthew there
and I'll talk a little bit more about
that as well but the man who's really
gonna be doing the heavy lifting on the
line today is amen amen are you there I
am here to Jamie oh no I do yes sir
there we go excellent okay great got
scared for a second alright awesome well
I'll let a man a little bit more as we
go just want to get through a couple
other housekeeping items before we dive
into the material so as I said we have
about an hour
you know our 15 questions are absolutely
welcome we try to make these responses
to what you all want to learn my only
request is just try to as best as
possible keep it keep this your
questions you know on topic we do have
other kinds of trainings you'll enjoy to
kubernetes intro to ranch or you know
intro to other materials so if for
whatever reason is just off topic we
might refer you to another resource also
if you want your question to be private
just let us know otherwise we will ask
it or answer it
for the benefit of everyone there is a
very cool chat feature and GoToWebinar
so you put your questions there and you
know while Amon is presenting and going
through the slides demo I'll do my best
to answer questions in the chat and all
the other ones we'll leave to Amon to
answer you might pause during mostly
we'll take questions at the end as I
said this session is being recorded we
post everything on YouTube so please
check check out the rancher YouTube
channel there are a ton of fantastic
videos fantastic presentations you know
with links to the slides and the
manifests and you know all that good
stuff so Chuck do check that out we will
be posting this session there as well
and as I mentioned before the Rancho
user slacked waiting to get in touch
with cleen and many other Rancher
community members it's absolutely free
there's thousands of members and
hundreds of people asking and answering
questions they are every day including
rancher engineers so just go to slacker
rancher die oh there's a many different
channels on our user slack you can you
can join the master class 1-pound master
class if you want you know news and
updates about these master classes and
finally there's other upcoming trainings
I have him and I have you down for next
week to sort of yeah so that should be a
fantastic session as well understanding
and implementing service smash a lot of
people have you know won't want to use
service mesh and it is integrated in
Rancher so we'll go over that and then
the intro training which we do every
week is a fantastic place to get to know
kubernetes and getting to know the
rancher management server so that is
every Thursday including this one so
that is all I have so a man I'm gonna
pass this over to you go we can get into
the heart of the material and make you
the presenter and I will show my screen
here and hopefully everybody can see
that cool yeah that's good okay so
welcome everyone to monitoring and
alerting with Prometheus and go fauna
thank you for that great introduction
Matt as you alluded to I of course am a
man bomb and I'm a field engineer here
rancher labs been here for about a year
very happy at rancher a lot of awesome
stuff going on at the
organization I love doing these
presentations these master classes these
trainings you know every few weeks or so
I'm it's always fun to engage with the
community and be able to present things
that I'm passionate about or that I
learned about and want to share with
folks so to that here's what we're gonna
do today first off for those who aren't
familiar we're going to cover some
basics of what Prometheus and Griffin
are so I'm going to go over some basic
concepts of these tools will actually
walk through and deploy Prometheus and
Griffin interactively as part of this
demo and then we'll walk through what
Rancho brings to the table with doing
it's monitoring feature and how Rancher
can manage for me theist and Griffin in
two great components of those tools and
to the rancher product and things like
that so without any further ado let's
jump in oh and and as matt said earlier
please feel free to ask questions
there's that little question section in
the GoToWebinar the apply interview or
whatever you're using so we will either
get to those throughout the presentation
or at the end but I love questions love
answering them love engagements during
and after the fact so please ask away
okay Prometheus and Griffin Oh what are
they so first of all start off with
Prometheus it is a time series database
and monitoring system well what does
that actually mean
Prometheus stores metrics over a period
of time and I put metrics in quotes
because we'll need to describe what a
metric is so a metric is going to be a
value that's going to change over that
period of time so we will store those
pieces of information in Prometheus and
we will collect those from a whole
different bunch of sources Prometheus
allows us then to query these metrics
using an expressive language that
they've titled prom QL so what we can do
that is with Prometheus store bits of
information that change over time and
then query those bits of information
using that prom ql language Prometheus
also gives us the ability to generate
alerts based on criteria so if we have a
value that exceeds a certain threshold
or exceeds a lower threshold whatever
the word for exceed on the lower side is
we can generate alerts based on that
criteria we
also have the ability to export metrics
from nodes in kubernetes now Prometheus
it's important to stop a note here is
not just a kubernetes tool so Prometheus
and Griffin ax are independent pieces of
software so it is a time-series database
and monitoring system that while it
integrates really well with kubernetes
and as you'll see when we deploy it and
when we manage it with Rancher is able
to grab a lot of information quickly out
of kubernetes its sole focus is not the
kubernetes ecosystem so there's a lot of
ways to grab information from a bunch of
different sources grab metrics that is
from a bunch of different sources and
store those in Prometheus obviously
you're here today to talk about rancher
and talk about kubernetes so that's what
we'll be focusing on but just know that
with Prometheus I can grab metrics from
a whole host of different sources I can
grab them from sequel databases I can
put tooling into my actual code to send
metrics to Prometheus like if I write a
little application and I want to
directly send metrics into the
Prometheus database I can do that
so not entirely kubernetes focus just an
important note to make there but
obviously that's where we've spending
our time today gravano
then on the other side is the visible
excuse me visualization tool for those
metrics that are stored in prometheus
so griffons going to allow us to build
visualizations of Prometheus metrics
Agrafena is really meant for visualizing
Prometheus metrics but it also has a
whole host of other data sources that
you can import information from so as we
go through the demo of deploying
Prometheus and grow fauna I'm gonna walk
through importing the Prometheus data
source but know that we also have other
options for instance that graph on ax
can pull in data sources like my sequel
from elasticsearch from things like an
AWS like the I can't think of time I had
like RDS there are other data sources
you can pull Integra fauna and create
visualizations using so it's not just a
Prometheus integration but they are kind
of a match made in heaven
Griffon also allows us to build complex
visualizations from several data sources
so a really cool
feature about Cortana that I don't know
that will have time to get to today is
the ability if you want to create
visualizations that pull data from
Prometheus and then also incorporate
information from my sequel or
elasticsearch whatever
combine those together into single
visualization so you can start to pull
in data from across your organization
from different data sources and be able
to present that in one single pane of
glass so to speak
final point you can compile these
visualizations that we're making into
dashboards and other groupings within
Griffon a-- so when I say visualization
it's it's kind of a broad term what I'm
really referring to our graphs and other
ways to present data visually so that's
gonna be maybe dials graphs bar line
charts bar charts pie charts things like
that any way that when you have data and
you want to be able to express it
visually that's what we're talking about
when we refer to as visualizations here
so digging into Prometheus again it's a
time series database and as I said we're
tracking changes to a metric over time
we're gonna collect metrics from many
different sources and the two that are
really important to think about our
clients and exporters so when we talk
about clients what I refer to when I say
that is Prometheus comes with a whole
host of SDKs that you can integrate with
your favorite language and then build
Prometheus metric integrations into your
applications so for instance I do a lot
of golang programming there's a great
goal laying integration for Prometheus
where literally when you set it up out
of the box and just wire up the basics
of the Prometheus integration you get a
whole host of metrics that are being
collected automatically about the
performance of the go application so
this is going to be things like the
number of go routines memory overhead
the total memory space that's being
occupied
I'm CPU usage things like that you can
do that than in any of these languages
that Prometheus has a client for so
there's Python clients Java JavaScript
all over the place collect different
metrics about your application and then
forward them into Prometheus or rather
make them available for Prometheus to
scrape to use specific language here
the other way to collect metrics our
exporters so we're going to specifically
focus on some of the kubernetes
exporters today but Prometheus has the
ability to export metrics from a bunch
of different sources
when I say export versus clients here a
client is an integration with a language
that you will build in order to present
metrics that Prometheus will scrape so
you literally define the metrics for
collection
in your application code and Prometheus
will grab and store those metrics on the
other hand an exporter is sort of more
of a prepackaged tool that you will
apply to something that you want to
collect metrics from now exporters exist
for a whole host of different things
like obviously we're gonna focus on
kubernetes today but there are metric
exporters for things like sequel server
for things like Network Devices for log
aggregation tools a whole host of stuff
now if we take like a network device for
example we're not using a client in that
regard because we can't directly
integrate with a network devices code
but we can use an exporter as a
pre-built package to collect metrics
from that network device and make those
available to Prometheus so the
difference is a client is a direct
integration with the code you build it
into your application the exporter is
something we use for existing tooling or
existing devices to collect that
information and make it available for
Prometheus will also collect information
from our nodes so when we deploy
exporters using Rancher we're going to
deploy an exporter for kubernetes to
grab state out of kubernetes things like
I'm deployments and pods and secrets you
know grab information from what the
world looks like inside of the
kubernetes cluster but also will use a
node exporter to grab information about
the nodes themselves so this will be
things like vmstat and network
statistics disk utilization you know all
the things you would want to monitor
about an odor rather about an operating
system again we touched on Prometheus
has the ability to generate alerts that
are based on criteria these criteria in
Prometheus parlance are called rules so
rules define when an alert will be
generated we combine these alerts or
these rules with receivers now
receivers are going to tell Prometheus
where should I send this alert so by
default when Prometheus generates alert
it's not going to go anywhere we have to
actually configure a receiver in the
Prometheus configuration in order to
define for Prometheus where to send that
alert so jump in to Gravano and
apparently I don't have any cool slide
transitions here Gravano is how we'll
build visualizations of those Prometheus
metrics we will connect in this next
demo Gravano
to Prometheus and we'll build those
visualizations using prom QL queries as
I touched on before we can build
visualizations of other metrics so my
sequel is one of those example sources
but RDS is and other source we can pull
information from elasticsearch from a
whole host of places where data is
stored we can pull that into Gravano and
visualize those pieces of information
and then again finally we can combine
data sources to build complex
visualizations so we're not tied when
we're building these graphs and these
visualizations to just a single data
source like my sequel or a single data
source like Prometheus we can combine
these together and make really cool
visualizations okay
deploying Prometheus angriff on it is
super easy we're going to use help
charts hell charts make life super easy
or super complex depending on how do you
get into them but for this example we're
going to use Prometheus and Griffin I
deployed for your help charts which will
be super easy now configuring Prometheus
and Grenada is not so super easy now I
say not so super easy in that it takes a
lot of time to do this to build up these
configurations that will make sense for
your organization like what metrics so
monitor what visualizations to build
what things to see so that part is not
so super easy and I'm gonna go over
deploying Prometheus and Griffin here
and talk a little bit about what those
configurations look like but then we'll
be able to see how Rancher can make that
process easier by deploying and
configuring these things on our behalf
now before I do this we're gonna have to
start with everyone raising their right
hand so wherever you are in the world if
you're at work if you're at home if
you're in quarantine if you're in
isolation whatever raise your right hand
and repeat after me
i webinar attendee do solemnly swear
to hold a man Baumann responsible for
any mishaps that occur during this live
demo so how me kubernetes alright let us
jump in and deploy Prometheus and
Cortana so I will whoops
hit escape on that we will move that
window out of the way minimize that I
have running here a rancher instance two
three five as you can see down there in
the lower left this is my personal
instance of Rancher and I've got three
different clusters here but local
cluster is obviously or of course if
you're not familiar the one that Rancher
itself runs on top of so we're gonna
leave that one alone for today but I
have two other clusters that will play
around with a Rio cluster which I use
for playing around with in demoing one
of ranchers other excellent products Rio
and then I have a work cluster which is
just a generic name for a cluster that I
do work and other play around stuff in
the work cluster is where we're going to
spend a lot of our time in this section
of the demo so what we will do here is
go under the global drop down to my work
cluster and then to the monitoring
project if you're not familiar with
rancher projects projects are groupings
of namespaces with in kubernetes there
are a rancher specific concept and a lot
of providers have different words for
them our word is projects it's a way to
group namespaces together and give you
the ability to apply our back controls
as well as resource quotas and
limitations to that grouping of
namespaces as opposed to having to do it
on a per namespace basis so now we're
inside of this monitoring project here
what we'll do is go to the app section
apps is our apps our ranchers approach
to deploying helm charts it's not
prescriptive so you can use your own
method if you want to but for this
instance we can use apps as a simple way
to get to our Prometheus and graph on a
how arts stood up so what we'll do is
we'll launch in the upper right and
we'll go ahead and search for the
Prometheus chart here so type in
Prometheus all right we have the
Prometheus helm chart right here that's
populated from the upstream helm short
repository and what we're going to have
to start with is configuring a few
different bits of information about this
chart first of all this is the
your interface for deploying a help
chart so this is the interface you would
see when you use Rancher to deploy any
help chart at all so go ahead and edit
as yamo here and i've got a bunch of
different configurations that will drop
in so first off we're going to do alert
manager and we're going to turn off
persistent volumes since we're just
doing this demo we don't really care if
persistent volumes are turned on and in
fact I actually don't have a storage
class inside this cluster that could
satisfy that persistent volume so we'll
turn that off then we'll change settings
about the Prometheus server and I am
going to go over what these components
are and things like that in just a
moment we're gonna turn on ingress for
the Prometheus server so we'll do
enabled true there I'm going to use a
hosts declaration here and type in
Prometheus 1010 11 33 dot X IP dot IO so
since this is my private instance of
Rancher I have the setup at IP address
10 10 11 33 in my little mock data
center if you're not familiar with what
xip io is this is a tool that allows you
to create a fully qualified domain name
and as long as it includes an IP address
as the first section here before the X
IP dot IO whatever comes before that
then will be a fully qualified domain
name that results in 10.10.5.3 3 so in
this case Prometheus dot IP address dot
X IP dot IO will resolve to 10 10 11 33
quick and dirty way to get an F qdm just
like with alert manager we're going to
turn persistent volume off so persistent
volume enabled equals false and those
are the different options we're going to
have to set now so what I will do is hit
launch here at the bottom and we'll
watch as Rancher pulls in that helm
chart and then deploys it on to our
project now if I click on from easiest
here we can see ranch you're walking
through these different steps and here
are a bunch of different components that
are deployed with this Prometheus helm
chart we can alert ok so let me start
from the basics the Prometheus server is
where the core of Prometheus data
storage and collection is done so the
Prometheus server here has a couple of
different images that are deployed the
first is that little config map reload
image you can see that just reloads
configuration Maps when we change
Prometheus configuration the other image
that shown there is that prom
that's the core prometheus operation we
also have things like the Prometheus
alert manager in the slides before I
spoke about prometheus having the
ability to generate alerts based on
criteria the alert manager is the two of
them that's responsible for doing that
we also have prometheus cube state
metrics this is one of those exporters
that I was talking about
so the Prometheus cube state metrics is
an exporter that allows Prometheus to
grab information about the state of the
world inside of the kubernetes cluster
so Prometheus cube state metrics then
will query our kubernetes cluster and
make that information available to this
Prometheus instance the node exporter
then again as another exporter and this
one's going to be responsible for
grabbing metrics from the nodes that I
have in this cluster so again this is my
private cluster I've got three little
nodes in it and you can see right here
that there's these on 9100 tcp ports if
I actually click on one of these we can
see the metrics that are being generated
by this node exporter so right off the
bat if you remember I discussed when I
use the Prometheus client library I get
a bunch of golang application
information and here's some of that
stuff being shown here so like mem stat
heap things like that but if I scroll
down on this page I'm now exporting and
making available to Prometheus metrics
about this node itself so if we scroll
down here no network carrier up changes
total well whatever that means for the
Calico device that metric has now been
made available for Prometheus this
format is the format that Prometheus
uses to grab metrics from a source so
even though this is the node exporter
output this is what the output this
format with these helper sections here
and then the metric sections here this
is what the output looks like for any
application that's going to spit out
Prometheus metrics and that Prometheus
will scrape so I'll close that simple
example here and what we have happened
now is Prometheus 1010 11:33 has been
generated so if I click on that we get
brought to the Prometheus UI pretty
simple user interface and this will give
us the ability to explore what the
operational status of Prometheus looks
like as well as clear query some of the
metrics that we've got
and take a look at any alerts that have
been generated so first let's go to the
status drop down and take a look at
configuration this configuration is
being imported from a config map inside
of that kubernetes cluster that were
deployed on - so if we wanted to edit
this and change that config map real
order would take care of that for us
you can see there's a whole bunch of
different sections that have been Auto
populated here like scrape Conn fix the
scrape config allows us to define where
and how we're going to scrape metrics
from a particular endpoint so for
instance this job named kubernetes API
servers here we're going to scrape
Prometheus metrics from the slash
metrics HTTP endpoint and we're going to
collect that endpoint it's specified
somewhere here I can't find enough time
ahead but we will use the kubernetes api
server slash metrics endpoint to grab
Prometheus metrics for collection
there's a whole host of other
configurations we could go through but
just know that this is the basic
approach that Prometheus has for
configuring the tool back under status
let's take a look at targets here
targets is a selection or rather a list
all of endpoints that Prometheus is
scraping to grab metrics so you remember
when we were back in Rancher here and we
had these 9100 slash tcp ports for our
node exporters these are showing up here
so on each one of these I can click
actually I'm sorry those are the API
servers so these are my kubernetes api
servers on part 6 4 4 3 there those are
the slash metrics endpoint where if I
effected correctly to those I would get
metrics the node exporters are probably
lower down here here we go
10 10 11 33 here's the metrics endpoints
we were looking at so you can see that
these are target's for Prometheus to
scrape metrics from and that correspond
to that node exporter that we dropped in
there actually those are kubernetes pots
but the example still remains let's go
back under status and go to service
discovery Prometheus has the ability to
auto discover metrics from a bunch of
different sources so if I expand this
kubernetes pod section here within
kubernetes because of that cube state
exporter being available and
of a couple other configurations
Prometheus can autodiscover pods inside
the cluster now when those pods are Auto
discovered we can add annotations on to
the pods themselves in order to scrape
metrics from a particular end point so
when a custom Prometheus deployment what
I can do is on my pods annotate them
with some Prometheus annotations that
allow me to introduce me allow me to
declaratively tell Prometheus this is my
application here is the metrics endpoint
go forth and grab those metrics for me
last thing to talk about is under alerts
it's kind of a whirlwind tour I don't
want to spend too much time here because
the point is not about deploying
Prometheus itself right it's about you
know the integration alerts is where we
see any of the alerts that we had
defined and again an alert is an
instance of a metric cross metric
crossing a threshold we don't have any
alerts configured currently but if we
did and there were alerts configured or
they were you know firing or crossing
that threshold status they would show up
here so we can define those using
Rancher and I'll show you that later in
this demo and then we'll have alerts
show up in this interface by default
when Prometheus is installed on the
kubernetes cluster like we have
currently those alerts are configured
via config map so if I go back to
Rancher and under the resources
drop-down I go to config I actually have
my Prometheus server configuration here
and I can define my alerting rules as a
yellow statement here in this value
section of the config map we looked at
our configuration in the Prometheus
interface and this is where it's being
pulled from that Prometheus server
config map okay that's good enough for
Prometheus and that wasn't a lot of work
to get it deployed and honestly it's not
a lot of work to get it to start
collecting metrics especially in a
kubernetes cluster so much of those
targets so much of that service
discovery functionality is built in by
way of deploying that helm chart and
those exporters along with their there's
not a lot of extra work short of
defining these alerts
excuse me short of defining these alerts
that we need to do for setting up
Prometheus so let's go ahead and deploy
Griffin and take a look at what that's
like so go back to my apps interface
here and my monitoring cluster or
monitoring project we'll click Launch
and we'll search for Griffin oh well not
Grovner
perfect under the helm shark repository
here we'll grab ref onna and just like
we were doing before we'll add it as e
ammo and import a couple configurations
then we'll need first off again we're
going to enable ingress because graph on
ax is a visualization tool we obviously
will be enable to be need to be able to
see something here so we'll enable that
and just like before we'll do another X
IP dot IO thing
11:33 dot X IP dot IO then also in the
admin interface we will set up an
existing secret existing secret Ravana
what we're doing here is we're telling
Griffin actually open secrets we're
telling Griffin that there is a
pre-existing secret called Griffin ah
that has our admin credentials and I'll
show you the username is admin and the
password is admin so nothing too
mysterious there but we're telling
Griffin ah that's where the secret lives
to automatically configure the admin
username and password will hit launch
here and Griffin Oh we'll get started up
for us when I click into this
application then similar to Prometheus
will see the workloads being deployed
but Griffin doesn't have a whole host of
workloads that are going to be deployed
like Prometheus does with the exporters
and the alert manager Griffin is just a
single instance here that does our
visualizations now we'll wait for that
ingress rule to be created and once it
is we'll be able to open up the Griffin
interface and build our first
visualization based on those metrics
we've collected now that it has we've
got Griffin at 10 10 11 33 so I click on
that and here's our Griffin an instance
will log in with a basic admin admin
username and password wants me to change
password we'll skip that for the time
being and now here is a bone-stock
Griffin instance nothing's been
configured about it no changes have been
made
we just have Griffin installed at its
base so what we will do now is set this
up by add
being a datasource so we'll start by
adding a data source here and we'll
configure it to connect to Prometheus
now remember I talked earlier about
Gravano having the ability to collect
metrics from Earth scuse me visualize
information from different sources
Prometheus obviously at the top of the
list they kind of go hat in hand
together but we also have in flux DB
elasticsearch my sequel bunch of
different cloud sources like cloud watch
Oracle New Relic all these different
Enterprise plugins soukra fauna can
visualize things from a whole host of
different sources
we'll start with Prometheus and we'll
click select there and we'll need to
give it a URL all the configures gives
me all the communication with Prometheus
has done over HTTP so we'll do HTTP
colon slash slash and I haven't enabled
TLS otherwise we'd of course have a nest
there we'll put in Prometheus Meethi yes
- server dot Prometheus so this is going
to be in kubernetes a DNS resolution
parlance this will be the name of the
service the Prometheus - server service
inside the Prometheus namespace so if we
look in Rancher here resource go back to
the resources workloads service
discovery we have a Prometheus server
service inside the Prometheus namespace
so we've got that set up and because
we've done no other configuration about
Prometheus security anything like that
there's nothing else we have to change
we can just save and test data source is
working so we're good to go there
we'll go back to graph fauna we can
check off now that we've created a data
source so let's go ahead and create our
first new dashboard we've got a
dashboard and dashboards are comprised
of different panels now a panel will
allow us to define a visualization so
we'll choose visualization here and
let's say actually know what let's do it
by query first so enter a prompt ql
query and this prompt ql query dropdown
will auto populate with metrics that are
being collected in our Prometheus
instance so if I type a there for
instance and scroll down we've got a
whole host of different metrics that are
being Auto matched here so let's grab
API server request latency x' count now
if I add query we should see here
there's a little spinning circle up here
we'll wait for that to resolve a
visualization that shows us API server
requests latencies
now we don't have a lot of information
about these currently because we've only
been collecting data for about ten
minutes or so so I'll change my
drop-down here should last five minutes
and now that visualization looks a
little cooler I mean it's a little flat
but it looks a little cool maybe we'll
do something neater how about go
routines I kind of like this one
go underscore go routine so I had that
query or not add that career I don't
need to do that those will just show up
there gogo routines do I have to hit
enter maybe we'll leave oh sorry it
already visualized here
so go-go routines will show us the
number of go routines that are executing
for any of these different sources so
this engine X ingress controller
currently has there we go drop over here
90 go routines that are being executed
so Prometheus is excuse me storing these
metrics anchor fountas is pulling those
in and visualizing those for us so now
we've done that we'll go to the
visualizations section and we can change
some of the labeling options that we
have here so this section down at the
bottom is kind of silly right like we've
got the metric that's being collected
and then we've got labels that show us
different and pieces of information
about that metric so the metrics are
stored together go-go routines is one
metric inside out from me theists and
the labels help us separate the source
of that metric so we can see I've got
all these different instances here well
let's actually add a title for this
where do I do that general panel title
we'll say this is going to be go
routines okay so now we have a go
routines title let's change what these
labels look like down on the bottom and
in Griffin here and make that look a
little nicer so if I go to the legend
actually do I have to do that under
general I kind of forget off Tom my head
where I have to do that label right so I
think in the label section we can set
for the x-axis where do I want to do
this I remember not off the top of my
head how to fix this doo doo maybe it's
under Chris legend format right so in
the legend format we can define where
the source is for this so let's go
instance as the source for the legend
here now we've simplified the axis down
here so the source for the goal routines
is this so the source for the girl
routine is Ubuntu
for where the source with the go routine
is that end point maybe not necessarily
descriptive in this instance but gives
us a little bit better information than
if I deleted this and we've just got
that garbage feeding vomited there so
we'll leave that back in there the
instance section here and then we'll go
back and now we have our go routines
dashboard so I can click on any of these
change that visualization there and once
we're done I can click back excuse me
click back there save our changes and
now we have our first dashboard built in
Griffon a pretty easy to configure
pretty easy to get through all those
steps but there's a lot to know about
ingre fauna and a lot that we'd have to
configure in order to build some really
beautiful dashboards now obviously these
are all cloud native tooling so we can
do API is to integrate with this and we
can script creation of all these
visualizations but the fact still
remains that if you want to build these
dashboards from scratch there's a lot of
legwork that needs to go in ahead of
time so let me close this and we will go
back to our presentation so I'll jump
back to PowerPoint here so let's deploy
for me some Granof rafin oh well we just
did we deploy Prometheus when we
explored some of the basics of that
Prometheus tool now we saw how
kubernetes metrics were Auto imported
and again that was by virtue of those
exporters being deployed alongside
Prometheus so that keeps state exporter
the node exporter those metrics became
available because we deploy those
exporter tools we also discussed how
alerts could be created I didn't get a
chance to show you those but when we
walk through our next demo which is
deploying this with Rancher we'll be
able to see how those alerts are created
we also deployed graph on ax and we got
a chance really to explore the dashboard
in Griffin ax because it is such a
visual tool so we connected graph on a
to Prometheus we added our first
visualization of those go routines we
changed some labels we saved our
dashboard and we adjusted a few things
so that's what we just did however what
would we still mean to do now with
Prometheus we need to wire up metrics
sources from other things now a list of
cube State metrics here it comes out of
the box with the helm chart deployment
but if you're going to be deploying it
in a different way you may need to wire
up cube State metrics yourself and of
course also we may need to wire up
custom sources so if you have
application code that you want to
instrument or if you have different
sources like network devices firewalls
whatever
that you want to grab information from
you're gonna have to wire up those
sources independently we also have to go
through the steps of building those
alerting rules that we touched on
gravano of course what we would still
need to do we built a very simple
visualization but we'd have to define
all the dashboards and all the graphs
and all the visualizations that we need
and of course integrate Cortana with
other data sources okay so now that
we've seen the basics of how you deploy
for me theist and Griffin on how you
configure them let's take a look at
ranchers monitoring tool and see what
that brings to the picture so I'll click
here Rancher monitoring the next thing
to cover so Rancher monitoring Rancher
and I really wish I had some slide
transitions here because it would make
this a lot cooler and more dramatic as
these things slide in Rancher deploys
Prometheus and related exporters for us
so that we got out of the box with the
help track deployment not a lot to do
there but Rancher deploys Griffin and it
wires up through the Prometheus data
source for us now that may sound pretty
simple unless you get to the next step
where Rancher also configures
visualizations in Griffin ax so when we
deploy our monitoring feature in Rancher
we're going to build all those graphs
and all those pieces of information and
graph on ax programmatically for you so
you don't have to do all that stuff
we're also going to configure dashboards
in Griffin on your behalf and build
those panes of glass so you can see
different sections of information
rancher also has the ability to import
those graph onto visualizations into the
ranch or UI so in certain contexts
within Rancher again which we will see
you don't actually have to go out to
Befana to see visualization of your
metrics we will import those crucial
bits of information right into Rancher
itself Rancher also makes available
alerting configurations now these can be
configured either through the ranch or
UI or our API and I'll show you that
again but you can configure alerts and
where they're going to go so remember
that's going to be the rules and the
receiver section of Prometheus
configuration right from within Rancher
and I can do all of this with three
clicks so we're not counting yet telling
you all this stuff is nice but showing
you all this stuff is better I really
want this to be a demo heavy
presentation so
take a look and jump into that so I'll
export that and we'll go back to the
global context here within Rancher and
I'm going to first do little legwork in
this work cluster here by deleting the
monitoring things that we've just set up
I don't want to tax this cluster too
much just because it's my little home
demo cluster here so we'll delete
griffon and delete Prometheus that we
just applied and both of those two links
should clean themselves up and then
disappear here momentarily once those
have disappeared then we'll go ahead and
deploy monitoring so from the global
context we're going to start with our
three clicks in Rancher hover over the
upper left drop down here and we'll go
to the work cluster one click hover over
the tools drop down in the upper right
and go to the monitoring section two
clicks now this cluster monitoring
configuration allows us to change
different bits of information that we'd
like for the helm chart deployment
what's going to happen in the background
here is Rancher will deploy the
Prometheus and helm Prometheus and
Gravano helm charts on our behalf and as
I said in that slide before
automatically configure those tools so
we can set different options here and
when I scroll to the bottom here is my
third click enable hopefully that came
through I didn't hold the mouse up to my
mic but I hope you all heard that click
with that now we'll go back to the work
cluster into the system project and you
can see once we're in the system project
here that we have Prometheus stuff being
deployed all over the place we're back
in services let's go to work loads we've
got cattle Prometheus namespace so I've
got the Prometheus cluster monitoring
being deployed I've got from II theist
operator being deployed the alert
manager sections already been deployed
all this stuff Khurana is being deployed
on my behalf all these different things
are being set up some of these may not
fully satisfied cuz I think I left
persistent storage on but we will be
able to see an example of how this all
works
what happens now now this is going to be
kind of like a cooking show where you
know the cooking host takes the chicken
that you've prepared over the first 20
minutes of the presentation and they put
it into the oven and then there's a
commercial break and you come back and
the chicken is magically cooked right
that's what we're going to do in this
demo because we don't have time to wait
for Prometheus to collect all these
metrics so let's click on our real
you're here and tada the chicken has
been cooked so the dashboard page that
we were on earlier remember we were in
this work cluster in the dashboard page
it was kind of boring and plain here in
this real cluster now it has been
enhanced by the metrics we are
collecting from Prometheus so instead of
just having a tachometer here that only
shows CPU utilization because of that
cube State metrics and the node
exporters being available I can see use
versus reserve CPU here and same with
this memory dial all of these component
statuses here like at CDE the controller
manager the scheduler
these all have gravano icons associated
with them if I click on one of these
Gryphon icons like sed for instance
Rancher is going to proxy me to the
running gravano instance note that I
never left the ranch or URL we actually
just do a HTTP proxy to get you to this
graph on instance so now I can see
different visualizations about the
performance of NCD and all of this was
set up out of the box for me so distinct
duration memory client traffic peer
traffic in and out all these different
metrics came out of the box just by
virtue of enabling that monitoring
function if I wanted I have the ability
to customize these so on the lower left
I can sign in and in an instance of
graph on a deployed by Rancher the
default password is admin admin we don't
make things too hard now that that's
been deployed here I can go back to my
dashboard section and let's go to @cd
dashboard and my I can make adjustments
to any of these that I want
so looking edit Etsy D has a leader and
if it does we can set it to yes or I
don't know what graph QL looks like but
if I said not okay well change no value
anyways you get the idea but we can make
adjustments to the visualizations here
insight graph on ax there's a whole host
of other things being shown all these
dashboards were built out of the box
when we deployed monitoring nodes is one
that I like to show because it's got
such a great selection of information
so here's node information for 10.10 9
11.30 which is one of the nodes in my
REO cluster
I can see CPU and memory information
swap that's a lot of CPU load I should
probably take a look at that
but scroll down here on this page and
now we have vmstat information so I can
see memory pages I can see all this disk
detail that's been set up system detail
all these different bits of information
all these different visualizations that
have been wired up for me so we'll close
that now you remember when I was talking
in the slides about Rancher having the
ability to pull in these visualizations
into the rancher UI let's take a look at
that so if I expand at CD metrics here
on this page I can see these imported
visualizations from grifone ax so gr PC
client traffic shows up as a graph here
though that otherwise I would have to
click on this graph on a link to proxy
out and view that metric I can change
its drop-down and of course that
corresponds with Accra fauna drop down
in the upper right to see the time
period over which we'd like to visualize
these different metrics scrolling up
here let's take a look if I go into the
Rio cluster into the default project
another place inside Rancher we're
monitoring gets deployed Rio is a
project of ranchers it's an application
deployment engine there's a whole host
of presentations that I've given on Rio
you can find them on YouTube I'm sure
I'll give another one in the future
so not to talk too much about that but
just that Rio is deployed here in this
workloads page and if I click on one of
these tools like let's take the
autoscaler from Rio for instance this
workload metrics tab becomes available
inside Rancher so if I expand workload
metrics here there's more of these
visualizations that are being made
available but in the context of a
deployed application so for instance
here I can see the CPU utilization for
that autoscaler pod or the memory
utilization or packets per second or
network i/o or disk i/o or all those
different bits here and if I want to
click on graph an ax and head out to all
of the metrics that kafan is collecting
and visualizing for me here they are
available in Sanger fauna for the Rio
system namespace and my autoscaler
deployment so that's the other section
in which you'll see metrics being
deployed in the rancher interface now
one other cool thing to talk about
before we get into some of the alerting
stuff
that the monitoring capability is
deployable not only at the cluster level
but also at the project level within
rancher so what that means is currently
I have monitoring deployed in my real
cluster which is to say if I go under
tools and monitoring here we can see I
have monitoring enabled and if I were to
hit save I could upgrade any of these
changes that's at the cluster level so
what happens when you deploy monitoring
at the cluster level is metrics from all
across the cluster and every workload
inside that cluster those metrics are
going to be collected and visualized we
can do the same thing inside one of the
projects so if I go to the default
project in Rio and I go back under tools
and monitoring I could enable monitoring
at the project level now this won't grab
metrics from the nodes themselves but
this is really useful if you use Rancher
with our projects feature to create
multi tenant kubernetes clusters when
monitoring is enabled at the project
level you can give your tenants than the
ability to visualize and track metrics
and performance of their specific
workloads so workload because it were to
exists inside this default project and
if I enabled monitoring I could have
those workload metrics show up here just
for my workload without necessarily the
cluster admin having to give me cluster
level admin access ok let's talk a
little bit about a learning let's go
back to the Rio drop down here and we're
at the cluster level now we'll go to the
tools section at the top and click on
alerts alerts are powered by again that
Prometheus alert manager and in this
section this is how we will define alert
rules so Rancher makes it really easy to
define alert rules visually so what
we'll do is we can group first of all
our rules together so as you can see
I've got a bunch of different alert
rules that have been grouped here if I
add a new alert rule to one of these
groups I can define for the Prometheus
alert manager what criteria should
change in order to generate this alert
so that could be something very broad
like the @cd excuse me when a system
service at CD is unhealthy
two critical alert that's pretty generic
pretty broad right I can get a little
more granular and say okay when a node
like Ubuntu zero one has a CPU
reservation over 70% then send a
critical alert or now because we
monitoring excuse me because we've
enabled monitoring we have this
functionality available
I can click expression and then define a
Prometheus metric or a prom ql query in
here and grab any of those metrics that
we are collecting from that Prometheus
instance so we were talking about go
routines let's see if we can search for
that there go underscore go routines
we've got all of our different bits here
so I can select when any one of these
and I can do a filter operation here
like let's do service kubernetes so I
could do probably service equals
kubernetes and if I do that that should
change and show me just endpoints that
have the service of kubernetes probably
could change instance and get even just
one section here now if any of these
values that are greater than 5,000 as an
upper bound here for a five-minute
period or one hour or 24 hours or
whatever we will set a critical alert so
right within Rancher I'm leveraging
Prometheus as capability of defining
these alert rules but doing it so
visually and in the context of the
things I'd like too much excuse me
perform alerts on now again
alerts in Prometheus are only one half
of the equation we also need to set up
receivers so Rancher has you covered
there if we go under the Tools drop-down
and notifiers notifiers and are sort of
analogous in Prometheus two receivers
somewhat there's a little hand waving
I'm doing there but Rancher supports
these five out of the box so slack email
Pedro Duty and WeChat now note this is
not the full list of receivers that are
available in Prometheus these are just
the five that we have available right
now so let's take slack for instance if
I wire up a slack notifier here put in a
name the web hook URL set and able to
send resolved alerts whatever and hit
adds let's just throw in some garbage
there doesn't matter and hit add here I
can then connect one of these alerts or
one of
alert groups with that notifier so let's
say we edit this alert group and we want
to say that all of these alerts then
should go to another blahblah that slack
notifier in whatever channel let's say
opps channel now I save that and any
alerts that are generated are going to
my slack notifier so that process is
taken care of in hard prometheus
configuration by wiring up those routes
and receivers in the alert manager but
here we're calling them notifiers
and then connecting them to these alert
rules now back under notifiers here
you'll note we have four pretty generic
ones slack email page duty and WeChat
there's also a nice web hook option that
I wanted to touch on again this is an
alert manager functionality that we're
just bringing into Rancher but what's
nice about the alert manager excuse me
about the web hook functionality is that
if none of these notifiers are
functional for your organization you can
always define a custom web hook to
receive and then manipulate that alert
so for instance I've had organizations
who have had like a Microsoft team's
interaction for instance they were able
to build a little Python flask web
application that then would receive the
JSON of the alert at that web hook and
then forward that using teams api's and
send a team's notification so that's a
good example of how to wire up on ranch
or really alert manager notifications
with a tool that may not necessarily be
in that list okay that is that Rancher
demo so what we just did Rancher deploys
Prometheus anchor fana for us Rancher
sets up those metrics and visualizations
on our behalf and we saw that when we
walked through the refining interface we
had all those dashboards built all those
graphs and visualizations were present
now those visualizations are imported
into the Rancher UI and we saw how they
were done at the cluster level and at
the workload level so if you recall we
had that cluster dashboard page showing
us at CD performance I'm showing us node
metrics things like that but we also had
metrics imported and visualized at the
workload level showing resource
utilization of independent pods we can
configure alerting rules and notifiers
in the rancher UI an API which we just
walk through with creating
notifiers creating an alert rule and
connecting those two things together and
then finally monitoring is available
both at the cluster and project context
so if you set up a kubernetes cluster to
be a multi-tenant environment then you
can set up monitoring for both of those
contexts the cluster admin or a tenant
inside that cluster so what's next for
Rancher monitoring it's GA now so what I
just showed you was a set of
functionality that we've had actually
for about a year now
that came out in our 2.2 version which
was released I believe last April or so
so we're coming up on about a year now
that monitoring functionality has been
GA for quite a while what's missing from
it is the ability to create custom
metrics and persist them so when you
deploy monitoring in a rancher
environment you currently don't have the
ability to set up your own custom
metrics and collect them from your
application endpoints so for instance if
I build my own application and I use a
Prometheus client to export a bunch of
metrics from my application
you cannot currently with Rancher
monitoring siphon those metrics into the
deployed Rancher Prometheus instance we
are working on that though so I say soon
with a little TM I don't have a road map
or an estimated date for this but it's
something we're really actively working
on because obviously that's such a
crucial point to have is the ability to
collect your own custom metrics so it's
coming soon I put the TM on there is
just a funny little disclaimer but I
don't know when but we are actively
iterating on this and want to have that
ability into the Rancher product soon
finally multi cluster monitoring I'm
gonna put a little maybe and a smiley
face here currently within Rancher you
can deploy monitoring on a per cluster
or again per project basis now that's
great except if you're running 400
clusters and you want to have a cohesive
dashboard for all of those clusters we
are working on something with this so
multi cluster monitoring is a maybe I
don't know if it's gonna land I don't
know when or where or how it's going to
land but multi cluster monitoring is
something we're definitely playing
around with there's some cool projects
out there from Prometheus that make this
possible so we're exploring those
options so where do you want to where do
you want to get help if you want to
learn more where do you want
any of those things we have the rancher
user slack so please join us slack
rancher die Oh hop on there myself and
other fuel engineers and other actually
software and direct product engineers
are available in that slack channel so
post inside any of the public channels
get some attention from other folks
inside the Rancher community and of
course Rancher employees and engineers
themselves Rancher also has a super
active forum so this is one of the most
active forums I've seen in the tech
community short of like the MSDN or
whatever the Microsoft TechNet forums
the rancher forms are a super active
place to post for help
our engineers are in their daily
engaging with open source consumers with
enterprise customers folks who need help
we're doing product announcements all
sorts of stuff inside the Rancher forums
finally of course check out our github
repository
so that's github.com slash rancher slash
Rancher so again that's the Rancher
organization and the Rancher project or
rather repository all of our issues are
tracked there so if we have a sub
project like Rancher slash I don't know
monitoring for instance something like
that we won't track issues there we
track them directly a rancher slash
furniture so if you have issues if you
have feedback check us out on our github
repository github.com slash rancher
slash Rancher so thank you all for your
time
you can find me on github i'm github.com
/e bauman i'm doing a bunch of cool
stuff a cool thing called hobby farm a
couple other different interesting
projects i'm developing so please come
check those out come give me some
feedback on those you can find me on
twitter and aim and be if you have any
questions about this presentation and
the interactivity anything you want to
poke me about on Twitter find me there
at aim and be and then of course please
don't find me in real life that would be
weird and creepy and probably also not
allowed because we're supposed to
quarantine and stay six feet apart so
yeah thank you all for your time I
really appreciate it
Eamon thank you so much as Matt Matthew
heard the beginning of this presentation
a man awesome jobs so much territory
covered and unsurprisingly there are
there are a ton of questions and there's
hundreds of people watching right now so
popular topic so we're gonna try to get
through these as best we can just so you
know
yawn also joins another
our field engineers he's been doing a
great job answering questions in the
chat yeah we're gonna need a help
because there's a ton of question so
let's jump in here so here's this first
Michael who says would it be possible to
scrape individual metrics from other
deployments as well with integrated
monitoring let's assume for example I
install and nginx deployment and want to
scrape the metrics also to this ranch
remote monitoring
Prometheus install is that possible so I
think that question may have been asked
a little bit before I covered that we
don't have that ability so we're working
on that actively right now we can't
scrape custom metrics from application
endpoints it's just from those exporters
that come with our deployment so again
the node exporter and cube state and
things like that
we are working on that you are and I say
this to encourage the point not to
discourage your problem for billions
person to ask for it which is great and
that's perfect because that means it's
something that the community really
needs and really wants
I'm so we're doing active work okay
awesome thank you all right here's the
next one this is from Andres who asks is
there any chance of Windows metrics
support like with the WMI exporter
project
I definitely think there's a chance for
it but I hesitate to commit to anything
because windows support within Rancher
is both a new and be more on the limited
side so particularly with windows
containers they of course have to be
tied to the underlying OS version and
there's challenges with different tools
with having different components being
able to deploy to those windows nodes I
certainly think the WMI exporter is a
great project and it's it's something
God loved us to take on I just don't
know if we'll have it anytime soon
there's a lot of other stuff with
networking and container stuff left us
all first you know I hear some
background noise not sure if that's
defects your honor or whatever but just
say you know there's okay alright great
so uh making himself known I love it
okay so even here's the next one this is
from Sergio who asks can all of this
work on AWS Azure I'm assuming he means
for imported clusters yes
um so it'll work in both scenarios if
you import a cluster into Rancher so
that would be you know add cluster
import it'll work in that scenario and
it will also work in clusters that
you've built using hosted kubernetes
providers so if you use Rancher to build
an a chaos cluster or your user answer
to build any chaos cluster you can still
deploy Prometheus and go final
monitoring onto those clusters awesome
thank you okay here's the next one this
is from raju who says gives us a
scenario he says let's say I have
multi-tenancy setup using kubernetes
namespaces as logical separation can we
set up prometheus except to separate
each tenant each tenants data logs into
separate storage and groups and not MIT
mix the metric the metric and the app
logs and data
I'm gonna be honest and say I don't know
so I don't want to expound on a topic
and you know snow you and tell you
something I don't know I'd have to
explore and see if that's possible I I
would guess the Prometheus has that
ability in Rancher it's done on a per
project basis instead of a per namespace
basis so you you get isolation by virtue
of having two separate Prometheus
instances now if you're doing one
Prometheus instance with multiple
namespaces I'm not exactly sure how the
isolation works especially with regard
to our back so I would have to find out
and get back to you I don't know off the
top of my head and I'm sorry I don't
have a direct answer for you yeah no
problem no problem okay here we go
here's the next one this is from hi Mei
who says and you might have answered
this way says if you have running
Griffin an instance can it be integrated
with ranch or in some way unfortunately
not so at the current date if you have a
running Griffin instance it needs to
remain separate we can't sort of consume
existing instances with all the wiring
up that we do there's a couple different
reasons so first of all rancher needs to
know where everything lives easily and
have control over in case there
configuration changes we need to make of
Griffin to get it to integrate with
Rancher and not only that it just helps
with support variability too because the
money-making arm of Rancher really is
our support environment and our in our
excellent support staff and we need to
make sure that those folks can walk into
a known variable when they're gonna be
configuring and helping someone with
their monitoring deployment whereas if
crow fauna is independently deployed we
can't make guarantees about if being
deployed in a sane way or anything not
that you would screwed up or anything
just that you know with that support
variability we have to limit how those
are set up so it's actually feasible for
our support engineers to do their jobs
sure okay cool thank you all right
here's next one is from Lexie who asks
how do you add note names instead of
node IP address on dashboards so that's
gonna be by virtue of the metric that's
being collected you'll probably be able
to do a translation sort of operation by
you know if this label equals ax then
display Y right but that's all done by
virtue of the metric that's being
exported so for instance when we were
talking about those different targets
for metric collection some of them were
based on IP address because the node
exporter exposes a node port IP excuse
me a node port for that metric endpoint
and we address them by IP address some
of that is done by virtue of like let's
say the kubernetes cube state node
exporter or an exporter
let me I'm losing myself here some of
that is by virtue of the cube state
exporter which refers to notes on a name
basis so a lot of it has to do with how
the metrics are getting to Prometheus
but I believe there is some label
translation that can be done where you
say you know if X then Y for deploying
that sure ok yeah this is a business a
marathon so what will pace ourselves
these questions here this is from hope
I'm not watching your name is from the
all who says how do we align logging and
metrics for troubleshooting core fauna
is a great way to do that it is it 8 to
use the word observability because
reserve ability is such a large domain
of knowledge and such a different
concept than what we're talking about
here but with graph on a having a data
source of elastic search for example I
can align a query that will pull
information from Prometheus and from
graph on ax excuse me and from elastic
search using information that's common
to both of those data sources so for
instance one of those could be like
maybe I want to grab logs from a
particular node and correspond those
logs to CPU utilization on a node well
my query for exists for example in graph
on ax can pull Prometheus CPU
utilization stats for IP address
10.10.5.3 I could combine that with
another dashboard
excuse me another panel on a dashboard
that pulls log entries from a particular
elastic search index
maybe that indexes like Farah log syslog
and
we key it based on the IP address of the
node so I would query against 10.10 down
11 out 30 so then my dashboard would
have like I'm seeing this visually in my
mind here on the left hand side CPU
utilization over a period of time and on
the right the log entries for a period
of time then the unifying factor between
those two queries even though they're
from different data sources is the IP
address of that node 10.10 not 11.3 okay
awesome
thank you okay here's here's the next
one this is from Pankaj who asks can we
scrape any application pod or does it
depend on how the application is
developed in other words is it the
developer's responsibility to provide a
port or link for scrape to use for
scraping it's the developer's
responsibility so if we ignore Rancher
monitoring for a second and we just
think about Prometheus as an independent
tool it is the responsibility of the
application developer to integrate
Prometheus into their application now
that is if you want to see application
level metrics specifically if you just
want to see performance characteristics
of the app like CPU and memory and
things like that
of course that's tracked automatically
by that cube stain exporter but if
you're interested in application
specific metrics the developer needs to
integrate that Prometheus Client SDK
into the code in order to export the
metrics that you're interested in in
particular okay thank you ok here's the
next one in it you might not be able to
answer it because it's a bit complex in
the description but we'll try this is
from Jack who says here's the scenario I
have two deployments
I have deployment a and B with only one
replicas each usually each deployment
resource is limited to four geez memory
if load is coming in to a and a is
approaching four G can we trigger a cube
CTL to resize a to six gigs and reduce B
to two gigs for example
I'm going to say yes but I say yes
simply because all of the parts exist to
do that not because I have a particular
ranch or solution for it so the closest
thing that we have for that sort of
adjustment is ranchers horizontal pod
auto-scaling
which isn't really what he's looking for
that's just scaling up and scaling down
the number of replicas in a deployment
but all of the bits of information
exists there to write your own
integration to accomplish this so if I
were to do this off top my head it would
be something like a little gold
application that watches for utilization
against a particular pod and then using
kubernetes client go can adjust a
resource reservation on the two
different deployments that I care about
so you'd almost end up writing your own
controller for kubernetes it's a little
complex and if there are projects out
there that do this already and I'm sure
there are I'm just not aware of them
they're probably just to do but
otherwise you'd be writing your own
kubernetes controller to accomplish this
which sounds like a lot of work at the
outset but actually once you understand
how the controller runtime and framework
work it's not the worst thing in the
world to do so I think you really could
accomplish that if you spend some time
either with the operator pattern or with
Rancher zone we have a controller
library called Wrangler that could help
you accomplish this and basically just
piece together those different bits of
information yourself and set up that
automation now again if something exists
to do this and I'm just kind of you know
spouting here without knowing please I
encourage someone to let me know if that
exists cuz that's cool an interesting
problem okay sweet thank you alright
here's the next one
how would a migration from a dedicated
Prometheus and Griffin Isetta to the
ranchers build look like
unfortunately it really wouldn't work we
don't have the facilities in place to
perform such a migration you wouldn't be
able to retain the metrics between the
records between the Promethean
instances now one thing you could do is
once we have deployed the ability to
collect custom metrics you could have
that first Prometheus instance export
those metrics and have the second to
rancher Prometheus instance import them
there is that ability between Prometheus
instances sort of to query one another
but I don't have any migration ability
today it's it would have to be a fresh
deployment out of Rancher sure
okay no problem okay here's the next one
this is from Xavier Xavier who says does
Rancher have a dashboard for alerts or
do you need a graph on a dashboard for
alerts or can't have both I don't
Rancher does not have a dashboard for
alerts you would either need a graph on
a dashboard if you can build such a
thing I don't know if you can I I don't
I literally don't know it's on my head
or just rely on like a web hook to
receive those and display them in a
format that's convenient for you but
unfortunately we don't have a dashboard
that displays you know running alerts at
any given time sure okay no problem
alright here's the next one this and
this and if you need water
alright okay cool okay okay here's the
next one this is from Alexi he says how
would I add ingress metrics like 4x x +
5 5 X X errors to grow fauna that are
specific to a project if ingress is
common to several projects that's a good
one that is a good one huh I wonder how
you could do that because you would need
you might be able to do it based on the
hostname it would be a custom metric for
sure but you might be able to do it
based on the hostname or the path of the
incoming request so you probably have to
set up some sort of request logging
within nginx in order to get you know
that incoming request path and hostname
and everything but once you have that
entry you probably would be able to
query for entries of a particular host
name and again it would be super custom
and that's something that come
out of the box with rancher but I think
if you're able to query on a based on
the hostname
generated by that log entry out of nginx
you could probably accomplish that okay
cool cool
thank you okay this is I think you
answered this in your demo already but
he says how is installing prometheus by
hand different than enabling cluster
monitoring under tools and rancher so if
you're looking for a difference there
isn't a lot of one Prometheus is
deployed by own chart when I enable
monitoring inside Rancher and I'll see a
lot of the heavy lifting within
Prometheus is done for us and a lot of
that's done for us by virtue of the
exporters that are made available and
Prometheus at his own just really great
auto discovery capabilities when it's
deployed inside a kubernetes cluster so
really when we deploy monitoring in
Rancher we're not heavily customizing
Prometheus or anything like that
it literally is and and I can show you
if you're interested in another demo it
literally is deploying that prometheus
helm chart and then the real heavy
customization comes in with them
configuring alerts and notifiers and
receivers and things like that but but
otherwise you're right there's not a lot
of a big difference it really is just
that helm chart deployment okay sweet
thank you okay let's see here's the next
one this is from Randall who says if you
use the ranch or sto integration I
noticed that you get monitoring with
Prometheus and grifone as a side effect
is that the payload you get along with
Sto mostly the same as what you get by
doing monitoring as as you demoed yes so
if you enable it you know in Rancher it
literally calls Rancher API to deploy
monitoring so it's not that it's similar
it's literally exactly the same as
deploying cluster monitoring and rancher
we combine those two because in order to
do certain aspects of sto functionality
you need Prometheus and Ravana so it
just made sense to deploy our own
monitoring for that but it's literally
exactly the same is going to cluster
level monitoring and hitting enable you
to
do it by virtue of okay great thank you
awesome all right here's the next one
what KPIs and metrics come out of the
box already to find it for a rancher RK
and by environment do we get a default
set of dashboards for example so with
the monitoring deployment you definitely
get a default set of dashboards in
Rancher and I encourage you to to deploy
Rancher it's a single node docker
container instance and then try
deploying monitoring if you've got the
resources available and see what those
dashboards are we surface a lot of
information in them some of it may not
make sense for your organization but a
lot of it is important stuff like on
Etsy DS G RPC rates Etsy keys rat for
puzzles no metrics like CPU things like
that those are kind of obvious KP
there's not obvious performance we have
those available in core fauna when it
comes to specifically so I'm kind of
taking this as a two-part question when
it comes to ranch or tooling
specifically like rancher it's dolphin
rke those tools don't have a lot of
metrics exported currently they were
built
Rancher was built and archaea was built
kind of before Prometheus had taken hold
as the default in our sort of
conventional way to export and collect
metrics from tooling and I I don't want
to gloss over but just haven't gone back
and really implemented it after the fact
attention more than exporting those
metrics that's not to say that we won't
go back and add those pieces of
functionality I think that's a very
valuable exercise but with the workload
that we have on a lot of other stuff
which haven't up till now so kind of a
two-part question there you know we
deploy a lot of dashboards by default
with monitoring I encourage you to take
a look at them because there are some
pretty obvious and some not so obvious
dashboards and KPIs that are being
visualized there but the rancher
products themselves don't export a lot
of metrics okay cool thank you
okay here's the next one this is from
Mohammed who says I've imported a
cluster to rancher that CD is not being
monitored Griffin has enabled in the
scheduler and controller manager but the
graph has no date no data any idea what
issues might be might be um I can fathom
a guess and it may be that on imported
clusters because we don't know how add
CD was set up finding those endpoints
and being able to directly monitor them
isn't the easiest it sounds simple but
it isn't the easiest thing in the world
that may just be a feature that lacks
inside imported clusters for monitoring
imported clusters have the additional
headache of not being able to do it CD
snapshots or any of that sort of thing a
lot of it also has to do with the
variability in which a CD can be
deployed in imported clusters like for
instance a perfectly valid deployment
method of kubernetes is to have a
completely external at CDE data store
now with our ke we deploy at CD as a set
of containers on to the nodes themselves
and because we have control over that we
can deploy the certs necessary for it C
communication and things like that
we don't have access necessarily to
those with an imported cluster so it's
almost really hard actually to to cover
all the bases in all the different ways
that kubernetes could be opted up to n
CD and imported clusters but I think it
was easier at the time to just say no
we're not gonna export at CD metrics you
know and collect them with commedia s--
okay okay cool
all right couple more we'll take we're
near the end of our scheduled time and I
want to be respectful of your time Eamon
so take a couple more I think we've
gotten to many many of the questions
John thank you so much again for jumping
on here and answering some it directly
in the chat thank you okay next one yeah
here's the next one this is from Steve
who says is another troubleshooting
question he says I saw in quotes
monitoring API is not ready in the top
right corner on my rancher 2.3.4 so
Ravana has disappeared how do I enable
it monitoring API is not
typically indicates an issue with either
and this is the most common instance
with grief is being deployed itself go
into your system project inside that
cluster and take a look at previous
deployment I think you may find that
there are issues with that deployment
such that the Prometheus API isn't
available and you'll probably have some
things to resolve there like for
instance if people persistent volumes
and persistent volumes aren't aren't
available in your cluster that
monitoring API won't ever become ready
because the Prometheus deployment is
never healthy right so go into that
system project take a look at that
Prometheus deployment I think you might
find some issues there ok sweet awesome
alright let's see more questions
this one is from Steven you ask what are
the monitoring layers of Griffin oh I
guess I'm not sure what that what that
question really means monitoring layers
there's a few different pieces to
gravano so there's the dashboards which
are collections of graphs there are
graphs which are visualizations of
metrics and those metrics come from
different data sources and data sources
are where the metrics are stored so I
guess in that that layer approach and
you have a cron instance and you connect
Ravana to data sources and data sources
will be things like of course Prometheus
but then sequel and elasticsearch and
things like that thank you there you can
build visualizations nose then
visualizations dashboards which are just
collections of those visualizations and
a way to display them in the griffon
interface I hope that's the answer the
person is looking for it was kind of
hand waving my part yeah no no no
problem ask us again if you if you need
or jump on one slack to ask more let's
see I think we'll take one more question
this is from raju who says is there
support and i'm assuming he means in
this in this amount of monitoring i've
been talking about is their support for
apps running on on net core three net
core three
with Rancher specific monitoring that's
gonna be another one of those cases were
supporting custom metrics yet now does
have the ability to collect metrics um
and I I'm almost a hundred percent sure
you know what actually I'm sharing my
screen let's take a look together and
find out because I believe that is the
case me do to do yes it's a great
tragedy monitoring system so we go Docs
we go instrumenting client libraries yes
so dotnet c-sharp there is a Prometheus
dinette client library so we can pull
metrics from within done and
applications know whether this is just
standard net or this is that core I
can't tell you okay look at that targets
down that courts before no so you would
be able to collect metrics from inside
your dotnet application now that's
Prometheus functionality specifically
Rancher again doesn't have that custom
metrics option yet but what it does it
will be able to take advantage of that
application endpoint awesome thanks so
much Tim okay well I think we'll we'll
end it there because we're just we're
just right at our time and there's a
couple of questions that we haven't
quite gotten to so please ask them come
on slack reach out reach out to us there
anything else you want to share with us
Eamonn before we wrap up only that ranch
has got a lot of other cool stuff in the
pipeline and other projects that are not
our core Rancher offering I mean we're
we're well known of course for our
namesake product you know the rancher
tooling to deploy Prometheus or excuse
me deploy kubernetes clusters but we
also have a lot a lot a lot of other
cool stuff going on projects like k3s
k3o has projects like Rio we're
deploying all sorts of different things
in the open-source community and I
really encourage you to check out the
work that we're doing on our
organization so github.com slash rancher
there's a whole host of projects
underneath there as well as different
engineers in the organization are
building their own open-source tooling
so we are
huge contributor literally 99% of the
things we do are open source so check
out everything to do with the rancher
ecosystem awesome thanks so much hey man
okay I think we'll end it there thanks
again everybody thinks your
participation fantastic questions keeps
us on our toes and if your question did
not get a there were quite a few that
came in please reach out to us on slack
or email we're happy to respond and you
know participate however we can help you
um yon thanks again as well and like I
said this session was recorded so we
will be posting the recording on YouTube
we'll be emailing it to you as well
along with the slides and any other
files that Amon wants to include and and
that's it thanks everybody we'll see you
on the next training alright have a good
week thanks everybody
take care